<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY standard "Working Draft">
<!ENTITY tracker "http://sourceforge.net/tracker/">
<!ENTITY RFE "&tracker;/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;">
]>

<article status="&standard;">

<articleinfo>
<productname>wd-docbook-simple</productname>
<productnumber>1.1b1</productnumber>

<releaseinfo role="product"><ulink url="wd-docbook-simple-1.1b1.xml">XML</ulink></releaseinfo>
<releaseinfo role="product"><ulink url="wd-docbook-simple-1.1b1.html">HTML</ulink></releaseinfo>
<releaseinfo role="product"><ulink url="wd-docbook-simple-1.1b1.pdf">PDF</ulink></releaseinfo>

<releaseinfo role="location">http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/specs</releaseinfo>

<title>The Simplified DocBook Document Type</title>

<authorgroup>
<editor>
  <firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname>
  <affiliation>
    <shortaffil>Sun</shortaffil>
    <orgname>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</orgname>
    <address><email>Norman.Walsh@Sun.COM</email></address>
  </affiliation>
</editor>
</authorgroup>

<pubdate>21 Dec 2003</pubdate>

<copyright><year>2001</year><year>2002</year><year>2003</year>
<holder>OASIS Open, Inc. All Rights Reserved.</holder></copyright>

<abstract>

<para>Simplified DocBook is a subset of
<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/">DocBook XML V4.2</ulink>.
It is a
a general purpose XML document type suited to articles about computer hardware
and software (though it is by no means limited to these applications).
</para>
</abstract>

<legalnotice role="status"><title>Status</title>

<para>This is a working draft constructed by the editor. It is not
an official committee work product and may not reflect the consensus
opinion of the committee.</para>

<!--
<para>This Committee Specification was approved for publication by the
OASIS DocBook Technical Committee. It represents the
consensus of the committee. Comments on this document may be
sent to
<ulink url="mailto:docbook@lists.oasis-open.org">docbook@lists.oasis-open.org</ulink>.
</para>
-->

<para>Please send comments on this specification to the
<email>docbook@lists.oasis-open.org</email> list. To subscribe, send
an email message to
<email>docbook-request@lists.oasis-open.org</email> with the word
<quote><literal>subscribe</literal></quote> as the body of the
message.
</para>

<!--
<para>The errata page for this specification is at
<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/specs/simple-errata.html"/>.
</para>
-->

</legalnotice>

</articleinfo>

<section id="s.intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>DocBook is general purpose document type particularly well
suited to books and papers about computer hardware and software
(though it is by no means limited to these applications).
</para>

<para>Simplified DocBook is an attempt to provide a proper subset of
DocBook that is simultaneously smaller and still useful. Its original
genesis was a desire to make <quote>the HTML subset of
DocBook,</quote> that is, a subset that had roughly as many tags as
HTML and roughly the same descriptive power.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="mailto:docbook-tc@oasis-open.org">DocBook
Technical Committee</ulink> maintains the Simplified DocBook schema.
Simplified DocBook is officially available as an <xref linkend="xml-rec"/> Document Type
Definition (DTD).</para>

<para>The Version 1.1 release is based on DocBook V4.3.</para>

<para>The DocBook Technical Committee welcomes bug reports and
requests for enhancement (RFEs) from the user community. The current list
of outstanding requests is available through the
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</ulink>
<ulink url="&tracker;/?atid=384107&amp;group_id=21935&amp;func=browse">tracker</ulink>
interface. This is also the preferred mechanism for submitting new requests.
Old RFEs, from a previous legacy tracking system, are
<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/old-rfes.html">archived</ulink>
for reference.</para>

</section>

<section id="s.terminology"><title>Terminology</title>

<para>The key words <glossterm>must</glossterm>, <glossterm>must
not</glossterm>, <glossterm>required</glossterm>,
<glossterm>shall</glossterm>, <glossterm>shall not</glossterm>,
<glossterm>should</glossterm>, <glossterm>should not</glossterm>,
<glossterm>recommended</glossterm>, <glossterm>may</glossterm>, and
<glossterm>optional</glossterm> in this &standard; are to be
interpreted as described in <xref linkend="rfc2119"/>. Note that for
reasons of style, these words are not capitalized in this
document.</para>

</section>

<section id="docbook">
<title>The Simplified DocBook Document Type V1.1b1</title>

<para>The Simplified DocBook document type is a subset of
<xref linkend="bib.docbook43CR2"/>.
It is distributed from the
<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/">DocBook site</ulink> at
<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/">OASIS</ulink>.
</para>

<section id="usage">
<title>Usage</title>

<para>To use this document type, specify the public and system identifiers
in your document type declaration. For example:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.1b1//EN"
                  "http://docbook.org/xml/simple/1.1b1/sdocbook.dtd">]]></screen>

<para>Naturally, you can include an internal subset if you wish.</para>

<para>To incorporate this module into a higher-level customization layer, use the
public and system identifiers of this module's customization layer in your own. For
example:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE % sdocbook PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML Customization V1.1b1//EN"
                  "http://docbook.org/xml/simple/1.1b1/sdocbook-custom.dtd">
%sdocbook;]]></screen>

</section>
</section>

<section id="s.changes">
<title>Changes in Simplified DocBook V1.1b1</title>

<para>Simplified DocBook V1.1 is based on DocBook V4.3. It introduces
HTML tables but no other additional markup.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Release Notes</title>

<para>None.</para>

</section>

<appendix id="a.committee" role="non-normative">
<title>OASIS DocBook Technical Committee</title>

<para>The following individuals were members of the committee during
the formulation of this &standard;:</para>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem><para>Jeff Beal</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Steve Cogorno</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Paul Grosso</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Dick Hamilton</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Nancy Harrison</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Scott Hudson</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mark Johnson</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Larry Rowland (prospective)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Michael Smith</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Bob Stayton, Secretary</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Norman Walsh, Chair, Editor</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</appendix>

<appendix id="a.notices">
<title>Notices</title>

<para>Copyright &#169; 2001, 2002 OASIS Open, Inc. All Rights Reserved.
</para>

<para>OASIS takes no position regarding the validity
or scope of any intellectual property or other rights
that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation
or use of the technology described in this document
or the extent to which any license under such rights
might or might not be available; neither does it represent
that it has made any effort to identify any such rights.
Information on OASIS's procedures with respect to rights
in OASIS specifications can be found at the OASIS website.
Copies of claims of rights made available for publication
and any assurances of licenses to be made available,
or the result of an attempt made to obtain a general
license or permission for the use of such proprietary
rights by implementors or users of this specification,
can be obtained from the OASIS Executive Director.</para>

<para>OASIS invites any interested party to bring to
its attention any copyrights, patents or patent applications,
or other proprietary rights which may cover technology
that may be required to implement this specification.
Please address the information to the OASIS Executive
Director.</para>

<para>This document and translations of it may be copied
and furnished to others, and derivative works that comment
on or otherwise explain it or assist in its implementation
may be prepared, copied, published and distributed,
in whole or in part, without restriction of any kind,
provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph
are included on all such copies and derivative works.
However, this document itself may not be modified in
any way, such as by removing the copyright notice or
references to OASIS, except as needed for the purpose
of developing OASIS specifications, in which case the
procedures for copyrights defined in the OASIS Intellectual
Property Rights document must be followed, or as required
to translate it into languages other than English.</para>

<para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual
and will not be revoked by OASIS or its successors or
assigns.</para>

<para>This document and the information contained herein
is provided on an <quote>AS IS</quote> basis and OASIS DISCLAIMS
ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT
LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION
HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES
OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</para>

<para>OASIS has been notified of intellectual property
rights claimed in regard to some or all of the contents
of this specification. For more information consult
the online list of claimed rights.</para>

</appendix>

<appendix id="a.ipr">
<title>Intellectual Property Rights</title>

<para>For information on wether any patents have been disclosed that may be
essential to implementing this specification, and any offers of patent
licensing terms, please refer to the Intellectual Property Rights section
of the DocBook web page
(<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/"/>)
</para>

</appendix>

<appendix id="a.revhistory">
<title>Revision History</title>

<para><revhistory>
<revision>
<revnumber>1.1b1</revnumber>
<date>21 Dec 2003</date>
</revision>
</revhistory>
</para>

</appendix>

<bibliography id="bibl"><title>References</title>

<bibliodiv><title>Normative</title>

<bibliomixed id="xml-rec"/>
<bibliomixed id="rfc2119"/>
<bibliomixed id="bib.docbook43CR2"/>

</bibliodiv>

</bibliography>

</article>
