<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="Audience"><title>Audience</title><para>This book is for people who want to publish DocBook XML files using the DocBook
        XSL stylesheets. It is a "how to" guide that gets you up and running quickly, and
        then provides the details you need to gain access to the full power of DocBook. The
        book covers:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Obtaining and setting up XSL tools and the DocBook XSL stylesheets.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Using the built-in options to control the XSL stylesheets.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Customizing the XSL stylesheets to match your design needs.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>(This book does not cover the SGML version of DocBook, nor the DocBook DSSSL
        stylesheets.) </para><para>You do not need to be an XML expert to use DocBook XSL. You will need to know
        about XML elements and attributes, since you will be working with DocBook XML files.
        And you will need to know how to execute commands by typing them on a command line
        rather than through a point-and-click interface. If you know nothing about XSL, you
        can still use the stylesheets to generate high-quality output. You can also
        customize to a degree using the built-in stylesheet parameters. Learning some XSL
        will enable you to more fully customize the output. This book can teach you basic
        XSL, and provides dozens of examples that you can use and learn from.</para><para>This book will not show you how to write DocBook documents. The best reference for
        writing in DocBook is <citetitle>DocBook: The Definitive Guide</citetitle> by Norman
        Walsh. That book has been made available by O'Reilly Books for reading from the web
        at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://docbook.org/tdg/en/html/docbook.html"/>. Keep that link
        bookmarked for future reference. A printed and bound version of the book is also
        available from O'Reilly Books, but it is a bit out of date now. The online book
        documents the most recent version of the DTD.</para></topic>
