<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="HowOrganized"><title>How this book is organized</title><para>Applying an XSL stylesheet to an XML file is a very straightforward process,
        once you get the tools working. <emphasis role="bold">Part I</emphasis> of this
        book tells you how to obtain and set up the XSL tools. It covers several XSL
        processors, and provides essential details for each one. It also covers XML
        Catalogs, which are used to map file references to actual directory locations on
        your system. XML Catalogs make the tools more versatile and portable.</para><para> Once you have the tools working, you can generate formatted print and HTML
        output from your DocBook XML documents. As you use the stylesheets, you will
        probably want to change certain aspects about the format or processing. The
        DocBook stylesheets provide a large number of options. The options are in the
        form of stylesheet parameters, which let you assign a value to a named variable
        that is used in the stylesheet. You can do quite a bit of customization of your
        output using just the parameters. <emphasis role="bold">Part II</emphasis> of
        this book describes the various stylesheet parameters and how to use them. </para><para>You will turn to <emphasis role="bold">Part III</emphasis> when you want to
        change something but you cannot find a parameter to do it. At that point you
        will need to do some stylesheet customization, which is done using the XSL
        language. You'll need to learn the syntax and methods of XSL, so that you can
        write a customization file with it. The chapters in Part III describe the
        methods of customization, as well as many applications for HTML and print
        output. You can use the appendix introducing XSL  to get started with XSL, but it
        is beyond the scope of this book to teach you all about XSL. You will need a
        good XSL reference book to create extensive customization. You can also use
            the appendix on debugging XSL  for help with debugging your
        customizations.</para><para><emphasis role="bold">Part IV</emphasis> of this book covers all of the
        special features of DocBook that require extra attention. That part is an
        encyclopedia of special topics, from bibliographies to websites. Use it as a
        reference when you need to process a certain feature, or browse it for new
        possibilities that you did not know DocBook could do.</para><note><title>Note on examples</title><para><indexterm><primary>backslash</primary><secondary>in examples</secondary></indexterm>Some examples of commands and code in this book are too long to
            fit on one line. Where a long line is broken to fit, the line will end with
            a backslash character "\". If you are using Microsoft Windows, you should
            omit the backslash character and join such a line to the following line. If
            you are using a Unix shell, you can use the example "as is".</para></note></topic>
