<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="introchapter"><title>Introduction</title><para>The <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/">
                <citetitle>Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL)</citetitle>
                </link> is a formal Recommendation put forward by the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org">World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</link> as a language
        for expressing stylesheets. It complements the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/XML/">
                <citetitle>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</citetitle>
                </link> by providing the methods for formatting content written in XML. One of the
        major goals of XML was keeping content and its semantic markup separate from its
        formatting, so that formatting could be applied independently. An XSL stylesheet
        describes the formatting that can be applied to XML files using an XSL processor.
        The XSL standard and XSL processors are described more fully in <xref linkend="XSLprocessors"/>.</para><para>The DocBook XSL stylesheets were written by Norman Walsh to help people publish
        their DocBook content with XSL. The stylesheets are now an open-source project
        maintained on <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook/">SourceForge</link>. The stylesheet distribution consists of a collection of
        modular XSL files that are assembled into several complete XSL stylesheets. There is
        a stylesheet for generating a single HTML file, and one for generating multiple
        smaller HTML files from a single DocBook document. There are stylesheets for print
        output, XHTML output, HTML Help output, and JavaHelp output. The stylesheet
        collection is freely available for download. Since there are XSL processors for all
        major computer types, you can use DocBook on Unix, Linux, Windows, and Macintosh
        computers.</para><para>This book shows you how to use and customize the DocBook XSL stylesheets. It
        unlocks the power of these stylesheets by documenting all of their features and
        making them easy to use.</para></topic>
