<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="OnlineResources"><title>Online resources for finding solutions to problems</title><para><indexterm><primary>online resources</primary></indexterm>If you run into problems with the DocBook XSL stylesheets that are
            not addressed anywhere in this guide, you can use a number of online resources
            to find solutions. <itemizedlist><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>mailing lists</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>docbook-apps mailing list</primary></indexterm>First try searching the archives of the <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem> mailing list for
                        keywords related to the problem. There is a good chance that someone
                        else has run into something similar. Archives of the list are
                        available at two different sites: an <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook-apps/">archive
                            at OASIS</link> (which also hosts the actual mailing list) and
                        an <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sources.redhat.com/ml/docbook-apps/">archive
                            at Red Hat</link>.</para><para>If, for example, you are seeing a specific error message, trying
                        cutting and pasting the error message (or some part of it) into the
                        search form for the mailing list archives.</para></listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>chat channel</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>IRC channel</primary></indexterm>You can get help in real time on the <systemitem role="channel">#docbook</systemitem> channel on <systemitem class="fqdomainname">irc.openprojects.net</systemitem>. If your
                        browser supports IRC URLs (or, like Mozilla, has a built-in IRC
                        client), you can access the channel by entering the following URL in
                        your browser: <blockquote><simpara> <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="irc://irc.openprojects.net#docbook"/> </simpara></blockquote>
                    </para></listitem><listitem><para>If you cannot find a solution in the <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem> or on the
                            <systemitem role="channel">#docbook</systemitem>, you should try
                        posting a question to <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem>. To subscribe to the list, send a
                        message from your email account to: <blockquote><simpara> <email>docbook-apps-subscribe@lists.oasis-open.org</email> </simpara></blockquote> To post a message to the list, send it to: <blockquote><simpara>
                    <email>docbook-apps@lists.oasis-open.org</email> </simpara></blockquote>
                    </para><para>Please read the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/mailinglist/guidelines.html">list guidelines</link> first, and to include examples of your
                        DocBook source document and your output (for example, HTML or FO
                        output) along with details about the tools you're using (including
                        version numbers of the tools). <note><simpara>Do not include attachments when you post to <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem>—the mailing
                                list management software automatically strips out
                                attachments. If you have a long example or an output format
                                that you cannot paste into your message, post it to a Web
                                site, and then include the URL in your message to the
                                list.</simpara></note> </para></listitem><listitem><para>The <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://wiki.docbook.org">DocBook Wiki</link>
                        website collects contributions from DocBook users and makes them
                        available to the world.</para></listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>SourceForge</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>DocBook</primary><secondary>SourceForge</secondary></indexterm>If you find something that seems to be a legitimate bug
                        in the DocBook XSL stylesheets, you can file a bug report from the
                            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=21935">Tracker page</link> at the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook/">DocBook Open
                            Repository</link> site at SourceForge. If instead you want to
                        request an enhancement to the stylesheets, file a <emphasis>feature
                            request</emphasis> from the same Tracker page at the SourceForge
                        site. <note><simpara>You will need to have a SourceForge user account to
                                file a bug report or feature request. This requirement makes
                                it easier follow up on bug reports. If the DocBook XSL
                                stylesheet developers need to get more details about a
                                specific bug report, it's difficult to follow up on it if it
                                was submitted anonymously.</simpara><simpara>You can <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/account/registration">register for an account</link> at the SourceForge
                                site.</simpara></note> </para></listitem></itemizedlist> </para></topic>
