<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="Portability"><title>Portability considerations</title><para><indexterm><primary>portability</primary></indexterm>If you need to be able to process XML files on more than one
            operating system, you need to consider how portable the XSL processors
            are.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Java-based processors are highly portable, as long as each platform
                    has a modern Java interpreter. (How modern depends on the individual
                    processor and version. Check the processor's requirements list.) With
                    Saxon, Xalan-Java, FOP, and other Java-based processors, you can install
                    a few Java archives without any compiling and produce identical results
                    on Linux, Unix, Windows, and Macintosh.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Processors written in C such as xsltproc and Sablotron are less
                    portable. You need a version compiled for each platform you want to run
                    it on. Many are available in precompiled packages, such as RPMs for
                    Linux or Zip files for Windows. But the packaged versions can lag behind
                    the latest version, so you may need to compile it yourself for a given
                    platform. The C code is written to be portable, but there are always
                    issues that come up when you have to compile.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The PassiveTeX FO processor is unique in that it is written in TeX, a
                    typesetting language. TeX is also very portable, but it is currently
                    difficult to get PassiveTeX to work properly with the DocBook XSL
                    stylesheets</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Another portability consideration is file permissions. Some packages may try
            to install files into areas of a filesystem controlled by a system
            administrator. If you do not have the necessary permissions, you may not be able
            to install a given package. All of the processors can be installed elsewhere,
            but you may need to spend time figuring out how to do so.</para></topic>
