<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="WhatIsDocbook"><title>What is DocBook?</title><para>DocBook is a collection of standards and tools for technical publishing. DocBook
        was originally created by a consortium of software companies as a standard for
        computer documentation. But the basic <quote>book</quote> features of DocBook can be
        used for other kinds of content, so it has been adapted to many purposes.</para><para>The core DocBook standard is the <glossterm>DocBook Document Type Definition
            (DTD)</glossterm> maintained by the DocBook Technical Committee in <indexterm><primary>OASIS</primary></indexterm><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook">OASIS</link>. The DTD
        defines the vocabulary of content elements that an author can use and how they
        relate to each other. For example, a <literal>book</literal> element can contain a
            <literal>title</literal> element, any number of <literal>para</literal> elements
        for paragraphs, and any number of <literal>chapter</literal> elements. Using the DTD
        and XML syntax, authors mark up their text content with tag names enclosed in angle
        brackets like <literal>&lt;chapter&gt;</literal>. The markup is similar to
        HTML, but with more tags and tighter rules.</para><para>Text that is marked up in this standard way can be processed by any number of
        software tools. A major advantage of DocBook is the availability of DocBook tools
        from many sources, not just from a single vendor of a proprietary file format. You
        can mix and match components for editing, typesetting, version control, and HTML
        conversion. You can assemble a custom system that is well suited to your needs, and
        many of the components are available for free.</para><para>The other major advantage of DocBook is the set of free stylesheets that are
        available for it. Written by Norman Walsh in the Extensible Stylesheet Language
        (XSL), these stylesheets enable anyone to publish their DocBook content in print and
        HTML. The stylesheets are now developed and maintained as an open-source project on
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook">SourceForge</link><indexterm><primary>SourceForge</primary></indexterm>. An active community of users and contributors keeps up the development
        of the stylesheets and answers questions.</para><para>As a publishing system, DocBook is best suited for any of these situations:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Large quantities of content.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Highly structured content.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Content that needs to be interchanged among otherwise incompatible
                systems.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Content that needs automated batch processing.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Content to be rendered in multiple output forms and versions.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>DocBook is not a WYSIWYG word processor (although graphical editors are available
        for DocBook). DocBook is hardly worth the trouble for short or one-off documents.
        And since the formatting is strictly by batch process with stylesheets, DocBook is
        not well matched to highly designed layout-driven content like magazines.</para><para>DocBook is well suited to any collection of technical documentation that is
        regularly maintained and published. Because you are not locked into a single vendor,
        you have flexibility in your choice of processes and tools, both now and in the
        future. Multiple authors can contribute, and their content can easily be merged
        because all the authors are using a standard markup language. The files are plain
        text, not binary, so they also work well with most version control systems.</para><para>Setting up a DocBook system will take some time and effort. But the payoff will be
        an efficient, flexible, and inexpensive publishing system that can grow with your
        needs.</para></topic>
