<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="XSLprocessors"><title>XSL processors</title><para><indexterm><primary>XSL</primary><secondary>processors</secondary></indexterm>An <emphasis>XSL processor</emphasis> is the software that transforms an
        XML file into formatted output. There is a growing list of XSL processors to choose
        from. Each tool implements parts or all of the XSL standard, which actually has
        several components: <variablelist><title>The XSL Standards</title><varlistentry><term>Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL)</term><listitem><para>A language for expressing stylesheets written in XML. It includes
                        the XSL formatting objects (XSL-FO) language, but refers to separate
                        documents for the transformation language and the path
                        language.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XSL Transformation (XSLT)</term><listitem><para>The part of XSL for transforming XML documents into other XML
                        documents, HTML, or text. It can be used to rearrange the content
                        and generate new content.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XML Path Language (XPath)</term><listitem><para>A language for addressing parts of an XML document. It is used to
                        find the parts of your document to apply different styles to. All
                        XSL processors use this component.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist></para><para>To publish HTML from your XML documents, you just need an XSLT processor. It will include the XPath
        language since that is used extensively in XSLT. To get to print, you need an XSLT
        processor to produce an intermediate formatting objects (FO) file, and then you need
        an XSL-FO processor to produce
        PostScript or PDF output from the FO file. A diagram of the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://nwalsh.com/docbook/procdiagram/index.html">DocBook Publishing
            Model</link> <indexterm><primary>publishing model</primary></indexterm>is available if you want to see how all the components flow
        together.</para></topic>
