<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
<articleinfo>
<title>The Slides Document Type</title>
<releaseinfo role="CVS">$Id$</releaseinfo>
<author><firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname>
        <affiliation><address><email>ndw@nwalsh.com</email></address></affiliation>
</author>
</articleinfo>

<para>The Slides Document Type is an XML vocabulary derived from
DocBook. It is used to create presentations (slides, foils, whatever
you call them) in HTML or print.</para>

<para>Presentations are by nature visual and the Slides stylesheets
provide a wide range of options to control how the transformation from
XML to HTML is performed.</para>

<para>This document is a first attempt at describing what some of
these options are and how to use them.</para>

<section id="ch.stylesheet">
<title>Choose a Stylesheet</title>

<para>At the highest level, you can choose one of five stylesheets:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><filename>slides.xsl</filename> produces basic slides in HTML, one page
per slide.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><filename>frames.xsl</filename> produces slides in HTML using frames.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><filename>tables.xsl</filename> produces slides in HTML using tables, one page
per slide.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><filename>w3c.xsl</filename> produces basic slides in HTML, one
page per slide, using a navigation style similar to that of most W3C
talks.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para><filename>fo-plain.xsl</filename> produces basic slides, one
page per slide, for print using XSL Formatting Objects.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id="ch.params">
<title>Choose your Parameters</title>

<para>The <ulink url="param.html">parameter reference</ulink> summarizes the
parameters that you can set to change the features of the slides.</para>

<para>Be aware that some features require JavaScript. Some effort has been taken
to assure that these features work across different browsers on different platforms,
but it is possible that older browsers will not render slides that use JavaScript
correctly.</para>

</section>

<section id="ch.process">
<title>Process the Slides</title>

<para>Run your slides source through your favorite XSLT processor using the stylesheet
and parameters you selected.</para>

<para>View the results in your favorite browser.</para>

</section>

</article>
