<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="publishers.rnc" type="compact"?><book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" role="play">
<title>As You Like It</title>

<info><author><personname><firstname>William</firstname><surname>Shakespeare</surname></personname></author><legalnotice>
<para>ASCII text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</para>
<para>SGML markup by Jon Bosak, 1992-1994.</para>
<para>XML version by Jon Bosak, 1996-1999.</para>
<para>The XML markup in this version is Copyright © 1999 Jon Bosak.
This work may freely be distributed on condition that it not be
modified or altered in any way.</para>
</legalnotice>     <copyright><year>2008</year><holder>Scott Hudson</holder></copyright></info>

<preface>
<title>Dramatis Personae</title>

<para><personname role="persona">DUKE SENIOR, living in banishment.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DUKE FREDERICK, his brother, an usurper of his dominions.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">AMIENS</personname><personname role="persona">JAQUES</personname></member><member>lords attending on the banished duke.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">LE BEAU, a courtier attending upon Frederick.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">CHARLES, wrestler to Frederick.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">OLIVER</personname><personname role="persona">JAQUES   </personname><personname role="persona">ORLANDO</personname></member><member>sons of Sir Rowland de Boys.</member></simplelist>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">ADAM</personname><personname role="persona">DENNIS</personname></member><member>servants to Oliver.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">TOUCHSTONE, a clown.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR OLIVER MARTEXT, a vicar.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">CORIN</personname><personname role="persona">SILVIUS</personname></member><member>shepherds.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">WILLIAM, a country fellow in love with Audrey.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">A person representing HYMEN. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">ROSALIND, daughter to the banished duke.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">CELIA, daughter to Frederick.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">PHEBE, a shepherdess.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">AUDREY, a country wench.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Lords, pages, and attendants, &amp;c.</personname></para>
    
    <para role="scndescr">SCENE  Oliver's house; Duke Frederick's court; and the Forest of Arden.</para>
</preface>



<chapter role="act"><title>ACT I</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Orchard of Oliver's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO and ADAM</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>As I remember, Adam, it was upon this fashion</line>
<line>bequeathed me by will but poor a thousand crowns,</line>
<line>and, as thou sayest, charged my brother, on his</line>
<line>blessing, to breed me well: and there begins my</line>
<line>sadness. My brother Jaques he keeps at school, and</line>
<line>report speaks goldenly of his profit: for my part,</line>
<line>he keeps me rustically at home, or, to speak more</line>
<line>properly, stays me here at home unkept; for call you</line>
<line>that keeping for a gentleman of my birth, that</line>
<line>differs not from the stalling of an ox? His horses</line>
<line>are bred better; for, besides that they are fair</line>
<line>with their feeding, they are taught their manage,</line>
<line>and to that end riders dearly hired: but I, his</line>
<line>brother, gain nothing under him but growth; for the</line>
<line>which his animals on his dunghills are as much</line>
<line>bound to him as I. Besides this nothing that he so</line>
<line>plentifully gives me, the something that nature gave</line>
<line>me his countenance seems to take from me: he lets</line>
<line>me feed with his hinds, bars me the place of a</line>
<line>brother, and, as much as in him lies, mines my</line>
<line>gentility with my education. This is it, Adam, that</line>
<line>grieves me; and the spirit of my father, which I</line>
<line>think is within me, begins to mutiny against this</line>
<line>servitude: I will no longer endure it, though yet I</line>
<line>know no wise remedy how to avoid it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>Yonder comes my master, your brother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Go apart, Adam, and thou shalt hear how he will</line>
<line>shake me up.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter OLIVER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Now, sir! what make you here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Nothing: I am not taught to make any thing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>What mar you then, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Marry, sir, I am helping you to mar that which God</line>
<line>made, a poor unworthy brother of yours, with idleness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Marry, sir, be better employed, and be naught awhile.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Shall I keep your hogs and eat husks with them?</line>
<line>What prodigal portion have I spent, that I should</line>
<line>come to such penury?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Know you where your are, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>O, sir, very well; here in your orchard.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Know you before whom, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Ay, better than him I am before knows me. I know</line>
<line>you are my eldest brother; and, in the gentle</line>
<line>condition of blood, you should so know me. The</line>
<line>courtesy of nations allows you my better, in that</line>
<line>you are the first-born; but the same tradition</line>
<line>takes not away my blood, were there twenty brothers</line>
<line>betwixt us: I have as much of my father in me as</line>
<line>you; albeit, I confess, your coming before me is</line>
<line>nearer to his reverence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>What, boy!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Come, come, elder brother, you are too young in this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou lay hands on me, villain?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I am no villain; I am the youngest son of Sir</line>
<line>Rowland de Boys; he was my father, and he is thrice</line>
<line>a villain that says such a father begot villains.</line>
<line>Wert thou not my brother, I would not take this hand</line>
<line>from thy throat till this other had pulled out thy</line>
<line>tongue for saying so: thou hast railed on thyself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>Sweet masters, be patient: for your father's</line>
<line>remembrance, be at accord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Let me go, I say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I will not, till I please: you shall hear me. My</line>
<line>father charged you in his will to give me good</line>
<line>education: you have trained me like a peasant,</line>
<line>obscuring and hiding from me all gentleman-like</line>
<line>qualities. The spirit of my father grows strong in</line>
<line>me, and I will no longer endure it: therefore allow</line>
<line>me such exercises as may become a gentleman, or</line>
<line>give me the poor allottery my father left me by</line>
<line>testament; with that I will go buy my fortunes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>And what wilt thou do? beg, when that is spent?</line>
<line>Well, sir, get you in: I will not long be troubled</line>
<line>with you; you shall have some part of your will: I</line>
<line>pray you, leave me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I will no further offend you than becomes me for my good.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Get you with him, you old dog.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>Is 'old dog' my reward? Most true, I have lost my</line>
<line>teeth in your service. God be with my old master!</line>
<line>he would not have spoke such a word.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt ORLANDO and ADAM</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Is it even so? begin you to grow upon me? I will</line>
<line>physic your rankness, and yet give no thousand</line>
<line>crowns neither. Holla, Dennis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DENNIS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DENNIS</speaker>
<line>Calls your worship?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Was not Charles, the duke's wrestler, here to speak with me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DENNIS</speaker>
<line>So please you, he is here at the door and importunes</line>
<line>access to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Call him in.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit DENNIS</para>
<line>'Twill be a good way; and to-morrow the wrestling is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter CHARLES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>Good morrow to your worship.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Good Monsieur Charles, what's the new news at the</line>
<line>new court?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>There's no news at the court, sir, but the old news:</line>
<line>that is, the old duke is banished by his younger</line>
<line>brother the new duke; and three or four loving lords</line>
<line>have put themselves into voluntary exile with him,</line>
<line>whose lands and revenues enrich the new duke;</line>
<line>therefore he gives them good leave to wander.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Can you tell if Rosalind, the duke's daughter, be</line>
<line>banished with her father?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>O, no; for the duke's daughter, her cousin, so loves</line>
<line>her, being ever from their cradles bred together,</line>
<line>that she would have followed her exile, or have died</line>
<line>to stay behind her. She is at the court, and no</line>
<line>less beloved of her uncle than his own daughter; and</line>
<line>never two ladies loved as they do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Where will the old duke live?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>They say he is already in the forest of Arden, and</line>
<line>a many merry men with him; and there they live like</line>
<line>the old Robin Hood of England: they say many young</line>
<line>gentlemen flock to him every day, and fleet the time</line>
<line>carelessly, as they did in the golden world.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>What, you wrestle to-morrow before the new duke?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>Marry, do I, sir; and I came to acquaint you with a</line>
<line>matter. I am given, sir, secretly to understand</line>
<line>that your younger brother Orlando hath a disposition</line>
<line>to come in disguised against me to try a fall.</line>
<line>To-morrow, sir, I wrestle for my credit; and he that</line>
<line>escapes me without some broken limb shall acquit him</line>
<line>well. Your brother is but young and tender; and,</line>
<line>for your love, I would be loath to foil him, as I</line>
<line>must, for my own honour, if he come in: therefore,</line>
<line>out of my love to you, I came hither to acquaint you</line>
<line>withal, that either you might stay him from his</line>
<line>intendment or brook such disgrace well as he shall</line>
<line>run into, in that it is a thing of his own search</line>
<line>and altogether against my will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Charles, I thank thee for thy love to me, which</line>
<line>thou shalt find I will most kindly requite. I had</line>
<line>myself notice of my brother's purpose herein and</line>
<line>have by underhand means laboured to dissuade him from</line>
<line>it, but he is resolute. I'll tell thee, Charles:</line>
<line>it is the stubbornest young fellow of France, full</line>
<line>of ambition, an envious emulator of every man's</line>
<line>good parts, a secret and villanous contriver against</line>
<line>me his natural brother: therefore use thy</line>
<line>discretion; I had as lief thou didst break his neck</line>
<line>as his finger. And thou wert best look to't; for if</line>
<line>thou dost him any slight disgrace or if he do not</line>
<line>mightily grace himself on thee, he will practise</line>
<line>against thee by poison, entrap thee by some</line>
<line>treacherous device and never leave thee till he</line>
<line>hath ta'en thy life by some indirect means or other;</line>
<line>for, I assure thee, and almost with tears I speak</line>
<line>it, there is not one so young and so villanous this</line>
<line>day living. I speak but brotherly of him; but</line>
<line>should I anatomize him to thee as he is, I must</line>
<line>blush and weep and thou must look pale and wonder.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>I am heartily glad I came hither to you. If he come</line>
<line>to-morrow, I'll give him his payment: if ever he go</line>
<line>alone again, I'll never wrestle for prize more: and</line>
<line>so God keep your worship!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Farewell, good Charles.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit CHARLES</para>
<line>Now will I stir this gamester: I hope I shall see</line>
<line>an end of him; for my soul, yet I know not why,</line>
<line>hates nothing more than he. Yet he's gentle, never</line>
<line>schooled and yet learned, full of noble device, of</line>
<line>all sorts enchantingly beloved, and indeed so much</line>
<line>in the heart of the world, and especially of my own</line>
<line>people, who best know him, that I am altogether</line>
<line>misprised: but it shall not be so long; this</line>
<line>wrestler shall clear all: nothing remains but that</line>
<line>I kindle the boy thither; which now I'll go about.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  Lawn before the Duke's palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CELIA and ROSALIND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I pray thee, Rosalind, sweet my coz, be merry.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Dear Celia, I show more mirth than I am mistress of;</line>
<line>and would you yet I were merrier? Unless you could</line>
<line>teach me to forget a banished father, you must not</line>
<line>learn me how to remember any extraordinary pleasure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Herein I see thou lovest me not with the full weight</line>
<line>that I love thee. If my uncle, thy banished father,</line>
<line>had banished thy uncle, the duke my father, so thou</line>
<line>hadst been still with me, I could have taught my</line>
<line>love to take thy father for mine: so wouldst thou,</line>
<line>if the truth of thy love to me were so righteously</line>
<line>tempered as mine is to thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Well, I will forget the condition of my estate, to</line>
<line>rejoice in yours.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>You know my father hath no child but I, nor none is</line>
<line>like to have: and, truly, when he dies, thou shalt</line>
<line>be his heir, for what he hath taken away from thy</line>
<line>father perforce, I will render thee again in</line>
<line>affection; by mine honour, I will; and when I break</line>
<line>that oath, let me turn monster: therefore, my</line>
<line>sweet Rose, my dear Rose, be merry.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>From henceforth I will, coz, and devise sports. Let</line>
<line>me see; what think you of falling in love?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Marry, I prithee, do, to make sport withal: but</line>
<line>love no man in good earnest; nor no further in sport</line>
<line>neither than with safety of a pure blush thou mayst</line>
<line>in honour come off again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>What shall be our sport, then?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Let us sit and mock the good housewife Fortune from</line>
<line>her wheel, that her gifts may henceforth be bestowed equally.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I would we could do so, for her benefits are</line>
<line>mightily misplaced, and the bountiful blind woman</line>
<line>doth most mistake in her gifts to women.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>'Tis true; for those that she makes fair she scarce</line>
<line>makes honest, and those that she makes honest she</line>
<line>makes very ill-favouredly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, now thou goest from Fortune's office to</line>
<line>Nature's: Fortune reigns in gifts of the world,</line>
<line>not in the lineaments of Nature.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter TOUCHSTONE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>No? when Nature hath made a fair creature, may she</line>
<line>not by Fortune fall into the fire? Though Nature</line>
<line>hath given us wit to flout at Fortune, hath not</line>
<line>Fortune sent in this fool to cut off the argument?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Indeed, there is Fortune too hard for Nature, when</line>
<line>Fortune makes Nature's natural the cutter-off of</line>
<line>Nature's wit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Peradventure this is not Fortune's work neither, but</line>
<line>Nature's; who perceiveth our natural wits too dull</line>
<line>to reason of such goddesses and hath sent this</line>
<line>natural for our whetstone; for always the dulness of</line>
<line>the fool is the whetstone of the wits. How now,</line>
<line>wit! whither wander you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Mistress, you must come away to your father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Were you made the messenger?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>No, by mine honour, but I was bid to come for you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Where learned you that oath, fool?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Of a certain knight that swore by his honour they</line>
<line>were good pancakes and swore by his honour the</line>
<line>mustard was naught: now I'll stand to it, the</line>
<line>pancakes were naught and the mustard was good, and</line>
<line>yet was not the knight forsworn.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>How prove you that, in the great heap of your</line>
<line>knowledge?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, marry, now unmuzzle your wisdom.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Stand you both forth now: stroke your chins, and</line>
<line>swear by your beards that I am a knave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>By our beards, if we had them, thou art.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>By my knavery, if I had it, then I were; but if you</line>
<line>swear by that that is not, you are not forsworn: no</line>
<line>more was this knight swearing by his honour, for he</line>
<line>never had any; or if he had, he had sworn it away</line>
<line>before ever he saw those pancakes or that mustard.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Prithee, who is't that thou meanest?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>One that old Frederick, your father, loves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>My father's love is enough to honour him: enough!</line>
<line>speak no more of him; you'll be whipped for taxation</line>
<line>one of these days.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>The more pity, that fools may not speak wisely what</line>
<line>wise men do foolishly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>By my troth, thou sayest true; for since the little</line>
<line>wit that fools have was silenced, the little foolery</line>
<line>that wise men have makes a great show. Here comes</line>
<line>Monsieur Le Beau.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>With his mouth full of news.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Which he will put on us, as pigeons feed their young.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Then shall we be news-crammed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>All the better; we shall be the more marketable.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter LE BEAU</para>
<line>Bon jour, Monsieur Le Beau: what's the news?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Fair princess, you have lost much good sport.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Sport! of what colour?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>What colour, madam! how shall I answer you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>As wit and fortune will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Or as the Destinies decree.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Well said: that was laid on with a trowel.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Nay, if I keep not my rank,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Thou losest thy old smell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>You amaze me, ladies: I would have told you of good</line>
<line>wrestling, which you have lost the sight of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>You tell us the manner of the wrestling.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>I will tell you the beginning; and, if it please</line>
<line>your ladyships, you may see the end; for the best is</line>
<line>yet to do; and here, where you are, they are coming</line>
<line>to perform it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Well, the beginning, that is dead and buried.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>There comes an old man and his three sons,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I could match this beginning with an old tale.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Three proper young men, of excellent growth and presence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>With bills on their necks, 'Be it known unto all men</line>
<line>by these presents.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>The eldest of the three wrestled with Charles, the</line>
<line>duke's wrestler; which Charles in a moment threw him</line>
<line>and broke three of his ribs, that there is little</line>
<line>hope of life in him: so he served the second, and</line>
<line>so the third. Yonder they lie; the poor old man,</line>
<line>their father, making such pitiful dole over them</line>
<line>that all the beholders take his part with weeping.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Alas!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>But what is the sport, monsieur, that the ladies</line>
<line>have lost?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Why, this that I speak of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Thus men may grow wiser every day: it is the first</line>
<line>time that ever I heard breaking of ribs was sport</line>
<line>for ladies.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Or I, I promise thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But is there any else longs to see this broken music</line>
<line>in his sides? is there yet another dotes upon</line>
<line>rib-breaking? Shall we see this wrestling, cousin?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>You must, if you stay here; for here is the place</line>
<line>appointed for the wrestling, and they are ready to</line>
<line>perform it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Yonder, sure, they are coming: let us now stay and see it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Enter DUKE FREDERICK, Lords, ORLANDO,
CHARLES, and Attendants</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Come on: since the youth will not be entreated, his</line>
<line>own peril on his forwardness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Is yonder the man?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Even he, madam.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Alas, he is too young! yet he looks successfully.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>How now, daughter and cousin! are you crept hither</line>
<line>to see the wrestling?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, my liege, so please you give us leave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>You will take little delight in it, I can tell you;</line>
<line>there is such odds in the man. In pity of the</line>
<line>challenger's youth I would fain dissuade him, but he</line>
<line>will not be entreated. Speak to him, ladies; see if</line>
<line>you can move him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Call him hither, good Monsieur Le Beau.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Do so: I'll not be by.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Monsieur the challenger, the princesses call for you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I attend them with all respect and duty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Young man, have you challenged Charles the wrestler?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>No, fair princess; he is the general challenger: I</line>
<line>come but in, as others do, to try with him the</line>
<line>strength of my youth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Young gentleman, your spirits are too bold for your</line>
<line>years. You have seen cruel proof of this man's</line>
<line>strength: if you saw yourself with your eyes or</line>
<line>knew yourself with your judgment, the fear of your</line>
<line>adventure would counsel you to a more equal</line>
<line>enterprise. We pray you, for your own sake, to</line>
<line>embrace your own safety and give over this attempt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Do, young sir; your reputation shall not therefore</line>
<line>be misprised: we will make it our suit to the duke</line>
<line>that the wrestling might not go forward.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I beseech you, punish me not with your hard</line>
<line>thoughts; wherein I confess me much guilty, to deny</line>
<line>so fair and excellent ladies any thing. But let</line>
<line>your fair eyes and gentle wishes go with me to my</line>
<line>trial: wherein if I be foiled, there is but one</line>
<line>shamed that was never gracious; if killed, but one</line>
<line>dead that was willing to be so: I shall do my</line>
<line>friends no wrong, for I have none to lament me, the</line>
<line>world no injury, for in it I have nothing; only in</line>
<line>the world I fill up a place, which may be better</line>
<line>supplied when I have made it empty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>The little strength that I have, I would it were with you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>And mine, to eke out hers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Fare you well: pray heaven I be deceived in you!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Your heart's desires be with you!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>Come, where is this young gallant that is so</line>
<line>desirous to lie with his mother earth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Ready, sir; but his will hath in it a more modest working.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>You shall try but one fall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHARLES</speaker>
<line>No, I warrant your grace, you shall not entreat him</line>
<line>to a second, that have so mightily persuaded him</line>
<line>from a first.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>An you mean to mock me after, you should not have</line>
<line>mocked me before: but come your ways.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Now Hercules be thy speed, young man!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I would I were invisible, to catch the strong</line>
<line>fellow by the leg.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They wrestle</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O excellent young man!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>If I had a thunderbolt in mine eye, I can tell who</line>
<line>should down.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Shout. CHARLES is thrown</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>No more, no more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Yes, I beseech your grace: I am not yet well breathed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>How dost thou, Charles?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>He cannot speak, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Bear him away. What is thy name, young man?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Orlando, my liege; the youngest son of Sir Rowland de Boys.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>I would thou hadst been son to some man else:</line>
<line>The world esteem'd thy father honourable,</line>
<line>But I did find him still mine enemy:</line>
<line>Thou shouldst have better pleased me with this deed,</line>
<line>Hadst thou descended from another house.</line>
<line>But fare thee well; thou art a gallant youth:</line>
<line>I would thou hadst told me of another father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt DUKE FREDERICK, train, and LE BEAU</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Were I my father, coz, would I do this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I am more proud to be Sir Rowland's son,</line>
<line>His youngest son; and would not change that calling,</line>
<line>To be adopted heir to Frederick.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>My father loved Sir Rowland as his soul,</line>
<line>And all the world was of my father's mind:</line>
<line>Had I before known this young man his son,</line>
<line>I should have given him tears unto entreaties,</line>
<line>Ere he should thus have ventured.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Gentle cousin,</line>
<line>Let us go thank him and encourage him:</line>
<line>My father's rough and envious disposition</line>
<line>Sticks me at heart. Sir, you have well deserved:</line>
<line>If you do keep your promises in love</line>
<line>But justly, as you have exceeded all promise,</line>
<line>Your mistress shall be happy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Gentleman,</line>
<para role="stagedir">Giving him a chain from her neck</para>
<line>Wear this for me, one out of suits with fortune,</line>
<line>That could give more, but that her hand lacks means.</line>
<line>Shall we go, coz?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Ay. Fare you well, fair gentleman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Can I not say, I thank you? My better parts</line>
<line>Are all thrown down, and that which here stands up</line>
<line>Is but a quintain, a mere lifeless block.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>He calls us back: my pride fell with my fortunes;</line>
<line>I'll ask him what he would. Did you call, sir?</line>
<line>Sir, you have wrestled well and overthrown</line>
<line>More than your enemies.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Will you go, coz?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Have with you. Fare you well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt ROSALIND and CELIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>What passion hangs these weights upon my tongue?</line>
<line>I cannot speak to her, yet she urged conference.</line>
<line>O poor Orlando, thou art overthrown!</line>
<line>Or Charles or something weaker masters thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter LE BEAU</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Good sir, I do in friendship counsel you</line>
<line>To leave this place. Albeit you have deserved</line>
<line>High commendation, true applause and love,</line>
<line>Yet such is now the duke's condition</line>
<line>That he misconstrues all that you have done.</line>
<line>The duke is humorous; what he is indeed,</line>
<line>More suits you to conceive than I to speak of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I thank you, sir: and, pray you, tell me this:</line>
<line>Which of the two was daughter of the duke</line>
<line>That here was at the wrestling?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LE BEAU</speaker>
<line>Neither his daughter, if we judge by manners;</line>
<line>But yet indeed the lesser is his daughter</line>
<line>The other is daughter to the banish'd duke,</line>
<line>And here detain'd by her usurping uncle,</line>
<line>To keep his daughter company; whose loves</line>
<line>Are dearer than the natural bond of sisters.</line>
<line>But I can tell you that of late this duke</line>
<line>Hath ta'en displeasure 'gainst his gentle niece,</line>
<line>Grounded upon no other argument</line>
<line>But that the people praise her for her virtues</line>
<line>And pity her for her good father's sake;</line>
<line>And, on my life, his malice 'gainst the lady</line>
<line>Will suddenly break forth. Sir, fare you well:</line>
<line>Hereafter, in a better world than this,</line>
<line>I shall desire more love and knowledge of you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I rest much bounden to you: fare you well.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit LE BEAU</para>
<line>Thus must I from the smoke into the smother;</line>
<line>From tyrant duke unto a tyrant brother:</line>
<line>But heavenly Rosalind!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CELIA and ROSALIND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Why, cousin! why, Rosalind! Cupid have mercy! not a word?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Not one to throw at a dog.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>No, thy words are too precious to be cast away upon</line>
<line>curs; throw some of them at me; come, lame me with reasons.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Then there were two cousins laid up; when the one</line>
<line>should be lamed with reasons and the other mad</line>
<line>without any.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>But is all this for your father?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>No, some of it is for my child's father. O, how</line>
<line>full of briers is this working-day world!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>They are but burs, cousin, thrown upon thee in</line>
<line>holiday foolery: if we walk not in the trodden</line>
<line>paths our very petticoats will catch them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I could shake them off my coat: these burs are in my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Hem them away.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I would try, if I could cry 'hem' and have him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Come, come, wrestle with thy affections.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O, they take the part of a better wrestler than myself!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>O, a good wish upon you! you will try in time, in</line>
<line>despite of a fall. But, turning these jests out of</line>
<line>service, let us talk in good earnest: is it</line>
<line>possible, on such a sudden, you should fall into so</line>
<line>strong a liking with old Sir Rowland's youngest son?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>The duke my father loved his father dearly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Doth it therefore ensue that you should love his son</line>
<line>dearly? By this kind of chase, I should hate him,</line>
<line>for my father hated his father dearly; yet I hate</line>
<line>not Orlando.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>No, faith, hate him not, for my sake.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Why should I not? doth he not deserve well?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Let me love him for that, and do you love him</line>
<line>because I do. Look, here comes the duke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>With his eyes full of anger.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE FREDERICK, with Lords</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Mistress, dispatch you with your safest haste</line>
<line>And get you from our court.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Me, uncle?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>You, cousin</line>
<line>Within these ten days if that thou be'st found</line>
<line>So near our public court as twenty miles,</line>
<line>Thou diest for it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I do beseech your grace,</line>
<line>Let me the knowledge of my fault bear with me:</line>
<line>If with myself I hold intelligence</line>
<line>Or have acquaintance with mine own desires,</line>
<line>If that I do not dream or be not frantic,--</line>
<line>As I do trust I am not--then, dear uncle,</line>
<line>Never so much as in a thought unborn</line>
<line>Did I offend your highness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Thus do all traitors:</line>
<line>If their purgation did consist in words,</line>
<line>They are as innocent as grace itself:</line>
<line>Let it suffice thee that I trust thee not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Yet your mistrust cannot make me a traitor:</line>
<line>Tell me whereon the likelihood depends.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Thou art thy father's daughter; there's enough.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>So was I when your highness took his dukedom;</line>
<line>So was I when your highness banish'd him:</line>
<line>Treason is not inherited, my lord;</line>
<line>Or, if we did derive it from our friends,</line>
<line>What's that to me? my father was no traitor:</line>
<line>Then, good my liege, mistake me not so much</line>
<line>To think my poverty is treacherous.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Dear sovereign, hear me speak.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Ay, Celia; we stay'd her for your sake,</line>
<line>Else had she with her father ranged along.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I did not then entreat to have her stay;</line>
<line>It was your pleasure and your own remorse:</line>
<line>I was too young that time to value her;</line>
<line>But now I know her: if she be a traitor,</line>
<line>Why so am I; we still have slept together,</line>
<line>Rose at an instant, learn'd, play'd, eat together,</line>
<line>And wheresoever we went, like Juno's swans,</line>
<line>Still we went coupled and inseparable.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>She is too subtle for thee; and her smoothness,</line>
<line>Her very silence and her patience</line>
<line>Speak to the people, and they pity her.</line>
<line>Thou art a fool: she robs thee of thy name;</line>
<line>And thou wilt show more bright and seem more virtuous</line>
<line>When she is gone. Then open not thy lips:</line>
<line>Firm and irrevocable is my doom</line>
<line>Which I have pass'd upon her; she is banish'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Pronounce that sentence then on me, my liege:</line>
<line>I cannot live out of her company.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>You are a fool. You, niece, provide yourself:</line>
<line>If you outstay the time, upon mine honour,</line>
<line>And in the greatness of my word, you die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt DUKE FREDERICK and Lords</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>O my poor Rosalind, whither wilt thou go?</line>
<line>Wilt thou change fathers? I will give thee mine.</line>
<line>I charge thee, be not thou more grieved than I am.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I have more cause.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Thou hast not, cousin;</line>
<line>Prithee be cheerful: know'st thou not, the duke</line>
<line>Hath banish'd me, his daughter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>That he hath not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>No, hath not? Rosalind lacks then the love</line>
<line>Which teacheth thee that thou and I am one:</line>
<line>Shall we be sunder'd? shall we part, sweet girl?</line>
<line>No: let my father seek another heir.</line>
<line>Therefore devise with me how we may fly,</line>
<line>Whither to go and what to bear with us;</line>
<line>And do not seek to take your change upon you,</line>
<line>To bear your griefs yourself and leave me out;</line>
<line>For, by this heaven, now at our sorrows pale,</line>
<line>Say what thou canst, I'll go along with thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why, whither shall we go?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>To seek my uncle in the forest of Arden.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Alas, what danger will it be to us,</line>
<line>Maids as we are, to travel forth so far!</line>
<line>Beauty provoketh thieves sooner than gold.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I'll put myself in poor and mean attire</line>
<line>And with a kind of umber smirch my face;</line>
<line>The like do you: so shall we pass along</line>
<line>And never stir assailants.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Were it not better,</line>
<line>Because that I am more than common tall,</line>
<line>That I did suit me all points like a man?</line>
<line>A gallant curtle-axe upon my thigh,</line>
<line>A boar-spear in my hand; and--in my heart</line>
<line>Lie there what hidden woman's fear there will--</line>
<line>We'll have a swashing and a martial outside,</line>
<line>As many other mannish cowards have</line>
<line>That do outface it with their semblances.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>What shall I call thee when thou art a man?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I'll have no worse a name than Jove's own page;</line>
<line>And therefore look you call me Ganymede.</line>
<line>But what will you be call'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Something that hath a reference to my state</line>
<line>No longer Celia, but Aliena.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But, cousin, what if we assay'd to steal</line>
<line>The clownish fool out of your father's court?</line>
<line>Would he not be a comfort to our travel?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>He'll go along o'er the wide world with me;</line>
<line>Leave me alone to woo him. Let's away,</line>
<line>And get our jewels and our wealth together,</line>
<line>Devise the fittest time and safest way</line>
<line>To hide us from pursuit that will be made</line>
<line>After my flight. Now go we in content</line>
<line>To liberty and not to banishment.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT II</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  The Forest of Arden.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE SENIOR, AMIENS, and two or three Lords,
like foresters</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Now, my co-mates and brothers in exile,</line>
<line>Hath not old custom made this life more sweet</line>
<line>Than that of painted pomp? Are not these woods</line>
<line>More free from peril than the envious court?</line>
<line>Here feel we but the penalty of Adam,</line>
<line>The seasons' difference, as the icy fang</line>
<line>And churlish chiding of the winter's wind,</line>
<line>Which, when it bites and blows upon my body,</line>
<line>Even till I shrink with cold, I smile and say</line>
<line>'This is no flattery: these are counsellors</line>
<line>That feelingly persuade me what I am.'</line>
<line>Sweet are the uses of adversity,</line>
<line>Which, like the toad, ugly and venomous,</line>
<line>Wears yet a precious jewel in his head;</line>
<line>And this our life exempt from public haunt</line>
<line>Finds tongues in trees, books in the running brooks,</line>
<line>Sermons in stones and good in every thing.</line>
<line>I would not change it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>Happy is your grace,</line>
<line>That can translate the stubbornness of fortune</line>
<line>Into so quiet and so sweet a style.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Come, shall we go and kill us venison?</line>
<line>And yet it irks me the poor dappled fools,</line>
<line>Being native burghers of this desert city,</line>
<line>Should in their own confines with forked heads</line>
<line>Have their round haunches gored.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>Indeed, my lord,</line>
<line>The melancholy Jaques grieves at that,</line>
<line>And, in that kind, swears you do more usurp</line>
<line>Than doth your brother that hath banish'd you.</line>
<line>To-day my Lord of Amiens and myself</line>
<line>Did steal behind him as he lay along</line>
<line>Under an oak whose antique root peeps out</line>
<line>Upon the brook that brawls along this wood:</line>
<line>To the which place a poor sequester'd stag,</line>
<line>That from the hunter's aim had ta'en a hurt,</line>
<line>Did come to languish, and indeed, my lord,</line>
<line>The wretched animal heaved forth such groans</line>
<line>That their discharge did stretch his leathern coat</line>
<line>Almost to bursting, and the big round tears</line>
<line>Coursed one another down his innocent nose</line>
<line>In piteous chase; and thus the hairy fool</line>
<line>Much marked of the melancholy Jaques,</line>
<line>Stood on the extremest verge of the swift brook,</line>
<line>Augmenting it with tears.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>But what said Jaques?</line>
<line>Did he not moralize this spectacle?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>O, yes, into a thousand similes.</line>
<line>First, for his weeping into the needless stream;</line>
<line>'Poor deer,' quoth he, 'thou makest a testament</line>
<line>As worldlings do, giving thy sum of more</line>
<line>To that which had too much:' then, being there alone,</line>
<line>Left and abandon'd of his velvet friends,</line>
<line>''Tis right:' quoth he; 'thus misery doth part</line>
<line>The flux of company:' anon a careless herd,</line>
<line>Full of the pasture, jumps along by him</line>
<line>And never stays to greet him; 'Ay' quoth Jaques,</line>
<line>'Sweep on, you fat and greasy citizens;</line>
<line>'Tis just the fashion: wherefore do you look</line>
<line>Upon that poor and broken bankrupt there?'</line>
<line>Thus most invectively he pierceth through</line>
<line>The body of the country, city, court,</line>
<line>Yea, and of this our life, swearing that we</line>
<line>Are mere usurpers, tyrants and what's worse,</line>
<line>To fright the animals and to kill them up</line>
<line>In their assign'd and native dwelling-place.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>And did you leave him in this contemplation?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Lord</speaker>
<line>We did, my lord, weeping and commenting</line>
<line>Upon the sobbing deer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Show me the place:</line>
<line>I love to cope him in these sullen fits,</line>
<line>For then he's full of matter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>I'll bring you to him straight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE FREDERICK, with Lords</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Can it be possible that no man saw them?</line>
<line>It cannot be: some villains of my court</line>
<line>Are of consent and sufferance in this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>I cannot hear of any that did see her.</line>
<line>The ladies, her attendants of her chamber,</line>
<line>Saw her abed, and in the morning early</line>
<line>They found the bed untreasured of their mistress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Lord</speaker>
<line>My lord, the roynish clown, at whom so oft</line>
<line>Your grace was wont to laugh, is also missing.</line>
<line>Hisperia, the princess' gentlewoman,</line>
<line>Confesses that she secretly o'erheard</line>
<line>Your daughter and her cousin much commend</line>
<line>The parts and graces of the wrestler</line>
<line>That did but lately foil the sinewy Charles;</line>
<line>And she believes, wherever they are gone,</line>
<line>That youth is surely in their company.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Send to his brother; fetch that gallant hither;</line>
<line>If he be absent, bring his brother to me;</line>
<line>I'll make him find him: do this suddenly,</line>
<line>And let not search and inquisition quail</line>
<line>To bring again these foolish runaways.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Before OLIVER'S house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO and ADAM, meeting</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Who's there?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>What, my young master? O, my gentle master!</line>
<line>O my sweet master! O you memory</line>
<line>Of old Sir Rowland! why, what make you here?</line>
<line>Why are you virtuous? why do people love you?</line>
<line>And wherefore are you gentle, strong and valiant?</line>
<line>Why would you be so fond to overcome</line>
<line>The bonny priser of the humorous duke?</line>
<line>Your praise is come too swiftly home before you.</line>
<line>Know you not, master, to some kind of men</line>
<line>Their graces serve them but as enemies?</line>
<line>No more do yours: your virtues, gentle master,</line>
<line>Are sanctified and holy traitors to you.</line>
<line>O, what a world is this, when what is comely</line>
<line>Envenoms him that bears it!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Why, what's the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>O unhappy youth!</line>
<line>Come not within these doors; within this roof</line>
<line>The enemy of all your graces lives:</line>
<line>Your brother--no, no brother; yet the son--</line>
<line>Yet not the son, I will not call him son</line>
<line>Of him I was about to call his father--</line>
<line>Hath heard your praises, and this night he means</line>
<line>To burn the lodging where you use to lie</line>
<line>And you within it: if he fail of that,</line>
<line>He will have other means to cut you off.</line>
<line>I overheard him and his practises.</line>
<line>This is no place; this house is but a butchery:</line>
<line>Abhor it, fear it, do not enter it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Why, whither, Adam, wouldst thou have me go?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>No matter whither, so you come not here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>What, wouldst thou have me go and beg my food?</line>
<line>Or with a base and boisterous sword enforce</line>
<line>A thievish living on the common road?</line>
<line>This I must do, or know not what to do:</line>
<line>Yet this I will not do, do how I can;</line>
<line>I rather will subject me to the malice</line>
<line>Of a diverted blood and bloody brother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>But do not so. I have five hundred crowns,</line>
<line>The thrifty hire I saved under your father,</line>
<line>Which I did store to be my foster-nurse</line>
<line>When service should in my old limbs lie lame</line>
<line>And unregarded age in corners thrown:</line>
<line>Take that, and He that doth the ravens feed,</line>
<line>Yea, providently caters for the sparrow,</line>
<line>Be comfort to my age! Here is the gold;</line>
<line>And all this I give you. Let me be your servant:</line>
<line>Though I look old, yet I am strong and lusty;</line>
<line>For in my youth I never did apply</line>
<line>Hot and rebellious liquors in my blood,</line>
<line>Nor did not with unbashful forehead woo</line>
<line>The means of weakness and debility;</line>
<line>Therefore my age is as a lusty winter,</line>
<line>Frosty, but kindly: let me go with you;</line>
<line>I'll do the service of a younger man</line>
<line>In all your business and necessities.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>O good old man, how well in thee appears</line>
<line>The constant service of the antique world,</line>
<line>When service sweat for duty, not for meed!</line>
<line>Thou art not for the fashion of these times,</line>
<line>Where none will sweat but for promotion,</line>
<line>And having that, do choke their service up</line>
<line>Even with the having: it is not so with thee.</line>
<line>But, poor old man, thou prunest a rotten tree,</line>
<line>That cannot so much as a blossom yield</line>
<line>In lieu of all thy pains and husbandry</line>
<line>But come thy ways; well go along together,</line>
<line>And ere we have thy youthful wages spent,</line>
<line>We'll light upon some settled low content.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>Master, go on, and I will follow thee,</line>
<line>To the last gasp, with truth and loyalty.</line>
<line>From seventeen years till now almost fourscore</line>
<line>Here lived I, but now live here no more.</line>
<line>At seventeen years many their fortunes seek;</line>
<line>But at fourscore it is too late a week:</line>
<line>Yet fortune cannot recompense me better</line>
<line>Than to die well and not my master's debtor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The Forest of Arden.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND for Ganymede, CELIA for Aliena,
and TOUCHSTONE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O Jupiter, how weary are my spirits!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>I care not for my spirits, if my legs were not weary.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I could find in my heart to disgrace my man's</line>
<line>apparel and to cry like a woman; but I must comfort</line>
<line>the weaker vessel, as doublet and hose ought to show</line>
<line>itself courageous to petticoat: therefore courage,</line>
<line>good Aliena!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I pray you, bear with me; I cannot go no further.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>For my part, I had rather bear with you than bear</line>
<line>you; yet I should bear no cross if I did bear you,</line>
<line>for I think you have no money in your purse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Well, this is the forest of Arden.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Ay, now am I in Arden; the more fool I; when I was</line>
<line>at home, I was in a better place: but travellers</line>
<line>must be content.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, be so, good Touchstone.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CORIN and SILVIUS</para>
<line>Look you, who comes here; a young man and an old in</line>
<line>solemn talk.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>That is the way to make her scorn you still.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>O Corin, that thou knew'st how I do love her!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>I partly guess; for I have loved ere now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>No, Corin, being old, thou canst not guess,</line>
<line>Though in thy youth thou wast as true a lover</line>
<line>As ever sigh'd upon a midnight pillow:</line>
<line>But if thy love were ever like to mine--</line>
<line>As sure I think did never man love so--</line>
<line>How many actions most ridiculous</line>
<line>Hast thou been drawn to by thy fantasy?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Into a thousand that I have forgotten.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>O, thou didst then ne'er love so heartily!</line>
<line>If thou remember'st not the slightest folly</line>
<line>That ever love did make thee run into,</line>
<line>Thou hast not loved:</line>
<line>Or if thou hast not sat as I do now,</line>
<line>Wearying thy hearer in thy mistress' praise,</line>
<line>Thou hast not loved:</line>
<line>Or if thou hast not broke from company</line>
<line>Abruptly, as my passion now makes me,</line>
<line>Thou hast not loved.</line>
<line>O Phebe, Phebe, Phebe!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Alas, poor shepherd! searching of thy wound,</line>
<line>I have by hard adventure found mine own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>And I mine. I remember, when I was in love I broke</line>
<line>my sword upon a stone and bid him take that for</line>
<line>coming a-night to Jane Smile; and I remember the</line>
<line>kissing of her batlet and the cow's dugs that her</line>
<line>pretty chopt hands had milked; and I remember the</line>
<line>wooing of a peascod instead of her, from whom I took</line>
<line>two cods and, giving her them again, said with</line>
<line>weeping tears 'Wear these for my sake.' We that are</line>
<line>true lovers run into strange capers; but as all is</line>
<line>mortal in nature, so is all nature in love mortal in folly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Thou speakest wiser than thou art ware of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Nay, I shall ne'er be ware of mine own wit till I</line>
<line>break my shins against it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Jove, Jove! this shepherd's passion</line>
<line>Is much upon my fashion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>And mine; but it grows something stale with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I pray you, one of you question yond man</line>
<line>If he for gold will give us any food:</line>
<line>I faint almost to death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Holla, you clown!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Peace, fool: he's not thy kinsman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Who calls?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Your betters, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Else are they very wretched.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Peace, I say. Good even to you, friend.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>And to you, gentle sir, and to you all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I prithee, shepherd, if that love or gold</line>
<line>Can in this desert place buy entertainment,</line>
<line>Bring us where we may rest ourselves and feed:</line>
<line>Here's a young maid with travel much oppress'd</line>
<line>And faints for succor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Fair sir, I pity her</line>
<line>And wish, for her sake more than for mine own,</line>
<line>My fortunes were more able to relieve her;</line>
<line>But I am shepherd to another man</line>
<line>And do not shear the fleeces that I graze:</line>
<line>My master is of churlish disposition</line>
<line>And little recks to find the way to heaven</line>
<line>By doing deeds of hospitality:</line>
<line>Besides, his cote, his flocks and bounds of feed</line>
<line>Are now on sale, and at our sheepcote now,</line>
<line>By reason of his absence, there is nothing</line>
<line>That you will feed on; but what is, come see.</line>
<line>And in my voice most welcome shall you be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>What is he that shall buy his flock and pasture?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>That young swain that you saw here but erewhile,</line>
<line>That little cares for buying any thing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I pray thee, if it stand with honesty,</line>
<line>Buy thou the cottage, pasture and the flock,</line>
<line>And thou shalt have to pay for it of us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>And we will mend thy wages. I like this place.</line>
<line>And willingly could waste my time in it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Assuredly the thing is to be sold:</line>
<line>Go with me: if you like upon report</line>
<line>The soil, the profit and this kind of life,</line>
<line>I will your very faithful feeder be</line>
<line>And buy it with your gold right suddenly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE V.  The Forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter AMIENS, JAQUES, and others</para>
<bridgehead role="subhead">SONG.</bridgehead>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>Under the greenwood tree</line>
<line>Who loves to lie with me,</line>
<line>And turn his merry note</line>
<line>Unto the sweet bird's throat,</line>
<line>Come hither, come hither, come hither:</line>
<line>Here shall he see No enemy</line>
<line>But winter and rough weather.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>More, more, I prithee, more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>It will make you melancholy, Monsieur Jaques.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I thank it. More, I prithee, more. I can suck</line>
<line>melancholy out of a song, as a weasel sucks eggs.</line>
<line>More, I prithee, more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>My voice is ragged: I know I cannot please you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I do not desire you to please me; I do desire you to</line>
<line>sing. Come, more; another stanzo: call you 'em stanzos?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>What you will, Monsieur Jaques.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Nay, I care not for their names; they owe me</line>
<line>nothing. Will you sing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>More at your request than to please myself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Well then, if ever I thank any man, I'll thank you;</line>
<line>but that they call compliment is like the encounter</line>
<line>of two dog-apes, and when a man thanks me heartily,</line>
<line>methinks I have given him a penny and he renders me</line>
<line>the beggarly thanks. Come, sing; and you that will</line>
<line>not, hold your tongues.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>Well, I'll end the song. Sirs, cover the while; the</line>
<line>duke will drink under this tree. He hath been all</line>
<line>this day to look you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>And I have been all this day to avoid him. He is</line>
<line>too disputable for my company: I think of as many</line>
<line>matters as he, but I give heaven thanks and make no</line>
<line>boast of them. Come, warble, come.</line>
<bridgehead role="subhead">SONG.</bridgehead>
<line>Who doth ambition shun</line>
<para role="stagedir">All together here</para>
<line>And loves to live i' the sun,</line>
<line>Seeking the food he eats</line>
<line>And pleased with what he gets,</line>
<line>Come hither, come hither, come hither:</line>
<line>Here shall he see No enemy</line>
<line>But winter and rough weather.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I'll give you a verse to this note that I made</line>
<line>yesterday in despite of my invention.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>And I'll sing it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Thus it goes:--</line>
<line>If it do come to pass</line>
<line>That any man turn ass,</line>
<line>Leaving his wealth and ease,</line>
<line>A stubborn will to please,</line>
<line>Ducdame, ducdame, ducdame:</line>
<line>Here shall he see</line>
<line>Gross fools as he,</line>
<line>An if he will come to me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>What's that 'ducdame'?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>'Tis a Greek invocation, to call fools into a</line>
<line>circle. I'll go sleep, if I can; if I cannot, I'll</line>
<line>rail against all the first-born of Egypt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>And I'll go seek the duke: his banquet is prepared.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt severally</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE VI.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO and ADAM</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>Dear master, I can go no further. O, I die for food!</line>
<line>Here lie I down, and measure out my grave. Farewell,</line>
<line>kind master.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Why, how now, Adam! no greater heart in thee? Live</line>
<line>a little; comfort a little; cheer thyself a little.</line>
<line>If this uncouth forest yield any thing savage, I</line>
<line>will either be food for it or bring it for food to</line>
<line>thee. Thy conceit is nearer death than thy powers.</line>
<line>For my sake be comfortable; hold death awhile at</line>
<line>the arm's end: I will here be with thee presently;</line>
<line>and if I bring thee not something to eat, I will</line>
<line>give thee leave to die: but if thou diest before I</line>
<line>come, thou art a mocker of my labour. Well said!</line>
<line>thou lookest cheerly, and I'll be with thee quickly.</line>
<line>Yet thou liest in the bleak air: come, I will bear</line>
<line>thee to some shelter; and thou shalt not die for</line>
<line>lack of a dinner, if there live any thing in this</line>
<line>desert. Cheerly, good Adam!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE VII.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">A table set out. Enter DUKE SENIOR, AMIENS, and
Lords like outlaws</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>I think he be transform'd into a beast;</line>
<line>For I can no where find him like a man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>My lord, he is but even now gone hence:</line>
<line>Here was he merry, hearing of a song.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>If he, compact of jars, grow musical,</line>
<line>We shall have shortly discord in the spheres.</line>
<line>Go, seek him: tell him I would speak with him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter JAQUES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>He saves my labour by his own approach.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Why, how now, monsieur! what a life is this,</line>
<line>That your poor friends must woo your company?</line>
<line>What, you look merrily!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>A fool, a fool! I met a fool i' the forest,</line>
<line>A motley fool; a miserable world!</line>
<line>As I do live by food, I met a fool</line>
<line>Who laid him down and bask'd him in the sun,</line>
<line>And rail'd on Lady Fortune in good terms,</line>
<line>In good set terms and yet a motley fool.</line>
<line>'Good morrow, fool,' quoth I. 'No, sir,' quoth he,</line>
<line>'Call me not fool till heaven hath sent me fortune:'</line>
<line>And then he drew a dial from his poke,</line>
<line>And, looking on it with lack-lustre eye,</line>
<line>Says very wisely, 'It is ten o'clock:</line>
<line>Thus we may see,' quoth he, 'how the world wags:</line>
<line>'Tis but an hour ago since it was nine,</line>
<line>And after one hour more 'twill be eleven;</line>
<line>And so, from hour to hour, we ripe and ripe,</line>
<line>And then, from hour to hour, we rot and rot;</line>
<line>And thereby hangs a tale.' When I did hear</line>
<line>The motley fool thus moral on the time,</line>
<line>My lungs began to crow like chanticleer,</line>
<line>That fools should be so deep-contemplative,</line>
<line>And I did laugh sans intermission</line>
<line>An hour by his dial. O noble fool!</line>
<line>A worthy fool! Motley's the only wear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>What fool is this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>O worthy fool! One that hath been a courtier,</line>
<line>And says, if ladies be but young and fair,</line>
<line>They have the gift to know it: and in his brain,</line>
<line>Which is as dry as the remainder biscuit</line>
<line>After a voyage, he hath strange places cramm'd</line>
<line>With observation, the which he vents</line>
<line>In mangled forms. O that I were a fool!</line>
<line>I am ambitious for a motley coat.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Thou shalt have one.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>It is my only suit;</line>
<line>Provided that you weed your better judgments</line>
<line>Of all opinion that grows rank in them</line>
<line>That I am wise. I must have liberty</line>
<line>Withal, as large a charter as the wind,</line>
<line>To blow on whom I please; for so fools have;</line>
<line>And they that are most galled with my folly,</line>
<line>They most must laugh. And why, sir, must they so?</line>
<line>The 'why' is plain as way to parish church:</line>
<line>He that a fool doth very wisely hit</line>
<line>Doth very foolishly, although he smart,</line>
<line>Not to seem senseless of the bob: if not,</line>
<line>The wise man's folly is anatomized</line>
<line>Even by the squandering glances of the fool.</line>
<line>Invest me in my motley; give me leave</line>
<line>To speak my mind, and I will through and through</line>
<line>Cleanse the foul body of the infected world,</line>
<line>If they will patiently receive my medicine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Fie on thee! I can tell what thou wouldst do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>What, for a counter, would I do but good?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Most mischievous foul sin, in chiding sin:</line>
<line>For thou thyself hast been a libertine,</line>
<line>As sensual as the brutish sting itself;</line>
<line>And all the embossed sores and headed evils,</line>
<line>That thou with licence of free foot hast caught,</line>
<line>Wouldst thou disgorge into the general world.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Why, who cries out on pride,</line>
<line>That can therein tax any private party?</line>
<line>Doth it not flow as hugely as the sea,</line>
<line>Till that the weary very means do ebb?</line>
<line>What woman in the city do I name,</line>
<line>When that I say the city-woman bears</line>
<line>The cost of princes on unworthy shoulders?</line>
<line>Who can come in and say that I mean her,</line>
<line>When such a one as she such is her neighbour?</line>
<line>Or what is he of basest function</line>
<line>That says his bravery is not of my cost,</line>
<line>Thinking that I mean him, but therein suits</line>
<line>His folly to the mettle of my speech?</line>
<line>There then; how then? what then? Let me see wherein</line>
<line>My tongue hath wrong'd him: if it do him right,</line>
<line>Then he hath wrong'd himself; if he be free,</line>
<line>Why then my taxing like a wild-goose flies,</line>
<line>Unclaim'd of any man. But who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO, with his sword drawn</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Forbear, and eat no more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Why, I have eat none yet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Nor shalt not, till necessity be served.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Of what kind should this cock come of?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Art thou thus bolden'd, man, by thy distress,</line>
<line>Or else a rude despiser of good manners,</line>
<line>That in civility thou seem'st so empty?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>You touch'd my vein at first: the thorny point</line>
<line>Of bare distress hath ta'en from me the show</line>
<line>Of smooth civility: yet am I inland bred</line>
<line>And know some nurture. But forbear, I say:</line>
<line>He dies that touches any of this fruit</line>
<line>Till I and my affairs are answered.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>An you will not be answered with reason, I must die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>What would you have? Your gentleness shall force</line>
<line>More than your force move us to gentleness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I almost die for food; and let me have it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Sit down and feed, and welcome to our table.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Speak you so gently? Pardon me, I pray you:</line>
<line>I thought that all things had been savage here;</line>
<line>And therefore put I on the countenance</line>
<line>Of stern commandment. But whate'er you are</line>
<line>That in this desert inaccessible,</line>
<line>Under the shade of melancholy boughs,</line>
<line>Lose and neglect the creeping hours of time</line>
<line>If ever you have look'd on better days,</line>
<line>If ever been where bells have knoll'd to church,</line>
<line>If ever sat at any good man's feast,</line>
<line>If ever from your eyelids wiped a tear</line>
<line>And know what 'tis to pity and be pitied,</line>
<line>Let gentleness my strong enforcement be:</line>
<line>In the which hope I blush, and hide my sword.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>True is it that we have seen better days,</line>
<line>And have with holy bell been knoll'd to church</line>
<line>And sat at good men's feasts and wiped our eyes</line>
<line>Of drops that sacred pity hath engender'd:</line>
<line>And therefore sit you down in gentleness</line>
<line>And take upon command what help we have</line>
<line>That to your wanting may be minister'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Then but forbear your food a little while,</line>
<line>Whiles, like a doe, I go to find my fawn</line>
<line>And give it food. There is an old poor man,</line>
<line>Who after me hath many a weary step</line>
<line>Limp'd in pure love: till he be first sufficed,</line>
<line>Oppress'd with two weak evils, age and hunger,</line>
<line>I will not touch a bit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Go find him out,</line>
<line>And we will nothing waste till you return.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I thank ye; and be blest for your good comfort!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Thou seest we are not all alone unhappy:</line>
<line>This wide and universal theatre</line>
<line>Presents more woeful pageants than the scene</line>
<line>Wherein we play in.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>All the world's a stage,</line>
<line>And all the men and women merely players:</line>
<line>They have their exits and their entrances;</line>
<line>And one man in his time plays many parts,</line>
<line>His acts being seven ages. At first the infant,</line>
<line>Mewling and puking in the nurse's arms.</line>
<line>And then the whining school-boy, with his satchel</line>
<line>And shining morning face, creeping like snail</line>
<line>Unwillingly to school. And then the lover,</line>
<line>Sighing like furnace, with a woeful ballad</line>
<line>Made to his mistress' eyebrow. Then a soldier,</line>
<line>Full of strange oaths and bearded like the pard,</line>
<line>Jealous in honour, sudden and quick in quarrel,</line>
<line>Seeking the bubble reputation</line>
<line>Even in the cannon's mouth. And then the justice,</line>
<line>In fair round belly with good capon lined,</line>
<line>With eyes severe and beard of formal cut,</line>
<line>Full of wise saws and modern instances;</line>
<line>And so he plays his part. The sixth age shifts</line>
<line>Into the lean and slipper'd pantaloon,</line>
<line>With spectacles on nose and pouch on side,</line>
<line>His youthful hose, well saved, a world too wide</line>
<line>For his shrunk shank; and his big manly voice,</line>
<line>Turning again toward childish treble, pipes</line>
<line>And whistles in his sound. Last scene of all,</line>
<line>That ends this strange eventful history,</line>
<line>Is second childishness and mere oblivion,</line>
<line>Sans teeth, sans eyes, sans taste, sans everything.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter ORLANDO, with ADAM</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Welcome. Set down your venerable burthen,</line>
<line>And let him feed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I thank you most for him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ADAM</speaker>
<line>So had you need:</line>
<line>I scarce can speak to thank you for myself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Welcome; fall to: I will not trouble you</line>
<line>As yet, to question you about your fortunes.</line>
<line>Give us some music; and, good cousin, sing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<bridgehead role="subhead">SONG.</bridgehead>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AMIENS</speaker>
<line>Blow, blow, thou winter wind.</line>
<line>Thou art not so unkind</line>
<line>As man's ingratitude;</line>
<line>Thy tooth is not so keen,</line>
<line>Because thou art not seen,</line>
<line>Although thy breath be rude.</line>
<line>Heigh-ho! sing, heigh-ho! unto the green holly:</line>
<line>Most friendship is feigning, most loving mere folly:</line>
<line>Then, heigh-ho, the holly!</line>
<line>This life is most jolly.</line>
<line>Freeze, freeze, thou bitter sky,</line>
<line>That dost not bite so nigh</line>
<line>As benefits forgot:</line>
<line>Though thou the waters warp,</line>
<line>Thy sting is not so sharp</line>
<line>As friend remember'd not.</line>
<line>Heigh-ho! sing, &amp;c.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>If that you were the good Sir Rowland's son,</line>
<line>As you have whisper'd faithfully you were,</line>
<line>And as mine eye doth his effigies witness</line>
<line>Most truly limn'd and living in your face,</line>
<line>Be truly welcome hither: I am the duke</line>
<line>That loved your father: the residue of your fortune,</line>
<line>Go to my cave and tell me. Good old man,</line>
<line>Thou art right welcome as thy master is.</line>
<line>Support him by the arm. Give me your hand,</line>
<line>And let me all your fortunes understand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT III</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE FREDERICK, Lords, and OLIVER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>Not see him since? Sir, sir, that cannot be:</line>
<line>But were I not the better part made mercy,</line>
<line>I should not seek an absent argument</line>
<line>Of my revenge, thou present. But look to it:</line>
<line>Find out thy brother, wheresoe'er he is;</line>
<line>Seek him with candle; bring him dead or living</line>
<line>Within this twelvemonth, or turn thou no more</line>
<line>To seek a living in our territory.</line>
<line>Thy lands and all things that thou dost call thine</line>
<line>Worth seizure do we seize into our hands,</line>
<line>Till thou canst quit thee by thy brothers mouth</line>
<line>Of what we think against thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>O that your highness knew my heart in this!</line>
<line>I never loved my brother in my life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
<line>More villain thou. Well, push him out of doors;</line>
<line>And let my officers of such a nature</line>
<line>Make an extent upon his house and lands:</line>
<line>Do this expediently and turn him going.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO, with a paper</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Hang there, my verse, in witness of my love:</line>
<line>And thou, thrice-crowned queen of night, survey</line>
<line>With thy chaste eye, from thy pale sphere above,</line>
<line>Thy huntress' name that my full life doth sway.</line>
<line>O Rosalind! these trees shall be my books</line>
<line>And in their barks my thoughts I'll character;</line>
<line>That every eye which in this forest looks</line>
<line>Shall see thy virtue witness'd every where.</line>
<line>Run, run, Orlando; carve on every tree</line>
<line>The fair, the chaste and unexpressive she.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CORIN and TOUCHSTONE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>And how like you this shepherd's life, Master Touchstone?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Truly, shepherd, in respect of itself, it is a good</line>
<line>life, but in respect that it is a shepherd's life,</line>
<line>it is naught. In respect that it is solitary, I</line>
<line>like it very well; but in respect that it is</line>
<line>private, it is a very vile life. Now, in respect it</line>
<line>is in the fields, it pleaseth me well; but in</line>
<line>respect it is not in the court, it is tedious. As</line>
<line>is it a spare life, look you, it fits my humour well;</line>
<line>but as there is no more plenty in it, it goes much</line>
<line>against my stomach. Hast any philosophy in thee, shepherd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>No more but that I know the more one sickens the</line>
<line>worse at ease he is; and that he that wants money,</line>
<line>means and content is without three good friends;</line>
<line>that the property of rain is to wet and fire to</line>
<line>burn; that good pasture makes fat sheep, and that a</line>
<line>great cause of the night is lack of the sun; that</line>
<line>he that hath learned no wit by nature nor art may</line>
<line>complain of good breeding or comes of a very dull kindred.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Such a one is a natural philosopher. Wast ever in</line>
<line>court, shepherd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>No, truly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Then thou art damned.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Nay, I hope.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Truly, thou art damned like an ill-roasted egg, all</line>
<line>on one side.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>For not being at court? Your reason.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Why, if thou never wast at court, thou never sawest</line>
<line>good manners; if thou never sawest good manners,</line>
<line>then thy manners must be wicked; and wickedness is</line>
<line>sin, and sin is damnation. Thou art in a parlous</line>
<line>state, shepherd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Not a whit, Touchstone: those that are good manners</line>
<line>at the court are as ridiculous in the country as the</line>
<line>behavior of the country is most mockable at the</line>
<line>court. You told me you salute not at the court, but</line>
<line>you kiss your hands: that courtesy would be</line>
<line>uncleanly, if courtiers were shepherds.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Instance, briefly; come, instance.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Why, we are still handling our ewes, and their</line>
<line>fells, you know, are greasy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Why, do not your courtier's hands sweat? and is not</line>
<line>the grease of a mutton as wholesome as the sweat of</line>
<line>a man? Shallow, shallow. A better instance, I say; come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Besides, our hands are hard.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Your lips will feel them the sooner. Shallow again.</line>
<line>A more sounder instance, come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>And they are often tarred over with the surgery of</line>
<line>our sheep: and would you have us kiss tar? The</line>
<line>courtier's hands are perfumed with civet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Most shallow man! thou worms-meat, in respect of a</line>
<line>good piece of flesh indeed! Learn of the wise, and</line>
<line>perpend: civet is of a baser birth than tar, the</line>
<line>very uncleanly flux of a cat. Mend the instance, shepherd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>You have too courtly a wit for me: I'll rest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou rest damned? God help thee, shallow man!</line>
<line>God make incision in thee! thou art raw.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Sir, I am a true labourer: I earn that I eat, get</line>
<line>that I wear, owe no man hate, envy no man's</line>
<line>happiness, glad of other men's good, content with my</line>
<line>harm, and the greatest of my pride is to see my ewes</line>
<line>graze and my lambs suck.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>That is another simple sin in you, to bring the ewes</line>
<line>and the rams together and to offer to get your</line>
<line>living by the copulation of cattle; to be bawd to a</line>
<line>bell-wether, and to betray a she-lamb of a</line>
<line>twelvemonth to a crooked-pated, old, cuckoldly ram,</line>
<line>out of all reasonable match. If thou beest not</line>
<line>damned for this, the devil himself will have no</line>
<line>shepherds; I cannot see else how thou shouldst</line>
<line>'scape.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Here comes young Master Ganymede, my new mistress's brother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND, with a paper, reading</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>From the east to western Ind,</line>
<line>No jewel is like Rosalind.</line>
<line>Her worth, being mounted on the wind,</line>
<line>Through all the world bears Rosalind.</line>
<line>All the pictures fairest lined</line>
<line>Are but black to Rosalind.</line>
<line>Let no fair be kept in mind</line>
<line>But the fair of Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>I'll rhyme you so eight years together, dinners and</line>
<line>suppers and sleeping-hours excepted: it is the</line>
<line>right butter-women's rank to market.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Out, fool!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>For a taste:</line>
<line>If a hart do lack a hind,</line>
<line>Let him seek out Rosalind.</line>
<line>If the cat will after kind,</line>
<line>So be sure will Rosalind.</line>
<line>Winter garments must be lined,</line>
<line>So must slender Rosalind.</line>
<line>They that reap must sheaf and bind;</line>
<line>Then to cart with Rosalind.</line>
<line>Sweetest nut hath sourest rind,</line>
<line>Such a nut is Rosalind.</line>
<line>He that sweetest rose will find</line>
<line>Must find love's prick and Rosalind.</line>
<line>This is the very false gallop of verses: why do you</line>
<line>infect yourself with them?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Peace, you dull fool! I found them on a tree.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Truly, the tree yields bad fruit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I'll graff it with you, and then I shall graff it</line>
<line>with a medlar: then it will be the earliest fruit</line>
<line>i' the country; for you'll be rotten ere you be half</line>
<line>ripe, and that's the right virtue of the medlar.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>You have said; but whether wisely or no, let the</line>
<line>forest judge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter CELIA, with a writing</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Peace! Here comes my sister, reading: stand aside.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Reads</phrase></line>
<line>Why should this a desert be?</line>
<line>For it is unpeopled? No:</line>
<line>Tongues I'll hang on every tree,</line>
<line>That shall civil sayings show:</line>
<line>Some, how brief the life of man</line>
<line>Runs his erring pilgrimage,</line>
<line>That the stretching of a span</line>
<line>Buckles in his sum of age;</line>
<line>Some, of violated vows</line>
<line>'Twixt the souls of friend and friend:</line>
<line>But upon the fairest boughs,</line>
<line>Or at every sentence end,</line>
<line>Will I Rosalinda write,</line>
<line>Teaching all that read to know</line>
<line>The quintessence of every sprite</line>
<line>Heaven would in little show.</line>
<line>Therefore Heaven Nature charged</line>
<line>That one body should be fill'd</line>
<line>With all graces wide-enlarged:</line>
<line>Nature presently distill'd</line>
<line>Helen's cheek, but not her heart,</line>
<line>Cleopatra's majesty,</line>
<line>Atalanta's better part,</line>
<line>Sad Lucretia's modesty.</line>
<line>Thus Rosalind of many parts</line>
<line>By heavenly synod was devised,</line>
<line>Of many faces, eyes and hearts,</line>
<line>To have the touches dearest prized.</line>
<line>Heaven would that she these gifts should have,</line>
<line>And I to live and die her slave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O most gentle pulpiter! what tedious homily of love</line>
<line>have you wearied your parishioners withal, and never</line>
<line>cried 'Have patience, good people!'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>How now! back, friends! Shepherd, go off a little.</line>
<line>Go with him, sirrah.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Come, shepherd, let us make an honourable retreat;</line>
<line>though not with bag and baggage, yet with scrip and scrippage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt CORIN and TOUCHSTONE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Didst thou hear these verses?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O, yes, I heard them all, and more too; for some of</line>
<line>them had in them more feet than the verses would bear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>That's no matter: the feet might bear the verses.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, but the feet were lame and could not bear</line>
<line>themselves without the verse and therefore stood</line>
<line>lamely in the verse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>But didst thou hear without wondering how thy name</line>
<line>should be hanged and carved upon these trees?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I was seven of the nine days out of the wonder</line>
<line>before you came; for look here what I found on a</line>
<line>palm-tree. I was never so be-rhymed since</line>
<line>Pythagoras' time, that I was an Irish rat, which I</line>
<line>can hardly remember.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Trow you who hath done this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Is it a man?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>And a chain, that you once wore, about his neck.</line>
<line>Change you colour?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I prithee, who?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>O Lord, Lord! it is a hard matter for friends to</line>
<line>meet; but mountains may be removed with earthquakes</line>
<line>and so encounter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, but who is it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Is it possible?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, I prithee now with most petitionary vehemence,</line>
<line>tell me who it is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>O wonderful, wonderful, and most wonderful</line>
<line>wonderful! and yet again wonderful, and after that,</line>
<line>out of all hooping!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Good my complexion! dost thou think, though I am</line>
<line>caparisoned like a man, I have a doublet and hose in</line>
<line>my disposition? One inch of delay more is a</line>
<line>South-sea of discovery; I prithee, tell me who is it</line>
<line>quickly, and speak apace. I would thou couldst</line>
<line>stammer, that thou mightst pour this concealed man</line>
<line>out of thy mouth, as wine comes out of a narrow-</line>
<line>mouthed bottle, either too much at once, or none at</line>
<line>all. I prithee, take the cork out of thy mouth that</line>
<line>may drink thy tidings.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>So you may put a man in your belly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Is he of God's making? What manner of man? Is his</line>
<line>head worth a hat, or his chin worth a beard?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Nay, he hath but a little beard.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why, God will send more, if the man will be</line>
<line>thankful: let me stay the growth of his beard, if</line>
<line>thou delay me not the knowledge of his chin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>It is young Orlando, that tripped up the wrestler's</line>
<line>heels and your heart both in an instant.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, but the devil take mocking: speak, sad brow and</line>
<line>true maid.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I' faith, coz, 'tis he.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Orlando?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Orlando.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Alas the day! what shall I do with my doublet and</line>
<line>hose? What did he when thou sawest him? What said</line>
<line>he? How looked he? Wherein went he? What makes</line>
<line>him here? Did he ask for me? Where remains he?</line>
<line>How parted he with thee? and when shalt thou see</line>
<line>him again? Answer me in one word.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>You must borrow me Gargantua's mouth first: 'tis a</line>
<line>word too great for any mouth of this age's size. To</line>
<line>say ay and no to these particulars is more than to</line>
<line>answer in a catechism.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But doth he know that I am in this forest and in</line>
<line>man's apparel? Looks he as freshly as he did the</line>
<line>day he wrestled?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>It is as easy to count atomies as to resolve the</line>
<line>propositions of a lover; but take a taste of my</line>
<line>finding him, and relish it with good observance.</line>
<line>I found him under a tree, like a dropped acorn.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>It may well be called Jove's tree, when it drops</line>
<line>forth such fruit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Give me audience, good madam.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Proceed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>There lay he, stretched along, like a wounded knight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Though it be pity to see such a sight, it well</line>
<line>becomes the ground.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Cry 'holla' to thy tongue, I prithee; it curvets</line>
<line>unseasonably. He was furnished like a hunter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O, ominous! he comes to kill my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I would sing my song without a burden: thou bringest</line>
<line>me out of tune.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Do you not know I am a woman? when I think, I must</line>
<line>speak. Sweet, say on.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>You bring me out. Soft! comes he not here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO and JAQUES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>'Tis he: slink by, and note him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I thank you for your company; but, good faith, I had</line>
<line>as lief have been myself alone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And so had I; but yet, for fashion sake, I thank you</line>
<line>too for your society.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>God be wi' you: let's meet as little as we can.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I do desire we may be better strangers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I pray you, mar no more trees with writing</line>
<line>love-songs in their barks.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I pray you, mar no more of my verses with reading</line>
<line>them ill-favouredly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Rosalind is your love's name?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Yes, just.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I do not like her name.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>There was no thought of pleasing you when she was</line>
<line>christened.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>What stature is she of?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Just as high as my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>You are full of pretty answers. Have you not been</line>
<line>acquainted with goldsmiths' wives, and conned them</line>
<line>out of rings?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Not so; but I answer you right painted cloth, from</line>
<line>whence you have studied your questions.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>You have a nimble wit: I think 'twas made of</line>
<line>Atalanta's heels. Will you sit down with me? and</line>
<line>we two will rail against our mistress the world and</line>
<line>all our misery.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I will chide no breather in the world but myself,</line>
<line>against whom I know most faults.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>The worst fault you have is to be in love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>'Tis a fault I will not change for your best virtue.</line>
<line>I am weary of you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>By my troth, I was seeking for a fool when I found</line>
<line>you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>He is drowned in the brook: look but in, and you</line>
<line>shall see him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>There I shall see mine own figure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Which I take to be either a fool or a cipher.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I'll tarry no longer with you: farewell, good</line>
<line>Signior Love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I am glad of your departure: adieu, good Monsieur</line>
<line>Melancholy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit JAQUES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside to CELIA</phrase>  I will speak to him, like a saucy</line>
<line>lackey and under that habit play the knave with him.</line>
<line>Do you hear, forester?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Very well: what would you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I pray you, what is't o'clock?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>You should ask me what time o' day: there's no clock</line>
<line>in the forest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Then there is no true lover in the forest; else</line>
<line>sighing every minute and groaning every hour would</line>
<line>detect the lazy foot of Time as well as a clock.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And why not the swift foot of Time? had not that</line>
<line>been as proper?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>By no means, sir: Time travels in divers paces with</line>
<line>divers persons. I'll tell you who Time ambles</line>
<line>withal, who Time trots withal, who Time gallops</line>
<line>withal and who he stands still withal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I prithee, who doth he trot withal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Marry, he trots hard with a young maid between the</line>
<line>contract of her marriage and the day it is</line>
<line>solemnized: if the interim be but a se'nnight,</line>
<line>Time's pace is so hard that it seems the length of</line>
<line>seven year.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Who ambles Time withal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>With a priest that lacks Latin and a rich man that</line>
<line>hath not the gout, for the one sleeps easily because</line>
<line>he cannot study, and the other lives merrily because</line>
<line>he feels no pain, the one lacking the burden of lean</line>
<line>and wasteful learning, the other knowing no burden</line>
<line>of heavy tedious penury; these Time ambles withal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Who doth he gallop withal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>With a thief to the gallows, for though he go as</line>
<line>softly as foot can fall, he thinks himself too soon there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Who stays it still withal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>With lawyers in the vacation, for they sleep between</line>
<line>term and term and then they perceive not how Time moves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Where dwell you, pretty youth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>With this shepherdess, my sister; here in the</line>
<line>skirts of the forest, like fringe upon a petticoat.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Are you native of this place?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>As the cony that you see dwell where she is kindled.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Your accent is something finer than you could</line>
<line>purchase in so removed a dwelling.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I have been told so of many: but indeed an old</line>
<line>religious uncle of mine taught me to speak, who was</line>
<line>in his youth an inland man; one that knew courtship</line>
<line>too well, for there he fell in love. I have heard</line>
<line>him read many lectures against it, and I thank God</line>
<line>I am not a woman, to be touched with so many</line>
<line>giddy offences as he hath generally taxed their</line>
<line>whole sex withal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Can you remember any of the principal evils that he</line>
<line>laid to the charge of women?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>There were none principal; they were all like one</line>
<line>another as half-pence are, every one fault seeming</line>
<line>monstrous till his fellow fault came to match it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I prithee, recount some of them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>No, I will not cast away my physic but on those that</line>
<line>are sick. There is a man haunts the forest, that</line>
<line>abuses our young plants with carving 'Rosalind' on</line>
<line>their barks; hangs odes upon hawthorns and elegies</line>
<line>on brambles, all, forsooth, deifying the name of</line>
<line>Rosalind: if I could meet that fancy-monger I would</line>
<line>give him some good counsel, for he seems to have the</line>
<line>quotidian of love upon him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I am he that is so love-shaked: I pray you tell me</line>
<line>your remedy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>There is none of my uncle's marks upon you: he</line>
<line>taught me how to know a man in love; in which cage</line>
<line>of rushes I am sure you are not prisoner.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>What were his marks?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>A lean cheek, which you have not, a blue eye and</line>
<line>sunken, which you have not, an unquestionable</line>
<line>spirit, which you have not, a beard neglected,</line>
<line>which you have not; but I pardon you for that, for</line>
<line>simply your having in beard is a younger brother's</line>
<line>revenue: then your hose should be ungartered, your</line>
<line>bonnet unbanded, your sleeve unbuttoned, your shoe</line>
<line>untied and every thing about you demonstrating a</line>
<line>careless desolation; but you are no such man; you</line>
<line>are rather point-device in your accoutrements as</line>
<line>loving yourself than seeming the lover of any other.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Fair youth, I would I could make thee believe I love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Me believe it! you may as soon make her that you</line>
<line>love believe it; which, I warrant, she is apter to</line>
<line>do than to confess she does: that is one of the</line>
<line>points in the which women still give the lie to</line>
<line>their consciences. But, in good sooth, are you he</line>
<line>that hangs the verses on the trees, wherein Rosalind</line>
<line>is so admired?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I swear to thee, youth, by the white hand of</line>
<line>Rosalind, I am that he, that unfortunate he.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But are you so much in love as your rhymes speak?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Neither rhyme nor reason can express how much.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Love is merely a madness, and, I tell you, deserves</line>
<line>as well a dark house and a whip as madmen do: and</line>
<line>the reason why they are not so punished and cured</line>
<line>is, that the lunacy is so ordinary that the whippers</line>
<line>are in love too. Yet I profess curing it by counsel.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Did you ever cure any so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Yes, one, and in this manner. He was to imagine me</line>
<line>his love, his mistress; and I set him every day to</line>
<line>woo me: at which time would I, being but a moonish</line>
<line>youth, grieve, be effeminate, changeable, longing</line>
<line>and liking, proud, fantastical, apish, shallow,</line>
<line>inconstant, full of tears, full of smiles, for every</line>
<line>passion something and for no passion truly any</line>
<line>thing, as boys and women are for the most part</line>
<line>cattle of this colour; would now like him, now loathe</line>
<line>him; then entertain him, then forswear him; now weep</line>
<line>for him, then spit at him; that I drave my suitor</line>
<line>from his mad humour of love to a living humour of</line>
<line>madness; which was, to forswear the full stream of</line>
<line>the world, and to live in a nook merely monastic.</line>
<line>And thus I cured him; and this way will I take upon</line>
<line>me to wash your liver as clean as a sound sheep's</line>
<line>heart, that there shall not be one spot of love in't.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I would not be cured, youth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I would cure you, if you would but call me Rosalind</line>
<line>and come every day to my cote and woo me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Now, by the faith of my love, I will: tell me</line>
<line>where it is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Go with me to it and I'll show it you and by the way</line>
<line>you shall tell me where in the forest you live.</line>
<line>Will you go?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>With all my heart, good youth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay you must call me Rosalind. Come, sister, will you go?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY; JAQUES behind</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Come apace, good Audrey: I will fetch up your</line>
<line>goats, Audrey. And how, Audrey? am I the man yet?</line>
<line>doth my simple feature content you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Your features! Lord warrant us! what features!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>I am here with thee and thy goats, as the most</line>
<line>capricious poet, honest Ovid, was among the Goths.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  O knowledge ill-inhabited, worse than Jove</line>
<line>in a thatched house!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>When a man's verses cannot be understood, nor a</line>
<line>man's good wit seconded with the forward child</line>
<line>Understanding, it strikes a man more dead than a</line>
<line>great reckoning in a little room. Truly, I would</line>
<line>the gods had made thee poetical.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>I do not know what 'poetical' is: is it honest in</line>
<line>deed and word? is it a true thing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>No, truly; for the truest poetry is the most</line>
<line>feigning; and lovers are given to poetry, and what</line>
<line>they swear in poetry may be said as lovers they do feign.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Do you wish then that the gods had made me poetical?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>I do, truly; for thou swearest to me thou art</line>
<line>honest: now, if thou wert a poet, I might have some</line>
<line>hope thou didst feign.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Would you not have me honest?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>No, truly, unless thou wert hard-favoured; for</line>
<line>honesty coupled to beauty is to have honey a sauce to sugar.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  A material fool!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Well, I am not fair; and therefore I pray the gods</line>
<line>make me honest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Truly, and to cast away honesty upon a foul slut</line>
<line>were to put good meat into an unclean dish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>I am not a slut, though I thank the gods I am foul.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Well, praised be the gods for thy foulness!</line>
<line>sluttishness may come hereafter. But be it as it may</line>
<line>be, I will marry thee, and to that end I have been</line>
<line>with Sir Oliver Martext, the vicar of the next</line>
<line>village, who hath promised to meet me in this place</line>
<line>of the forest and to couple us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  I would fain see this meeting.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Well, the gods give us joy!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Amen. A man may, if he were of a fearful heart,</line>
<line>stagger in this attempt; for here we have no temple</line>
<line>but the wood, no assembly but horn-beasts. But what</line>
<line>though? Courage! As horns are odious, they are</line>
<line>necessary. It is said, 'many a man knows no end of</line>
<line>his goods:' right; many a man has good horns, and</line>
<line>knows no end of them. Well, that is the dowry of</line>
<line>his wife; 'tis none of his own getting. Horns?</line>
<line>Even so. Poor men alone? No, no; the noblest deer</line>
<line>hath them as huge as the rascal. Is the single man</line>
<line>therefore blessed? No: as a walled town is more</line>
<line>worthier than a village, so is the forehead of a</line>
<line>married man more honourable than the bare brow of a</line>
<line>bachelor; and by how much defence is better than no</line>
<line>skill, by so much is a horn more precious than to</line>
<line>want. Here comes Sir Oliver.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</para>
<line>Sir Oliver Martext, you are well met: will you</line>
<line>dispatch us here under this tree, or shall we go</line>
<line>with you to your chapel?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</speaker>
<line>Is there none here to give the woman?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>I will not take her on gift of any man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</speaker>
<line>Truly, she must be given, or the marriage is not lawful.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Advancing</phrase></line>
<line>Proceed, proceed I'll give her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Good even, good Master What-ye-call't: how do you,</line>
<line>sir? You are very well met: God 'ild you for your</line>
<line>last company: I am very glad to see you: even a</line>
<line>toy in hand here, sir: nay, pray be covered.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Will you be married, motley?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>As the ox hath his bow, sir, the horse his curb and</line>
<line>the falcon her bells, so man hath his desires; and</line>
<line>as pigeons bill, so wedlock would be nibbling.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>And will you, being a man of your breeding, be</line>
<line>married under a bush like a beggar? Get you to</line>
<line>church, and have a good priest that can tell you</line>
<line>what marriage is: this fellow will but join you</line>
<line>together as they join wainscot; then one of you will</line>
<line>prove a shrunk panel and, like green timber, warp, warp.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  I am not in the mind but I were better to be</line>
<line>married of him than of another: for he is not like</line>
<line>to marry me well; and not being well married, it</line>
<line>will be a good excuse for me hereafter to leave my wife.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Go thou with me, and let me counsel thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>'Come, sweet Audrey:</line>
<line>We must be married, or we must live in bawdry.</line>
<line>Farewell, good Master Oliver: not,--</line>
<line>O sweet Oliver,</line>
<line>O brave Oliver,</line>
<line>Leave me not behind thee: but,--</line>
<line>Wind away,</line>
<line>Begone, I say,</line>
<line>I will not to wedding with thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt JAQUES, TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</speaker>
<line>'Tis no matter: ne'er a fantastical knave of them</line>
<line>all shall flout me out of my calling.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND and CELIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Never talk to me; I will weep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Do, I prithee; but yet have the grace to consider</line>
<line>that tears do not become a man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But have I not cause to weep?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>As good cause as one would desire; therefore weep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>His very hair is of the dissembling colour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Something browner than Judas's marry, his kisses are</line>
<line>Judas's own children.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I' faith, his hair is of a good colour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>An excellent colour: your chestnut was ever the only colour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And his kissing is as full of sanctity as the touch</line>
<line>of holy bread.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>He hath bought a pair of cast lips of Diana: a nun</line>
<line>of winter's sisterhood kisses not more religiously;</line>
<line>the very ice of chastity is in them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But why did he swear he would come this morning, and</line>
<line>comes not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Nay, certainly, there is no truth in him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Do you think so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Yes; I think he is not a pick-purse nor a</line>
<line>horse-stealer, but for his verity in love, I do</line>
<line>think him as concave as a covered goblet or a</line>
<line>worm-eaten nut.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Not true in love?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Yes, when he is in; but I think he is not in.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>You have heard him swear downright he was.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>'Was' is not 'is:' besides, the oath of a lover is</line>
<line>no stronger than the word of a tapster; they are</line>
<line>both the confirmer of false reckonings. He attends</line>
<line>here in the forest on the duke your father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I met the duke yesterday and had much question with</line>
<line>him: he asked me of what parentage I was; I told</line>
<line>him, of as good as he; so he laughed and let me go.</line>
<line>But what talk we of fathers, when there is such a</line>
<line>man as Orlando?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>O, that's a brave man! he writes brave verses,</line>
<line>speaks brave words, swears brave oaths and breaks</line>
<line>them bravely, quite traverse, athwart the heart of</line>
<line>his lover; as a puisny tilter, that spurs his horse</line>
<line>but on one side, breaks his staff like a noble</line>
<line>goose: but all's brave that youth mounts and folly</line>
<line>guides. Who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter CORIN</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Mistress and master, you have oft inquired</line>
<line>After the shepherd that complain'd of love,</line>
<line>Who you saw sitting by me on the turf,</line>
<line>Praising the proud disdainful shepherdess</line>
<line>That was his mistress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Well, and what of him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>If you will see a pageant truly play'd,</line>
<line>Between the pale complexion of true love</line>
<line>And the red glow of scorn and proud disdain,</line>
<line>Go hence a little and I shall conduct you,</line>
<line>If you will mark it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O, come, let us remove:</line>
<line>The sight of lovers feedeth those in love.</line>
<line>Bring us to this sight, and you shall say</line>
<line>I'll prove a busy actor in their play.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE V.  Another part of the forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SILVIUS and PHEBE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Sweet Phebe, do not scorn me; do not, Phebe;</line>
<line>Say that you love me not, but say not so</line>
<line>In bitterness. The common executioner,</line>
<line>Whose heart the accustom'd sight of death makes hard,</line>
<line>Falls not the axe upon the humbled neck</line>
<line>But first begs pardon: will you sterner be</line>
<line>Than he that dies and lives by bloody drops?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND, CELIA, and CORIN, behind</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>I would not be thy executioner:</line>
<line>I fly thee, for I would not injure thee.</line>
<line>Thou tell'st me there is murder in mine eye:</line>
<line>'Tis pretty, sure, and very probable,</line>
<line>That eyes, that are the frail'st and softest things,</line>
<line>Who shut their coward gates on atomies,</line>
<line>Should be call'd tyrants, butchers, murderers!</line>
<line>Now I do frown on thee with all my heart;</line>
<line>And if mine eyes can wound, now let them kill thee:</line>
<line>Now counterfeit to swoon; why now fall down;</line>
<line>Or if thou canst not, O, for shame, for shame,</line>
<line>Lie not, to say mine eyes are murderers!</line>
<line>Now show the wound mine eye hath made in thee:</line>
<line>Scratch thee but with a pin, and there remains</line>
<line>Some scar of it; lean but upon a rush,</line>
<line>The cicatrice and capable impressure</line>
<line>Thy palm some moment keeps; but now mine eyes,</line>
<line>Which I have darted at thee, hurt thee not,</line>
<line>Nor, I am sure, there is no force in eyes</line>
<line>That can do hurt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>O dear Phebe,</line>
<line>If ever,--as that ever may be near,--</line>
<line>You meet in some fresh cheek the power of fancy,</line>
<line>Then shall you know the wounds invisible</line>
<line>That love's keen arrows make.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>But till that time</line>
<line>Come not thou near me: and when that time comes,</line>
<line>Afflict me with thy mocks, pity me not;</line>
<line>As till that time I shall not pity thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And why, I pray you? Who might be your mother,</line>
<line>That you insult, exult, and all at once,</line>
<line>Over the wretched? What though you have no beauty,--</line>
<line>As, by my faith, I see no more in you</line>
<line>Than without candle may go dark to bed--</line>
<line>Must you be therefore proud and pitiless?</line>
<line>Why, what means this? Why do you look on me?</line>
<line>I see no more in you than in the ordinary</line>
<line>Of nature's sale-work. 'Od's my little life,</line>
<line>I think she means to tangle my eyes too!</line>
<line>No, faith, proud mistress, hope not after it:</line>
<line>'Tis not your inky brows, your black silk hair,</line>
<line>Your bugle eyeballs, nor your cheek of cream,</line>
<line>That can entame my spirits to your worship.</line>
<line>You foolish shepherd, wherefore do you follow her,</line>
<line>Like foggy south puffing with wind and rain?</line>
<line>You are a thousand times a properer man</line>
<line>Than she a woman: 'tis such fools as you</line>
<line>That makes the world full of ill-favour'd children:</line>
<line>'Tis not her glass, but you, that flatters her;</line>
<line>And out of you she sees herself more proper</line>
<line>Than any of her lineaments can show her.</line>
<line>But, mistress, know yourself: down on your knees,</line>
<line>And thank heaven, fasting, for a good man's love:</line>
<line>For I must tell you friendly in your ear,</line>
<line>Sell when you can: you are not for all markets:</line>
<line>Cry the man mercy; love him; take his offer:</line>
<line>Foul is most foul, being foul to be a scoffer.</line>
<line>So take her to thee, shepherd: fare you well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Sweet youth, I pray you, chide a year together:</line>
<line>I had rather hear you chide than this man woo.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>He's fallen in love with your foulness and she'll</line>
<line>fall in love with my anger. If it be so, as fast as</line>
<line>she answers thee with frowning looks, I'll sauce her</line>
<line>with bitter words. Why look you so upon me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>For no ill will I bear you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I pray you, do not fall in love with me,</line>
<line>For I am falser than vows made in wine:</line>
<line>Besides, I like you not. If you will know my house,</line>
<line>'Tis at the tuft of olives here hard by.</line>
<line>Will you go, sister? Shepherd, ply her hard.</line>
<line>Come, sister. Shepherdess, look on him better,</line>
<line>And be not proud: though all the world could see,</line>
<line>None could be so abused in sight as he.</line>
<line>Come, to our flock.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt ROSALIND, CELIA and CORIN</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Dead Shepherd, now I find thy saw of might,</line>
<line>'Who ever loved that loved not at first sight?'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Sweet Phebe,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Ha, what say'st thou, Silvius?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Sweet Phebe, pity me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Why, I am sorry for thee, gentle Silvius.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Wherever sorrow is, relief would be:</line>
<line>If you do sorrow at my grief in love,</line>
<line>By giving love your sorrow and my grief</line>
<line>Were both extermined.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Thou hast my love: is not that neighbourly?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>I would have you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Why, that were covetousness.</line>
<line>Silvius, the time was that I hated thee,</line>
<line>And yet it is not that I bear thee love;</line>
<line>But since that thou canst talk of love so well,</line>
<line>Thy company, which erst was irksome to me,</line>
<line>I will endure, and I'll employ thee too:</line>
<line>But do not look for further recompense</line>
<line>Than thine own gladness that thou art employ'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>So holy and so perfect is my love,</line>
<line>And I in such a poverty of grace,</line>
<line>That I shall think it a most plenteous crop</line>
<line>To glean the broken ears after the man</line>
<line>That the main harvest reaps: loose now and then</line>
<line>A scatter'd smile, and that I'll live upon.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Know'st now the youth that spoke to me erewhile?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Not very well, but I have met him oft;</line>
<line>And he hath bought the cottage and the bounds</line>
<line>That the old carlot once was master of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Think not I love him, though I ask for him:</line>
<line>'Tis but a peevish boy; yet he talks well;</line>
<line>But what care I for words? yet words do well</line>
<line>When he that speaks them pleases those that hear.</line>
<line>It is a pretty youth: not very pretty:</line>
<line>But, sure, he's proud, and yet his pride becomes him:</line>
<line>He'll make a proper man: the best thing in him</line>
<line>Is his complexion; and faster than his tongue</line>
<line>Did make offence his eye did heal it up.</line>
<line>He is not very tall; yet for his years he's tall:</line>
<line>His leg is but so so; and yet 'tis well:</line>
<line>There was a pretty redness in his lip,</line>
<line>A little riper and more lusty red</line>
<line>Than that mix'd in his cheek; 'twas just the difference</line>
<line>Between the constant red and mingled damask.</line>
<line>There be some women, Silvius, had they mark'd him</line>
<line>In parcels as I did, would have gone near</line>
<line>To fall in love with him; but, for my part,</line>
<line>I love him not nor hate him not; and yet</line>
<line>I have more cause to hate him than to love him:</line>
<line>For what had he to do to chide at me?</line>
<line>He said mine eyes were black and my hair black:</line>
<line>And, now I am remember'd, scorn'd at me:</line>
<line>I marvel why I answer'd not again:</line>
<line>But that's all one; omittance is no quittance.</line>
<line>I'll write to him a very taunting letter,</line>
<line>And thou shalt bear it: wilt thou, Silvius?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Phebe, with all my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>I'll write it straight;</line>
<line>The matter's in my head and in my heart:</line>
<line>I will be bitter with him and passing short.</line>
<line>Go with me, Silvius.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT IV</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND, CELIA, and JAQUES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I prithee, pretty youth, let me be better acquainted</line>
<line>with thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>They say you are a melancholy fellow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I am so; I do love it better than laughing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Those that are in extremity of either are abominable</line>
<line>fellows and betray themselves to every modern</line>
<line>censure worse than drunkards.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Why, 'tis good to be sad and say nothing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why then, 'tis good to be a post.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>I have neither the scholar's melancholy, which is</line>
<line>emulation, nor the musician's, which is fantastical,</line>
<line>nor the courtier's, which is proud, nor the</line>
<line>soldier's, which is ambitious, nor the lawyer's,</line>
<line>which is politic, nor the lady's, which is nice, nor</line>
<line>the lover's, which is all these: but it is a</line>
<line>melancholy of mine own, compounded of many simples,</line>
<line>extracted from many objects, and indeed the sundry's</line>
<line>contemplation of my travels, in which my often</line>
<line>rumination wraps me m a most humorous sadness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>A traveller! By my faith, you have great reason to</line>
<line>be sad: I fear you have sold your own lands to see</line>
<line>other men's; then, to have seen much and to have</line>
<line>nothing, is to have rich eyes and poor hands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Yes, I have gained my experience.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And your experience makes you sad: I had rather have</line>
<line>a fool to make me merry than experience to make me</line>
<line>sad; and to travel for it too!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Good day and happiness, dear Rosalind!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Nay, then, God be wi' you, an you talk in blank verse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Farewell, Monsieur Traveller: look you lisp and</line>
<line>wear strange suits, disable all the benefits of your</line>
<line>own country, be out of love with your nativity and</line>
<line>almost chide God for making you that countenance you</line>
<line>are, or I will scarce think you have swam in a</line>
<line>gondola. Why, how now, Orlando! where have you been</line>
<line>all this while? You a lover! An you serve me such</line>
<line>another trick, never come in my sight more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>My fair Rosalind, I come within an hour of my promise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Break an hour's promise in love! He that will</line>
<line>divide a minute into a thousand parts and break but</line>
<line>a part of the thousandth part of a minute in the</line>
<line>affairs of love, it may be said of him that Cupid</line>
<line>hath clapped him o' the shoulder, but I'll warrant</line>
<line>him heart-whole.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Pardon me, dear Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, an you be so tardy, come no more in my sight: I</line>
<line>had as lief be wooed of a snail.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Of a snail?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, of a snail; for though he comes slowly, he</line>
<line>carries his house on his head; a better jointure,</line>
<line>I think, than you make a woman: besides he brings</line>
<line>his destiny with him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>What's that?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why, horns, which such as you are fain to be</line>
<line>beholding to your wives for: but he comes armed in</line>
<line>his fortune and prevents the slander of his wife.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Virtue is no horn-maker; and my Rosalind is virtuous.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And I am your Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>It pleases him to call you so; but he hath a</line>
<line>Rosalind of a better leer than you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Come, woo me, woo me, for now I am in a holiday</line>
<line>humour and like enough to consent. What would you</line>
<line>say to me now, an I were your very very Rosalind?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I would kiss before I spoke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, you were better speak first, and when you were</line>
<line>gravelled for lack of matter, you might take</line>
<line>occasion to kiss. Very good orators, when they are</line>
<line>out, they will spit; and for lovers lacking--God</line>
<line>warn us!--matter, the cleanliest shift is to kiss.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>How if the kiss be denied?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Then she puts you to entreaty, and there begins new matter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Who could be out, being before his beloved mistress?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Marry, that should you, if I were your mistress, or</line>
<line>I should think my honesty ranker than my wit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>What, of my suit?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Not out of your apparel, and yet out of your suit.</line>
<line>Am not I your Rosalind?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I take some joy to say you are, because I would be</line>
<line>talking of her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Well in her person I say I will not have you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Then in mine own person I die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>No, faith, die by attorney. The poor world is</line>
<line>almost six thousand years old, and in all this time</line>
<line>there was not any man died in his own person,</line>
<line>videlicit, in a love-cause. Troilus had his brains</line>
<line>dashed out with a Grecian club; yet he did what he</line>
<line>could to die before, and he is one of the patterns</line>
<line>of love. Leander, he would have lived many a fair</line>
<line>year, though Hero had turned nun, if it had not been</line>
<line>for a hot midsummer night; for, good youth, he went</line>
<line>but forth to wash him in the Hellespont and being</line>
<line>taken with the cramp was drowned and the foolish</line>
<line>coroners of that age found it was 'Hero of Sestos.'</line>
<line>But these are all lies: men have died from time to</line>
<line>time and worms have eaten them, but not for love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I would not have my right Rosalind of this mind,</line>
<line>for, I protest, her frown might kill me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>By this hand, it will not kill a fly. But come, now</line>
<line>I will be your Rosalind in a more coming-on</line>
<line>disposition, and ask me what you will. I will grant</line>
<line>it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Then love me, Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Yes, faith, will I, Fridays and Saturdays and all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And wilt thou have me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, and twenty such.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>What sayest thou?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Are you not good?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I hope so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why then, can one desire too much of a good thing?</line>
<line>Come, sister, you shall be the priest and marry us.</line>
<line>Give me your hand, Orlando. What do you say, sister?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Pray thee, marry us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I cannot say the words.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>You must begin, 'Will you, Orlando--'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Go to. Will you, Orlando, have to wife this Rosalind?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, but when?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Why now; as fast as she can marry us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Then you must say 'I take thee, Rosalind, for wife.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I take thee, Rosalind, for wife.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I might ask you for your commission; but I do take</line>
<line>thee, Orlando, for my husband: there's a girl goes</line>
<line>before the priest; and certainly a woman's thought</line>
<line>runs before her actions.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>So do all thoughts; they are winged.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Now tell me how long you would have her after you</line>
<line>have possessed her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>For ever and a day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Say 'a day,' without the 'ever.' No, no, Orlando;</line>
<line>men are April when they woo, December when they wed:</line>
<line>maids are May when they are maids, but the sky</line>
<line>changes when they are wives. I will be more jealous</line>
<line>of thee than a Barbary cock-pigeon over his hen,</line>
<line>more clamorous than a parrot against rain, more</line>
<line>new-fangled than an ape, more giddy in my desires</line>
<line>than a monkey: I will weep for nothing, like Diana</line>
<line>in the fountain, and I will do that when you are</line>
<line>disposed to be merry; I will laugh like a hyen, and</line>
<line>that when thou art inclined to sleep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>But will my Rosalind do so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>By my life, she will do as I do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>O, but she is wise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Or else she could not have the wit to do this: the</line>
<line>wiser, the waywarder: make the doors upon a woman's</line>
<line>wit and it will out at the casement; shut that and</line>
<line>'twill out at the key-hole; stop that, 'twill fly</line>
<line>with the smoke out at the chimney.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>A man that had a wife with such a wit, he might say</line>
<line>'Wit, whither wilt?'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Nay, you might keep that cheque for it till you met</line>
<line>your wife's wit going to your neighbour's bed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And what wit could wit have to excuse that?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Marry, to say she came to seek you there. You shall</line>
<line>never take her without her answer, unless you take</line>
<line>her without her tongue. O, that woman that cannot</line>
<line>make her fault her husband's occasion, let her</line>
<line>never nurse her child herself, for she will breed</line>
<line>it like a fool!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>For these two hours, Rosalind, I will leave thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Alas! dear love, I cannot lack thee two hours.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I must attend the duke at dinner: by two o'clock I</line>
<line>will be with thee again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Ay, go your ways, go your ways; I knew what you</line>
<line>would prove: my friends told me as much, and I</line>
<line>thought no less: that flattering tongue of yours</line>
<line>won me: 'tis but one cast away, and so, come,</line>
<line>death! Two o'clock is your hour?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Ay, sweet Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>By my troth, and in good earnest, and so God mend</line>
<line>me, and by all pretty oaths that are not dangerous,</line>
<line>if you break one jot of your promise or come one</line>
<line>minute behind your hour, I will think you the most</line>
<line>pathetical break-promise and the most hollow lover</line>
<line>and the most unworthy of her you call Rosalind that</line>
<line>may be chosen out of the gross band of the</line>
<line>unfaithful: therefore beware my censure and keep</line>
<line>your promise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>With no less religion than if thou wert indeed my</line>
<line>Rosalind: so adieu.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Well, Time is the old justice that examines all such</line>
<line>offenders, and let Time try: adieu.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit ORLANDO</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>You have simply misused our sex in your love-prate:</line>
<line>we must have your doublet and hose plucked over your</line>
<line>head, and show the world what the bird hath done to</line>
<line>her own nest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O coz, coz, coz, my pretty little coz, that thou</line>
<line>didst know how many fathom deep I am in love! But</line>
<line>it cannot be sounded: my affection hath an unknown</line>
<line>bottom, like the bay of Portugal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Or rather, bottomless, that as fast as you pour</line>
<line>affection in, it runs out.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>No, that same wicked bastard of Venus that was begot</line>
<line>of thought, conceived of spleen and born of madness,</line>
<line>that blind rascally boy that abuses every one's eyes</line>
<line>because his own are out, let him be judge how deep I</line>
<line>am in love. I'll tell thee, Aliena, I cannot be out</line>
<line>of the sight of Orlando: I'll go find a shadow and</line>
<line>sigh till he come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>And I'll sleep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter JAQUES, Lords, and Foresters</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Which is he that killed the deer?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">A Lord</speaker>
<line>Sir, it was I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Let's present him to the duke, like a Roman</line>
<line>conqueror; and it would do well to set the deer's</line>
<line>horns upon his head, for a branch of victory. Have</line>
<line>you no song, forester, for this purpose?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Forester</speaker>
<line>Yes, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Sing it: 'tis no matter how it be in tune, so it</line>
<line>make noise enough.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<bridgehead role="subhead">SONG.</bridgehead>
<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Forester</speaker>
<line>What shall he have that kill'd the deer?</line>
<line>His leather skin and horns to wear.</line>
<line>Then sing him home;</line>
<para role="stagedir">The rest shall bear this burden</para>
<line>Take thou no scorn to wear the horn;</line>
<line>It was a crest ere thou wast born:</line>
<line>Thy father's father wore it,</line>
<line>And thy father bore it:</line>
<line>The horn, the horn, the lusty horn</line>
<line>Is not a thing to laugh to scorn.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND and CELIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>How say you now? Is it not past two o'clock? and</line>
<line>here much Orlando!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I warrant you, with pure love and troubled brain, he</line>
<line>hath ta'en his bow and arrows and is gone forth to</line>
<line>sleep. Look, who comes here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter SILVIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>My errand is to you, fair youth;</line>
<line>My gentle Phebe bid me give you this:</line>
<line>I know not the contents; but, as I guess</line>
<line>By the stern brow and waspish action</line>
<line>Which she did use as she was writing of it,</line>
<line>It bears an angry tenor: pardon me:</line>
<line>I am but as a guiltless messenger.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Patience herself would startle at this letter</line>
<line>And play the swaggerer; bear this, bear all:</line>
<line>She says I am not fair, that I lack manners;</line>
<line>She calls me proud, and that she could not love me,</line>
<line>Were man as rare as phoenix. 'Od's my will!</line>
<line>Her love is not the hare that I do hunt:</line>
<line>Why writes she so to me? Well, shepherd, well,</line>
<line>This is a letter of your own device.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>No, I protest, I know not the contents:</line>
<line>Phebe did write it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Come, come, you are a fool</line>
<line>And turn'd into the extremity of love.</line>
<line>I saw her hand: she has a leathern hand.</line>
<line>A freestone-colour'd hand; I verily did think</line>
<line>That her old gloves were on, but 'twas her hands:</line>
<line>She has a huswife's hand; but that's no matter:</line>
<line>I say she never did invent this letter;</line>
<line>This is a man's invention and his hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Sure, it is hers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why, 'tis a boisterous and a cruel style.</line>
<line>A style for-challengers; why, she defies me,</line>
<line>Like Turk to Christian: women's gentle brain</line>
<line>Could not drop forth such giant-rude invention</line>
<line>Such Ethiope words, blacker in their effect</line>
<line>Than in their countenance. Will you hear the letter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>So please you, for I never heard it yet;</line>
<line>Yet heard too much of Phebe's cruelty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>She Phebes me: mark how the tyrant writes.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Reads</para>
<line>Art thou god to shepherd turn'd,</line>
<line>That a maiden's heart hath burn'd?</line>
<line>Can a woman rail thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Call you this railing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Reads</phrase></line>
<line>Why, thy godhead laid apart,</line>
<line>Warr'st thou with a woman's heart?</line>
<line>Did you ever hear such railing?</line>
<line>Whiles the eye of man did woo me,</line>
<line>That could do no vengeance to me.</line>
<line>Meaning me a beast.</line>
<line>If the scorn of your bright eyne</line>
<line>Have power to raise such love in mine,</line>
<line>Alack, in me what strange effect</line>
<line>Would they work in mild aspect!</line>
<line>Whiles you chid me, I did love;</line>
<line>How then might your prayers move!</line>
<line>He that brings this love to thee</line>
<line>Little knows this love in me:</line>
<line>And by him seal up thy mind;</line>
<line>Whether that thy youth and kind</line>
<line>Will the faithful offer take</line>
<line>Of me and all that I can make;</line>
<line>Or else by him my love deny,</line>
<line>And then I'll study how to die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Call you this chiding?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Alas, poor shepherd!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Do you pity him? no, he deserves no pity. Wilt</line>
<line>thou love such a woman? What, to make thee an</line>
<line>instrument and play false strains upon thee! not to</line>
<line>be endured! Well, go your way to her, for I see</line>
<line>love hath made thee a tame snake, and say this to</line>
<line>her: that if she love me, I charge her to love</line>
<line>thee; if she will not, I will never have her unless</line>
<line>thou entreat for her. If you be a true lover,</line>
<line>hence, and not a word; for here comes more company.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit SILVIUS</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter OLIVER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, fair ones: pray you, if you know,</line>
<line>Where in the purlieus of this forest stands</line>
<line>A sheep-cote fenced about with olive trees?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>West of this place, down in the neighbour bottom:</line>
<line>The rank of osiers by the murmuring stream</line>
<line>Left on your right hand brings you to the place.</line>
<line>But at this hour the house doth keep itself;</line>
<line>There's none within.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>If that an eye may profit by a tongue,</line>
<line>Then should I know you by description;</line>
<line>Such garments and such years: 'The boy is fair,</line>
<line>Of female favour, and bestows himself</line>
<line>Like a ripe sister: the woman low</line>
<line>And browner than her brother.' Are not you</line>
<line>The owner of the house I did inquire for?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>It is no boast, being ask'd, to say we are.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Orlando doth commend him to you both,</line>
<line>And to that youth he calls his Rosalind</line>
<line>He sends this bloody napkin. Are you he?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I am: what must we understand by this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Some of my shame; if you will know of me</line>
<line>What man I am, and how, and why, and where</line>
<line>This handkercher was stain'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>I pray you, tell it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>When last the young Orlando parted from you</line>
<line>He left a promise to return again</line>
<line>Within an hour, and pacing through the forest,</line>
<line>Chewing the food of sweet and bitter fancy,</line>
<line>Lo, what befell! he threw his eye aside,</line>
<line>And mark what object did present itself:</line>
<line>Under an oak, whose boughs were moss'd with age</line>
<line>And high top bald with dry antiquity,</line>
<line>A wretched ragged man, o'ergrown with hair,</line>
<line>Lay sleeping on his back: about his neck</line>
<line>A green and gilded snake had wreathed itself,</line>
<line>Who with her head nimble in threats approach'd</line>
<line>The opening of his mouth; but suddenly,</line>
<line>Seeing Orlando, it unlink'd itself,</line>
<line>And with indented glides did slip away</line>
<line>Into a bush: under which bush's shade</line>
<line>A lioness, with udders all drawn dry,</line>
<line>Lay couching, head on ground, with catlike watch,</line>
<line>When that the sleeping man should stir; for 'tis</line>
<line>The royal disposition of that beast</line>
<line>To prey on nothing that doth seem as dead:</line>
<line>This seen, Orlando did approach the man</line>
<line>And found it was his brother, his elder brother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>O, I have heard him speak of that same brother;</line>
<line>And he did render him the most unnatural</line>
<line>That lived amongst men.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>And well he might so do,</line>
<line>For well I know he was unnatural.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But, to Orlando: did he leave him there,</line>
<line>Food to the suck'd and hungry lioness?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Twice did he turn his back and purposed so;</line>
<line>But kindness, nobler ever than revenge,</line>
<line>And nature, stronger than his just occasion,</line>
<line>Made him give battle to the lioness,</line>
<line>Who quickly fell before him: in which hurtling</line>
<line>From miserable slumber I awaked.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Are you his brother?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Wast you he rescued?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Was't you that did so oft contrive to kill him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>'Twas I; but 'tis not I I do not shame</line>
<line>To tell you what I was, since my conversion</line>
<line>So sweetly tastes, being the thing I am.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But, for the bloody napkin?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>By and by.</line>
<line>When from the first to last betwixt us two</line>
<line>Tears our recountments had most kindly bathed,</line>
<line>As how I came into that desert place:--</line>
<line>In brief, he led me to the gentle duke,</line>
<line>Who gave me fresh array and entertainment,</line>
<line>Committing me unto my brother's love;</line>
<line>Who led me instantly unto his cave,</line>
<line>There stripp'd himself, and here upon his arm</line>
<line>The lioness had torn some flesh away,</line>
<line>Which all this while had bled; and now he fainted</line>
<line>And cried, in fainting, upon Rosalind.</line>
<line>Brief, I recover'd him, bound up his wound;</line>
<line>And, after some small space, being strong at heart,</line>
<line>He sent me hither, stranger as I am,</line>
<line>To tell this story, that you might excuse</line>
<line>His broken promise, and to give this napkin</line>
<line>Dyed in his blood unto the shepherd youth</line>
<line>That he in sport doth call his Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">ROSALIND swoons</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Why, how now, Ganymede! sweet Ganymede!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Many will swoon when they do look on blood.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>There is more in it. Cousin Ganymede!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Look, he recovers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I would I were at home.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>We'll lead you thither.</line>
<line>I pray you, will you take him by the arm?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Be of good cheer, youth: you a man! you lack a</line>
<line>man's heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I do so, I confess it. Ah, sirrah, a body would</line>
<line>think this was well counterfeited! I pray you, tell</line>
<line>your brother how well I counterfeited. Heigh-ho!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>This was not counterfeit: there is too great</line>
<line>testimony in your complexion that it was a passion</line>
<line>of earnest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Counterfeit, I assure you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Well then, take a good heart and counterfeit to be a man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>So I do: but, i' faith, I should have been a woman by right.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CELIA</speaker>
<line>Come, you look paler and paler: pray you, draw</line>
<line>homewards. Good sir, go with us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>That will I, for I must bear answer back</line>
<line>How you excuse my brother, Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I shall devise something: but, I pray you, commend</line>
<line>my counterfeiting to him. Will you go?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT V</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>We shall find a time, Audrey; patience, gentle Audrey.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Faith, the priest was good enough, for all the old</line>
<line>gentleman's saying.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>A most wicked Sir Oliver, Audrey, a most vile</line>
<line>Martext. But, Audrey, there is a youth here in the</line>
<line>forest lays claim to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Ay, I know who 'tis; he hath no interest in me in</line>
<line>the world: here comes the man you mean.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>It is meat and drink to me to see a clown: by my</line>
<line>troth, we that have good wits have much to answer</line>
<line>for; we shall be flouting; we cannot hold.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter WILLIAM</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>Good even, Audrey.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>God ye good even, William.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>And good even to you, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Good even, gentle friend. Cover thy head, cover thy</line>
<line>head; nay, prithee, be covered. How old are you, friend?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>Five and twenty, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>A ripe age. Is thy name William?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>William, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>A fair name. Wast born i' the forest here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>Ay, sir, I thank God.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>'Thank God;' a good answer. Art rich?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>Faith, sir, so so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>'So so' is good, very good, very excellent good; and</line>
<line>yet it is not; it is but so so. Art thou wise?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>Ay, sir, I have a pretty wit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Why, thou sayest well. I do now remember a saying,</line>
<line>'The fool doth think he is wise, but the wise man</line>
<line>knows himself to be a fool.' The heathen</line>
<line>philosopher, when he had a desire to eat a grape,</line>
<line>would open his lips when he put it into his mouth;</line>
<line>meaning thereby that grapes were made to eat and</line>
<line>lips to open. You do love this maid?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>I do, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Give me your hand. Art thou learned?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>No, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Then learn this of me: to have, is to have; for it</line>
<line>is a figure in rhetoric that drink, being poured out</line>
<line>of a cup into a glass, by filling the one doth empty</line>
<line>the other; for all your writers do consent that ipse</line>
<line>is he: now, you are not ipse, for I am he.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>Which he, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>He, sir, that must marry this woman. Therefore, you</line>
<line>clown, abandon,--which is in the vulgar leave,--the</line>
<line>society,--which in the boorish is company,--of this</line>
<line>female,--which in the common is woman; which</line>
<line>together is, abandon the society of this female, or,</line>
<line>clown, thou perishest; or, to thy better</line>
<line>understanding, diest; or, to wit I kill thee, make</line>
<line>thee away, translate thy life into death, thy</line>
<line>liberty into bondage: I will deal in poison with</line>
<line>thee, or in bastinado, or in steel; I will bandy</line>
<line>with thee in faction; I will o'errun thee with</line>
<line>policy; I will kill thee a hundred and fifty ways:</line>
<line>therefore tremble and depart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>Do, good William.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WILLIAM</speaker>
<line>God rest you merry, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CORIN</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CORIN</speaker>
<line>Our master and mistress seeks you; come, away, away!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Trip, Audrey! trip, Audrey! I attend, I attend.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ORLANDO and OLIVER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Is't possible that on so little acquaintance you</line>
<line>should like her? that but seeing you should love</line>
<line>her? and loving woo? and, wooing, she should</line>
<line>grant? and will you persever to enjoy her?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>Neither call the giddiness of it in question, the</line>
<line>poverty of her, the small acquaintance, my sudden</line>
<line>wooing, nor her sudden consenting; but say with me,</line>
<line>I love Aliena; say with her that she loves me;</line>
<line>consent with both that we may enjoy each other: it</line>
<line>shall be to your good; for my father's house and all</line>
<line>the revenue that was old Sir Rowland's will I</line>
<line>estate upon you, and here live and die a shepherd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>You have my consent. Let your wedding be to-morrow:</line>
<line>thither will I invite the duke and all's contented</line>
<line>followers. Go you and prepare Aliena; for look</line>
<line>you, here comes my Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>God save you, brother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">OLIVER</speaker>
<line>And you, fair sister.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O, my dear Orlando, how it grieves me to see thee</line>
<line>wear thy heart in a scarf!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>It is my arm.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I thought thy heart had been wounded with the claws</line>
<line>of a lion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Wounded it is, but with the eyes of a lady.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Did your brother tell you how I counterfeited to</line>
<line>swoon when he showed me your handkerchief?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Ay, and greater wonders than that.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>O, I know where you are: nay, 'tis true: there was</line>
<line>never any thing so sudden but the fight of two rams</line>
<line>and Caesar's thrasonical brag of 'I came, saw, and</line>
<line>overcame:' for your brother and my sister no sooner</line>
<line>met but they looked, no sooner looked but they</line>
<line>loved, no sooner loved but they sighed, no sooner</line>
<line>sighed but they asked one another the reason, no</line>
<line>sooner knew the reason but they sought the remedy;</line>
<line>and in these degrees have they made a pair of stairs</line>
<line>to marriage which they will climb incontinent, or</line>
<line>else be incontinent before marriage: they are in</line>
<line>the very wrath of love and they will together; clubs</line>
<line>cannot part them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>They shall be married to-morrow, and I will bid the</line>
<line>duke to the nuptial. But, O, how bitter a thing it</line>
<line>is to look into happiness through another man's</line>
<line>eyes! By so much the more shall I to-morrow be at</line>
<line>the height of heart-heaviness, by how much I shall</line>
<line>think my brother happy in having what he wishes for.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Why then, to-morrow I cannot serve your turn for Rosalind?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I can live no longer by thinking.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I will weary you then no longer with idle talking.</line>
<line>Know of me then, for now I speak to some purpose,</line>
<line>that I know you are a gentleman of good conceit: I</line>
<line>speak not this that you should bear a good opinion</line>
<line>of my knowledge, insomuch I say I know you are;</line>
<line>neither do I labour for a greater esteem than may in</line>
<line>some little measure draw a belief from you, to do</line>
<line>yourself good and not to grace me. Believe then, if</line>
<line>you please, that I can do strange things: I have,</line>
<line>since I was three year old, conversed with a</line>
<line>magician, most profound in his art and yet not</line>
<line>damnable. If you do love Rosalind so near the heart</line>
<line>as your gesture cries it out, when your brother</line>
<line>marries Aliena, shall you marry her: I know into</line>
<line>what straits of fortune she is driven; and it is</line>
<line>not impossible to me, if it appear not inconvenient</line>
<line>to you, to set her before your eyes tomorrow human</line>
<line>as she is and without any danger.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Speakest thou in sober meanings?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>By my life, I do; which I tender dearly, though I</line>
<line>say I am a magician. Therefore, put you in your</line>
<line>best array: bid your friends; for if you will be</line>
<line>married to-morrow, you shall, and to Rosalind, if you will.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SILVIUS and PHEBE</para>
<line>Look, here comes a lover of mine and a lover of hers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Youth, you have done me much ungentleness,</line>
<line>To show the letter that I writ to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I care not if I have: it is my study</line>
<line>To seem despiteful and ungentle to you:</line>
<line>You are there followed by a faithful shepherd;</line>
<line>Look upon him, love him; he worships you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Good shepherd, tell this youth what 'tis to love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>It is to be all made of sighs and tears;</line>
<line>And so am I for Phebe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>And I for Ganymede.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And I for Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And I for no woman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>It is to be all made of faith and service;</line>
<line>And so am I for Phebe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>And I for Ganymede.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And I for Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And I for no woman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>It is to be all made of fantasy,</line>
<line>All made of passion and all made of wishes,</line>
<line>All adoration, duty, and observance,</line>
<line>All humbleness, all patience and impatience,</line>
<line>All purity, all trial, all observance;</line>
<line>And so am I for Phebe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>And so am I for Ganymede.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>And so am I for Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And so am I for no woman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Who do you speak to, 'Why blame you me to love you?'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>To her that is not here, nor doth not hear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Pray you, no more of this; 'tis like the howling</line>
<line>of Irish wolves against the moon.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To SILVIUS</para>
<line>I will help you, if I can:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To PHEBE</para>
<line>I would love you, if I could. To-morrow meet me all together.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To PHEBE</para>
<line>I will marry you, if ever I marry woman, and I'll be</line>
<line>married to-morrow:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To ORLANDO</para>
<line>I will satisfy you, if ever I satisfied man, and you</line>
<line>shall be married to-morrow:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To SILVIUS</para>
<line>I will content you, if what pleases you contents</line>
<line>you, and you shall be married to-morrow.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To ORLANDO</para>
<line>As you love Rosalind, meet:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To SILVIUS</para>
<line>as you love Phebe, meet: and as I love no woman,</line>
<line>I'll meet. So fare you well: I have left you commands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>I'll not fail, if I live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>Nor I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>Nor I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>To-morrow is the joyful day, Audrey; to-morrow will</line>
<line>we be married.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AUDREY</speaker>
<line>I do desire it with all my heart; and I hope it is</line>
<line>no dishonest desire to desire to be a woman of the</line>
<line>world. Here comes two of the banished duke's pages.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter two Pages</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Page</speaker>
<line>Well met, honest gentleman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>By my troth, well met. Come, sit, sit, and a song.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Page</speaker>
<line>We are for you: sit i' the middle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Page</speaker>
<line>Shall we clap into't roundly, without hawking or</line>
<line>spitting or saying we are hoarse, which are the only</line>
<line>prologues to a bad voice?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Page</speaker>
<line>I'faith, i'faith; and both in a tune, like two</line>
<line>gipsies on a horse.</line>
<bridgehead role="subhead">SONG.</bridgehead>
<line>It was a lover and his lass,</line>
<line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,</line>
<line>That o'er the green corn-field did pass</line>
<line>In the spring time, the only pretty ring time,</line>
<line>When birds do sing, hey ding a ding, ding:</line>
<line>Sweet lovers love the spring.</line>
<line>Between the acres of the rye,</line>
<line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino</line>
<line>These pretty country folks would lie,</line>
<line>In spring time, &amp;c.</line>
<line>This carol they began that hour,</line>
<line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,</line>
<line>How that a life was but a flower</line>
<line>In spring time, &amp;c.</line>
<line>And therefore take the present time,</line>
<line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino;</line>
<line>For love is crowned with the prime</line>
<line>In spring time, &amp;c.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Truly, young gentlemen, though there was no great</line>
<line>matter in the ditty, yet the note was very</line>
<line>untuneable.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Page</speaker>
<line>You are deceived, sir: we kept time, we lost not our time.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>By my troth, yes; I count it but time lost to hear</line>
<line>such a foolish song. God be wi' you; and God mend</line>
<line>your voices! Come, Audrey.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE SENIOR, AMIENS, JAQUES, ORLANDO, OLIVER,
and CELIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Dost thou believe, Orlando, that the boy</line>
<line>Can do all this that he hath promised?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>I sometimes do believe, and sometimes do not;</line>
<line>As those that fear they hope, and know they fear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter ROSALIND, SILVIUS, and PHEBE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>Patience once more, whiles our compact is urged:</line>
<line>You say, if I bring in your Rosalind,</line>
<line>You will bestow her on Orlando here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>That would I, had I kingdoms to give with her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>And you say, you will have her, when I bring her?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>That would I, were I of all kingdoms king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>You say, you'll marry me, if I be willing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>That will I, should I die the hour after.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>But if you do refuse to marry me,</line>
<line>You'll give yourself to this most faithful shepherd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>So is the bargain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>You say, that you'll have Phebe, if she will?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SILVIUS</speaker>
<line>Though to have her and death were both one thing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I have promised to make all this matter even.</line>
<line>Keep you your word, O duke, to give your daughter;</line>
<line>You yours, Orlando, to receive his daughter:</line>
<line>Keep your word, Phebe, that you'll marry me,</line>
<line>Or else refusing me, to wed this shepherd:</line>
<line>Keep your word, Silvius, that you'll marry her.</line>
<line>If she refuse me: and from hence I go,</line>
<line>To make these doubts all even.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt ROSALIND and CELIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>I do remember in this shepherd boy</line>
<line>Some lively touches of my daughter's favour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>My lord, the first time that I ever saw him</line>
<line>Methought he was a brother to your daughter:</line>
<line>But, my good lord, this boy is forest-born,</line>
<line>And hath been tutor'd in the rudiments</line>
<line>Of many desperate studies by his uncle,</line>
<line>Whom he reports to be a great magician,</line>
<line>Obscured in the circle of this forest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>There is, sure, another flood toward, and these</line>
<line>couples are coming to the ark. Here comes a pair of</line>
<line>very strange beasts, which in all tongues are called fools.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Salutation and greeting to you all!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Good my lord, bid him welcome: this is the</line>
<line>motley-minded gentleman that I have so often met in</line>
<line>the forest: he hath been a courtier, he swears.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>If any man doubt that, let him put me to my</line>
<line>purgation. I have trod a measure; I have flattered</line>
<line>a lady; I have been politic with my friend, smooth</line>
<line>with mine enemy; I have undone three tailors; I have</line>
<line>had four quarrels, and like to have fought one.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>And how was that ta'en up?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Faith, we met, and found the quarrel was upon the</line>
<line>seventh cause.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>How seventh cause? Good my lord, like this fellow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>I like him very well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>God 'ild you, sir; I desire you of the like. I</line>
<line>press in here, sir, amongst the rest of the country</line>
<line>copulatives, to swear and to forswear: according as</line>
<line>marriage binds and blood breaks: a poor virgin,</line>
<line>sir, an ill-favoured thing, sir, but mine own; a poor</line>
<line>humour of mine, sir, to take that that no man else</line>
<line>will: rich honesty dwells like a miser, sir, in a</line>
<line>poor house; as your pearl in your foul oyster.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>By my faith, he is very swift and sententious.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>According to the fool's bolt, sir, and such dulcet diseases.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>But, for the seventh cause; how did you find the</line>
<line>quarrel on the seventh cause?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>Upon a lie seven times removed:--bear your body more</line>
<line>seeming, Audrey:--as thus, sir. I did dislike the</line>
<line>cut of a certain courtier's beard: he sent me word,</line>
<line>if I said his beard was not cut well, he was in the</line>
<line>mind it was: this is called the Retort Courteous.</line>
<line>If I sent him word again 'it was not well cut,' he</line>
<line>would send me word, he cut it to please himself:</line>
<line>this is called the Quip Modest. If again 'it was</line>
<line>not well cut,' he disabled my judgment: this is</line>
<line>called the Reply Churlish. If again 'it was not</line>
<line>well cut,' he would answer, I spake not true: this</line>
<line>is called the Reproof Valiant. If again 'it was not</line>
<line>well cut,' he would say I lied: this is called the</line>
<line>Counter-cheque Quarrelsome: and so to the Lie</line>
<line>Circumstantial and the Lie Direct.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>And how oft did you say his beard was not well cut?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>I durst go no further than the Lie Circumstantial,</line>
<line>nor he durst not give me the Lie Direct; and so we</line>
<line>measured swords and parted.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Can you nominate in order now the degrees of the lie?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
<line>O sir, we quarrel in print, by the book; as you have</line>
<line>books for good manners: I will name you the degrees.</line>
<line>The first, the Retort Courteous; the second, the</line>
<line>Quip Modest; the third, the Reply Churlish; the</line>
<line>fourth, the Reproof Valiant; the fifth, the</line>
<line>Countercheque Quarrelsome; the sixth, the Lie with</line>
<line>Circumstance; the seventh, the Lie Direct. All</line>
<line>these you may avoid but the Lie Direct; and you may</line>
<line>avoid that too, with an If. I knew when seven</line>
<line>justices could not take up a quarrel, but when the</line>
<line>parties were met themselves, one of them thought but</line>
<line>of an If, as, 'If you said so, then I said so;' and</line>
<line>they shook hands and swore brothers. Your If is the</line>
<line>only peacemaker; much virtue in If.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Is not this a rare fellow, my lord? he's as good at</line>
<line>any thing and yet a fool.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>He uses his folly like a stalking-horse and under</line>
<line>the presentation of that he shoots his wit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HYMEN, ROSALIND, and CELIA</para>
<para role="stagedir">Still Music</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HYMEN</speaker>
<line>Then is there mirth in heaven,</line>
<line>When earthly things made even</line>
<line>Atone together.</line>
<line>Good duke, receive thy daughter</line>
<line>Hymen from heaven brought her,</line>
<line>Yea, brought her hither,</line>
<line>That thou mightst join her hand with his</line>
<line>Whose heart within his bosom is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To DUKE SENIOR</phrase>  To you I give myself, for I am yours.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To ORLANDO</para>
<line>To you I give myself, for I am yours.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>If there be truth in sight, you are my daughter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ORLANDO</speaker>
<line>If there be truth in sight, you are my Rosalind.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>If sight and shape be true,</line>
<line>Why then, my love adieu!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>I'll have no father, if you be not he:</line>
<line>I'll have no husband, if you be not he:</line>
<line>Nor ne'er wed woman, if you be not she.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HYMEN</speaker>
<line>Peace, ho! I bar confusion:</line>
<line>'Tis I must make conclusion</line>
<line>Of these most strange events:</line>
<line>Here's eight that must take hands</line>
<line>To join in Hymen's bands,</line>
<line>If truth holds true contents.</line>
<line>You and you no cross shall part:</line>
<line>You and you are heart in heart</line>
<line>You to his love must accord,</line>
<line>Or have a woman to your lord:</line>
<line>You and you are sure together,</line>
<line>As the winter to foul weather.</line>
<line>Whiles a wedlock-hymn we sing,</line>
<line>Feed yourselves with questioning;</line>
<line>That reason wonder may diminish,</line>
<line>How thus we met, and these things finish.</line>
<bridgehead role="subhead">SONG.</bridgehead>
<line>Wedding is great Juno's crown:</line>
<line>O blessed bond of board and bed!</line>
<line>'Tis Hymen peoples every town;</line>
<line>High wedlock then be honoured:</line>
<line>Honour, high honour and renown,</line>
<line>To Hymen, god of every town!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>O my dear niece, welcome thou art to me!</line>
<line>Even daughter, welcome, in no less degree.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHEBE</speaker>
<line>I will not eat my word, now thou art mine;</line>
<line>Thy faith my fancy to thee doth combine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter JAQUES DE BOYS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES DE BOYS</speaker>
<line>Let me have audience for a word or two:</line>
<line>I am the second son of old Sir Rowland,</line>
<line>That bring these tidings to this fair assembly.</line>
<line>Duke Frederick, hearing how that every day</line>
<line>Men of great worth resorted to this forest,</line>
<line>Address'd a mighty power; which were on foot,</line>
<line>In his own conduct, purposely to take</line>
<line>His brother here and put him to the sword:</line>
<line>And to the skirts of this wild wood he came;</line>
<line>Where meeting with an old religious man,</line>
<line>After some question with him, was converted</line>
<line>Both from his enterprise and from the world,</line>
<line>His crown bequeathing to his banish'd brother,</line>
<line>And all their lands restored to them again</line>
<line>That were with him exiled. This to be true,</line>
<line>I do engage my life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Welcome, young man;</line>
<line>Thou offer'st fairly to thy brothers' wedding:</line>
<line>To one his lands withheld, and to the other</line>
<line>A land itself at large, a potent dukedom.</line>
<line>First, in this forest, let us do those ends</line>
<line>That here were well begun and well begot:</line>
<line>And after, every of this happy number</line>
<line>That have endured shrewd days and nights with us</line>
<line>Shall share the good of our returned fortune,</line>
<line>According to the measure of their states.</line>
<line>Meantime, forget this new-fall'n dignity</line>
<line>And fall into our rustic revelry.</line>
<line>Play, music! And you, brides and bridegrooms all,</line>
<line>With measure heap'd in joy, to the measures fall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>Sir, by your patience. If I heard you rightly,</line>
<line>The duke hath put on a religious life</line>
<line>And thrown into neglect the pompous court?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES DE BOYS</speaker>
<line>He hath.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>To him will I : out of these convertites</line>
<line>There is much matter to be heard and learn'd.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To DUKE SENIOR</para>
<line>You to your former honour I bequeath;</line>
<line>Your patience and your virtue well deserves it:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To ORLANDO</para>
<line>You to a love that your true faith doth merit:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To OLIVER</para>
<line>You to your land and love and great allies:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To SILVIUS</para>
<line>You to a long and well-deserved bed:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To TOUCHSTONE</para>
<line>And you to wrangling; for thy loving voyage</line>
<line>Is but for two months victuall'd. So, to your pleasures:</line>
<line>I am for other than for dancing measures.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Stay, Jaques, stay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JAQUES</speaker>
<line>To see no pastime I what you would have</line>
<line>I'll stay to know at your abandon'd cave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
<line>Proceed, proceed: we will begin these rites,</line>
<line>As we do trust they'll end, in true delights.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">A dance</para>
</section>

<section role="epilogue"><title>EPILOGUE</title>
<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ROSALIND</speaker>
<line>It is not the fashion to see the lady the epilogue;</line>
<line>but it is no more unhandsome than to see the lord</line>
<line>the prologue. If it be true that good wine needs</line>
<line>no bush, 'tis true that a good play needs no</line>
<line>epilogue; yet to good wine they do use good bushes,</line>
<line>and good plays prove the better by the help of good</line>
<line>epilogues. What a case am I in then, that am</line>
<line>neither a good epilogue nor cannot insinuate with</line>
<line>you in the behalf of a good play! I am not</line>
<line>furnished like a beggar, therefore to beg will not</line>
<line>become me: my way is to conjure you; and I'll begin</line>
<line>with the women. I charge you, O women, for the love</line>
<line>you bear to men, to like as much of this play as</line>
<line>please you: and I charge you, O men, for the love</line>
<line>you bear to women--as I perceive by your simpering,</line>
<line>none of you hates them--that between you and the</line>
<line>women the play may please. If I were a woman I</line>
<line>would kiss as many of you as had beards that pleased</line>
<line>me, complexions that liked me and breaths that I</line>
<line>defied not: and, I am sure, as many as have good</line>
<line>beards or good faces or sweet breaths will, for my</line>
<line>kind offer, when I make curtsy, bid me farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>