<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="publishers.rnc" type="compact"?><book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" role="play">
<title>The First Part of Henry the Fourth</title>

<info><author><personname><firstname>William</firstname><surname>Shakespeare</surname></personname></author><legalnotice>
<para>ASCII text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</para>
<para>SGML markup by Jon Bosak, 1992-1994.</para>
<para>XML version by Jon Bosak, 1996-1999.</para>
<para>The XML markup in this version is Copyright © 1999 Jon Bosak.
This work may freely be distributed on condition that it not be
modified or altered in any way.</para>
</legalnotice>     <copyright><year>2008</year><holder>Scott Hudson</holder></copyright></info>

<preface>
<title>Dramatis Personae</title>

<para><personname role="persona">KING HENRY, the Fourth. </personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">HENRY, Prince of Wales</personname><personname role="persona">JOHN of Lancaster</personname></member><member>sons of the King</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">WESTMORELAND</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR WALTER BLUNT</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">THOMAS PERCY, Earl of Worcester. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">HENRY PERCY, Earl of Northumberland. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">HENRY PERCY, surnamed HOTSPUR, his son. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">EDMUND MORTIMER, Earl of March. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">RICHARD SCROOP, Archbishop of York. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">ARCHIBALD, Earl of Douglas. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">OWEN GLENDOWER</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR RICHARD VERNON</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR JOHN FALSTAFF</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR MICHAEL, a friend to the Archbishop of York.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">POINS</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">GADSHILL</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">PETO</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">BARDOLPH</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">FRANCIS, a waiter.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LADY PERCY, wife to Hotspur, and sister to Mortimer.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LADY MORTIMER, daughter to Glendower, and wife to Mortimer.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">MISTRESS QUICKLY, hostess of a tavern in Eastcheap. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Lords, Officers, Sheriff, Vintner, Chamberlain, Drawers, two Carriers, Travellers, Attendants, and an Ostler.</personname></para>
    <para role="scndescr">SCENE  England.</para>
</preface>




<chapter role="act"><title>ACT I</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  London. The palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING HENRY, LORD JOHN OF LANCASTER, the EARL
of WESTMORELAND, SIR WALTER BLUNT, and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>So shaken as we are, so wan with care,</line>
<line>Find we a time for frighted peace to pant,</line>
<line>And breathe short-winded accents of new broils</line>
<line>To be commenced in strands afar remote.</line>
<line>No more the thirsty entrance of this soil</line>
<line>Shall daub her lips with her own children's blood;</line>
<line>Nor more shall trenching war channel her fields,</line>
<line>Nor bruise her flowerets with the armed hoofs</line>
<line>Of hostile paces: those opposed eyes,</line>
<line>Which, like the meteors of a troubled heaven,</line>
<line>All of one nature, of one substance bred,</line>
<line>Did lately meet in the intestine shock</line>
<line>And furious close of civil butchery</line>
<line>Shall now, in mutual well-beseeming ranks,</line>
<line>March all one way and be no more opposed</line>
<line>Against acquaintance, kindred and allies:</line>
<line>The edge of war, like an ill-sheathed knife,</line>
<line>No more shall cut his master. Therefore, friends,</line>
<line>As far as to the sepulchre of Christ,</line>
<line>Whose soldier now, under whose blessed cross</line>
<line>We are impressed and engaged to fight,</line>
<line>Forthwith a power of English shall we levy;</line>
<line>Whose arms were moulded in their mothers' womb</line>
<line>To chase these pagans in those holy fields</line>
<line>Over whose acres walk'd those blessed feet</line>
<line>Which fourteen hundred years ago were nail'd</line>
<line>For our advantage on the bitter cross.</line>
<line>But this our purpose now is twelve month old,</line>
<line>And bootless 'tis to tell you we will go:</line>
<line>Therefore we meet not now. Then let me hear</line>
<line>Of you, my gentle cousin Westmoreland,</line>
<line>What yesternight our council did decree</line>
<line>In forwarding this dear expedience.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>My liege, this haste was hot in question,</line>
<line>And many limits of the charge set down</line>
<line>But yesternight: when all athwart there came</line>
<line>A post from Wales loaden with heavy news;</line>
<line>Whose worst was, that the noble Mortimer,</line>
<line>Leading the men of Herefordshire to fight</line>
<line>Against the irregular and wild Glendower,</line>
<line>Was by the rude hands of that Welshman taken,</line>
<line>A thousand of his people butchered;</line>
<line>Upon whose dead corpse there was such misuse,</line>
<line>Such beastly shameless transformation,</line>
<line>By those Welshwomen done as may not be</line>
<line>Without much shame retold or spoken of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>It seems then that the tidings of this broil</line>
<line>Brake off our business for the Holy Land.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>This match'd with other did, my gracious lord;</line>
<line>For more uneven and unwelcome news</line>
<line>Came from the north and thus it did import:</line>
<line>On Holy-rood day, the gallant Hotspur there,</line>
<line>Young Harry Percy and brave Archibald,</line>
<line>That ever-valiant and approved Scot,</line>
<line>At Holmedon met,</line>
<line>Where they did spend a sad and bloody hour,</line>
<line>As by discharge of their artillery,</line>
<line>And shape of likelihood, the news was told;</line>
<line>For he that brought them, in the very heat</line>
<line>And pride of their contention did take horse,</line>
<line>Uncertain of the issue any way.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Here is a dear, a true industrious friend,</line>
<line>Sir Walter Blunt, new lighted from his horse.</line>
<line>Stain'd with the variation of each soil</line>
<line>Betwixt that Holmedon and this seat of ours;</line>
<line>And he hath brought us smooth and welcome news.</line>
<line>The Earl of Douglas is discomfited:</line>
<line>Ten thousand bold Scots, two and twenty knights,</line>
<line>Balk'd in their own blood did Sir Walter see</line>
<line>On Holmedon's plains. Of prisoners, Hotspur took</line>
<line>Mordake the Earl of Fife, and eldest son</line>
<line>To beaten Douglas; and the Earl of Athol,</line>
<line>Of Murray, Angus, and Menteith:</line>
<line>And is not this an honourable spoil?</line>
<line>A gallant prize? ha, cousin, is it not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>In faith,</line>
<line>It is a conquest for a prince to boast of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Yea, there thou makest me sad and makest me sin</line>
<line>In envy that my Lord Northumberland</line>
<line>Should be the father to so blest a son,</line>
<line>A son who is the theme of honour's tongue;</line>
<line>Amongst a grove, the very straightest plant;</line>
<line>Who is sweet Fortune's minion and her pride:</line>
<line>Whilst I, by looking on the praise of him,</line>
<line>See riot and dishonour stain the brow</line>
<line>Of my young Harry. O that it could be proved</line>
<line>That some night-tripping fairy had exchanged</line>
<line>In cradle-clothes our children where they lay,</line>
<line>And call'd mine Percy, his Plantagenet!</line>
<line>Then would I have his Harry, and he mine.</line>
<line>But let him from my thoughts. What think you, coz,</line>
<line>Of this young Percy's pride? the prisoners,</line>
<line>Which he in this adventure hath surprised,</line>
<line>To his own use he keeps; and sends me word,</line>
<line>I shall have none but Mordake Earl of Fife.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>This is his uncle's teaching; this is Worcester,</line>
<line>Malevolent to you in all aspects;</line>
<line>Which makes him prune himself, and bristle up</line>
<line>The crest of youth against your dignity.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>But I have sent for him to answer this;</line>
<line>And for this cause awhile we must neglect</line>
<line>Our holy purpose to Jerusalem.</line>
<line>Cousin, on Wednesday next our council we</line>
<line>Will hold at Windsor; so inform the lords:</line>
<line>But come yourself with speed to us again;</line>
<line>For more is to be said and to be done</line>
<line>Than out of anger can be uttered.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>I will, my liege.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  London. An apartment of the Prince's.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter the PRINCE OF WALES and FALSTAFF</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Now, Hal, what time of day is it, lad?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou art so fat-witted, with drinking of old sack</line>
<line>and unbuttoning thee after supper and sleeping upon</line>
<line>benches after noon, that thou hast forgotten to</line>
<line>demand that truly which thou wouldst truly know.</line>
<line>What a devil hast thou to do with the time of the</line>
<line>day? Unless hours were cups of sack and minutes</line>
<line>capons and clocks the tongues of bawds and dials the</line>
<line>signs of leaping-houses and the blessed sun himself</line>
<line>a fair hot wench in flame-coloured taffeta, I see no</line>
<line>reason why thou shouldst be so superfluous to demand</line>
<line>the time of the day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Indeed, you come near me now, Hal; for we that take</line>
<line>purses go by the moon and the seven stars, and not</line>
<line>by Phoebus, he,'that wandering knight so fair.' And,</line>
<line>I prithee, sweet wag, when thou art king, as, God</line>
<line>save thy grace,--majesty I should say, for grace</line>
<line>thou wilt have none,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, none?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>No, by my troth, not so much as will serve to</line>
<line>prologue to an egg and butter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, how then? come, roundly, roundly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Marry, then, sweet wag, when thou art king, let not</line>
<line>us that are squires of the night's body be called</line>
<line>thieves of the day's beauty: let us be Diana's</line>
<line>foresters, gentlemen of the shade, minions of the</line>
<line>moon; and let men say we be men of good government,</line>
<line>being governed, as the sea is, by our noble and</line>
<line>chaste mistress the moon, under whose countenance we steal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou sayest well, and it holds well too; for the</line>
<line>fortune of us that are the moon's men doth ebb and</line>
<line>flow like the sea, being governed, as the sea is,</line>
<line>by the moon. As, for proof, now: a purse of gold</line>
<line>most resolutely snatched on Monday night and most</line>
<line>dissolutely spent on Tuesday morning; got with</line>
<line>swearing 'Lay by' and spent with crying 'Bring in;'</line>
<line>now in as low an ebb as the foot of the ladder</line>
<line>and by and by in as high a flow as the ridge of the gallows.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>By the Lord, thou sayest true, lad. And is not my</line>
<line>hostess of the tavern a most sweet wench?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>As the honey of Hybla, my old lad of the castle. And</line>
<line>is not a buff jerkin a most sweet robe of durance?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>How now, how now, mad wag! what, in thy quips and</line>
<line>thy quiddities? what a plague have I to do with a</line>
<line>buff jerkin?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, what a pox have I to do with my hostess of the tavern?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, thou hast called her to a reckoning many a</line>
<line>time and oft.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Did I ever call for thee to pay thy part?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>No; I'll give thee thy due, thou hast paid all there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Yea, and elsewhere, so far as my coin would stretch;</line>
<line>and where it would not, I have used my credit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Yea, and so used it that were it not here apparent</line>
<line>that thou art heir apparent--But, I prithee, sweet</line>
<line>wag, shall there be gallows standing in England when</line>
<line>thou art king? and resolution thus fobbed as it is</line>
<line>with the rusty curb of old father antic the law? Do</line>
<line>not thou, when thou art king, hang a thief.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>No; thou shalt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Shall I? O rare! By the Lord, I'll be a brave judge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou judgest false already: I mean, thou shalt have</line>
<line>the hanging of the thieves and so become a rare hangman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, Hal, well; and in some sort it jumps with my</line>
<line>humour as well as waiting in the court, I can tell</line>
<line>you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>For obtaining of suits?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Yea, for obtaining of suits, whereof the hangman</line>
<line>hath no lean wardrobe. 'Sblood, I am as melancholy</line>
<line>as a gib cat or a lugged bear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Or an old lion, or a lover's lute.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Yea, or the drone of a Lincolnshire bagpipe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What sayest thou to a hare, or the melancholy of</line>
<line>Moor-ditch?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Thou hast the most unsavoury similes and art indeed</line>
<line>the most comparative, rascalliest, sweet young</line>
<line>prince. But, Hal, I prithee, trouble me no more</line>
<line>with vanity. I would to God thou and I knew where a</line>
<line>commodity of good names were to be bought. An old</line>
<line>lord of the council rated me the other day in the</line>
<line>street about you, sir, but I marked him not; and yet</line>
<line>he talked very wisely, but I regarded him not; and</line>
<line>yet he talked wisely, and in the street too.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou didst well; for wisdom cries out in the</line>
<line>streets, and no man regards it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>O, thou hast damnable iteration and art indeed able</line>
<line>to corrupt a saint. Thou hast done much harm upon</line>
<line>me, Hal; God forgive thee for it! Before I knew</line>
<line>thee, Hal, I knew nothing; and now am I, if a man</line>
<line>should speak truly, little better than one of the</line>
<line>wicked. I must give over this life, and I will give</line>
<line>it over: by the Lord, and I do not, I am a villain:</line>
<line>I'll be damned for never a king's son in</line>
<line>Christendom.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Where shall we take a purse tomorrow, Jack?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Zounds, where thou wilt, lad; I'll make one; an I</line>
<line>do not, call me villain and baffle me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I see a good amendment of life in thee; from praying</line>
<line>to purse-taking.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Why, Hal, 'tis my vocation, Hal; 'tis no sin for a</line>
<line>man to labour in his vocation.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter POINS</para>
<line>Poins! Now shall we know if Gadshill have set a</line>
<line>match. O, if men were to be saved by merit, what</line>
<line>hole in hell were hot enough for him? This is the</line>
<line>most omnipotent villain that ever cried 'Stand' to</line>
<line>a true man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, Ned.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, sweet Hal. What says Monsieur Remorse?</line>
<line>what says Sir John Sack and Sugar? Jack! how</line>
<line>agrees the devil and thee about thy soul, that thou</line>
<line>soldest him on Good-Friday last for a cup of Madeira</line>
<line>and a cold capon's leg?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Sir John stands to his word, the devil shall have</line>
<line>his bargain; for he was never yet a breaker of</line>
<line>proverbs: he will give the devil his due.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Then art thou damned for keeping thy word with the devil.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Else he had been damned for cozening the devil.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>But, my lads, my lads, to-morrow morning, by four</line>
<line>o'clock, early at Gadshill! there are pilgrims going</line>
<line>to Canterbury with rich offerings, and traders</line>
<line>riding to London with fat purses: I have vizards</line>
<line>for you all; you have horses for yourselves:</line>
<line>Gadshill lies to-night in Rochester: I have bespoke</line>
<line>supper to-morrow night in Eastcheap: we may do it</line>
<line>as secure as sleep. If you will go, I will stuff</line>
<line>your purses full of crowns; if you will not, tarry</line>
<line>at home and be hanged.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Hear ye, Yedward; if I tarry at home and go not,</line>
<line>I'll hang you for going.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>You will, chops?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Hal, wilt thou make one?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Who, I rob? I a thief? not I, by my faith.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>There's neither honesty, manhood, nor good</line>
<line>fellowship in thee, nor thou camest not of the blood</line>
<line>royal, if thou darest not stand for ten shillings.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well then, once in my days I'll be a madcap.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Why, that's well said.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, come what will, I'll tarry at home.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>By the Lord, I'll be a traitor then, when thou art king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I care not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Sir John, I prithee, leave the prince and me alone:</line>
<line>I will lay him down such reasons for this adventure</line>
<line>that he shall go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, God give thee the spirit of persuasion and him</line>
<line>the ears of profiting, that what thou speakest may</line>
<line>move and what he hears may be believed, that the</line>
<line>true prince may, for recreation sake, prove a false</line>
<line>thief; for the poor abuses of the time want</line>
<line>countenance. Farewell: you shall find me in Eastcheap.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Farewell, thou latter spring! farewell, All-hallown summer!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit Falstaff</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Now, my good sweet honey lord, ride with us</line>
<line>to-morrow: I have a jest to execute that I cannot</line>
<line>manage alone. Falstaff, Bardolph, Peto and Gadshill</line>
<line>shall rob those men that we have already waylaid:</line>
<line>yourself and I will not be there; and when they</line>
<line>have the booty, if you and I do not rob them, cut</line>
<line>this head off from my shoulders.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>How shall we part with them in setting forth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Why, we will set forth before or after them, and</line>
<line>appoint them a place of meeting, wherein it is at</line>
<line>our pleasure to fail, and then will they adventure</line>
<line>upon the exploit themselves; which they shall have</line>
<line>no sooner achieved, but we'll set upon them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Yea, but 'tis like that they will know us by our</line>
<line>horses, by our habits and by every other</line>
<line>appointment, to be ourselves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Tut! our horses they shall not see: I'll tie them</line>
<line>in the wood; our vizards we will change after we</line>
<line>leave them: and, sirrah, I have cases of buckram</line>
<line>for the nonce, to immask our noted outward garments.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Yea, but I doubt they will be too hard for us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Well, for two of them, I know them to be as</line>
<line>true-bred cowards as ever turned back; and for the</line>
<line>third, if he fight longer than he sees reason, I'll</line>
<line>forswear arms. The virtue of this jest will be, the</line>
<line>incomprehensible lies that this same fat rogue will</line>
<line>tell us when we meet at supper: how thirty, at</line>
<line>least, he fought with; what wards, what blows, what</line>
<line>extremities he endured; and in the reproof of this</line>
<line>lies the jest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, I'll go with thee: provide us all things</line>
<line>necessary and meet me to-morrow night in Eastcheap;</line>
<line>there I'll sup. Farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Farewell, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit Poins</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I know you all, and will awhile uphold</line>
<line>The unyoked humour of your idleness:</line>
<line>Yet herein will I imitate the sun,</line>
<line>Who doth permit the base contagious clouds</line>
<line>To smother up his beauty from the world,</line>
<line>That, when he please again to be himself,</line>
<line>Being wanted, he may be more wonder'd at,</line>
<line>By breaking through the foul and ugly mists</line>
<line>Of vapours that did seem to strangle him.</line>
<line>If all the year were playing holidays,</line>
<line>To sport would be as tedious as to work;</line>
<line>But when they seldom come, they wish'd for come,</line>
<line>And nothing pleaseth but rare accidents.</line>
<line>So, when this loose behavior I throw off</line>
<line>And pay the debt I never promised,</line>
<line>By how much better than my word I am,</line>
<line>By so much shall I falsify men's hopes;</line>
<line>And like bright metal on a sullen ground,</line>
<line>My reformation, glittering o'er my fault,</line>
<line>Shall show more goodly and attract more eyes</line>
<line>Than that which hath no foil to set it off.</line>
<line>I'll so offend, to make offence a skill;</line>
<line>Redeeming time when men think least I will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  London. The palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter the KING, NORTHUMBERLAND, WORCESTER, HOTSPUR,
SIR WALTER BLUNT, with others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>My blood hath been too cold and temperate,</line>
<line>Unapt to stir at these indignities,</line>
<line>And you have found me; for accordingly</line>
<line>You tread upon my patience: but be sure</line>
<line>I will from henceforth rather be myself,</line>
<line>Mighty and to be fear'd, than my condition;</line>
<line>Which hath been smooth as oil, soft as young down,</line>
<line>And therefore lost that title of respect</line>
<line>Which the proud soul ne'er pays but to the proud.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Our house, my sovereign liege, little deserves</line>
<line>The scourge of greatness to be used on it;</line>
<line>And that same greatness too which our own hands</line>
<line>Have holp to make so portly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My lord.--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Worcester, get thee gone; for I do see</line>
<line>Danger and disobedience in thine eye:</line>
<line>O, sir, your presence is too bold and peremptory,</line>
<line>And majesty might never yet endure</line>
<line>The moody frontier of a servant brow.</line>
<line>You have good leave to leave us: when we need</line>
<line>Your use and counsel, we shall send for you.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Worcester</para>
<line>You were about to speak.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">To North</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Yea, my good lord.</line>
<line>Those prisoners in your highness' name demanded,</line>
<line>Which Harry Percy here at Holmedon took,</line>
<line>Were, as he says, not with such strength denied</line>
<line>As is deliver'd to your majesty:</line>
<line>Either envy, therefore, or misprison</line>
<line>Is guilty of this fault and not my son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>My liege, I did deny no prisoners.</line>
<line>But I remember, when the fight was done,</line>
<line>When I was dry with rage and extreme toil,</line>
<line>Breathless and faint, leaning upon my sword,</line>
<line>Came there a certain lord, neat, and trimly dress'd,</line>
<line>Fresh as a bridegroom; and his chin new reap'd</line>
<line>Show'd like a stubble-land at harvest-home;</line>
<line>He was perfumed like a milliner;</line>
<line>And 'twixt his finger and his thumb he held</line>
<line>A pouncet-box, which ever and anon</line>
<line>He gave his nose and took't away again;</line>
<line>Who therewith angry, when it next came there,</line>
<line>Took it in snuff; and still he smiled and talk'd,</line>
<line>And as the soldiers bore dead bodies by,</line>
<line>He call'd them untaught knaves, unmannerly,</line>
<line>To bring a slovenly unhandsome corse</line>
<line>Betwixt the wind and his nobility.</line>
<line>With many holiday and lady terms</line>
<line>He question'd me; amongst the rest, demanded</line>
<line>My prisoners in your majesty's behalf.</line>
<line>I then, all smarting with my wounds being cold,</line>
<line>To be so pester'd with a popinjay,</line>
<line>Out of my grief and my impatience,</line>
<line>Answer'd neglectingly I know not what,</line>
<line>He should or he should not; for he made me mad</line>
<line>To see him shine so brisk and smell so sweet</line>
<line>And talk so like a waiting-gentlewoman</line>
<line>Of guns and drums and wounds,--God save the mark!--</line>
<line>And telling me the sovereign'st thing on earth</line>
<line>Was parmaceti for an inward bruise;</line>
<line>And that it was great pity, so it was,</line>
<line>This villanous salt-petre should be digg'd</line>
<line>Out of the bowels of the harmless earth,</line>
<line>Which many a good tall fellow had destroy'd</line>
<line>So cowardly; and but for these vile guns,</line>
<line>He would himself have been a soldier.</line>
<line>This bald unjointed chat of his, my lord,</line>
<line>I answer'd indirectly, as I said;</line>
<line>And I beseech you, let not his report</line>
<line>Come current for an accusation</line>
<line>Betwixt my love and your high majesty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>The circumstance consider'd, good my lord,</line>
<line>Whate'er Lord Harry Percy then had said</line>
<line>To such a person and in such a place,</line>
<line>At such a time, with all the rest retold,</line>
<line>May reasonably die and never rise</line>
<line>To do him wrong or any way impeach</line>
<line>What then he said, so he unsay it now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Why, yet he doth deny his prisoners,</line>
<line>But with proviso and exception,</line>
<line>That we at our own charge shall ransom straight</line>
<line>His brother-in-law, the foolish Mortimer;</line>
<line>Who, on my soul, hath wilfully betray'd</line>
<line>The lives of those that he did lead to fight</line>
<line>Against that great magician, damn'd Glendower,</line>
<line>Whose daughter, as we hear, the Earl of March</line>
<line>Hath lately married. Shall our coffers, then,</line>
<line>Be emptied to redeem a traitor home?</line>
<line>Shall we but treason? and indent with fears,</line>
<line>When they have lost and forfeited themselves?</line>
<line>No, on the barren mountains let him starve;</line>
<line>For I shall never hold that man my friend</line>
<line>Whose tongue shall ask me for one penny cost</line>
<line>To ransom home revolted Mortimer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Revolted Mortimer!</line>
<line>He never did fall off, my sovereign liege,</line>
<line>But by the chance of war; to prove that true</line>
<line>Needs no more but one tongue for all those wounds,</line>
<line>Those mouthed wounds, which valiantly he took</line>
<line>When on the gentle Severn's sedgy bank,</line>
<line>In single opposition, hand to hand,</line>
<line>He did confound the best part of an hour</line>
<line>In changing hardiment with great Glendower:</line>
<line>Three times they breathed and three times did</line>
<line>they drink,</line>
<line>Upon agreement, of swift Severn's flood;</line>
<line>Who then, affrighted with their bloody looks,</line>
<line>Ran fearfully among the trembling reeds,</line>
<line>And hid his crisp head in the hollow bank,</line>
<line>Bloodstained with these valiant combatants.</line>
<line>Never did base and rotten policy</line>
<line>Colour her working with such deadly wounds;</line>
<line>Nor could the noble Mortimer</line>
<line>Receive so many, and all willingly:</line>
<line>Then let not him be slander'd with revolt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Thou dost belie him, Percy, thou dost belie him;</line>
<line>He never did encounter with Glendower:</line>
<line>I tell thee,</line>
<line>He durst as well have met the devil alone</line>
<line>As Owen Glendower for an enemy.</line>
<line>Art thou not ashamed? But, sirrah, henceforth</line>
<line>Let me not hear you speak of Mortimer:</line>
<line>Send me your prisoners with the speediest means,</line>
<line>Or you shall hear in such a kind from me</line>
<line>As will displease you. My Lord Northumberland,</line>
<line>We licence your departure with your son.</line>
<line>Send us your prisoners, or you will hear of it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt King Henry, Blunt, and train</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>An if the devil come and roar for them,</line>
<line>I will not send them: I will after straight</line>
<line>And tell him so; for I will ease my heart,</line>
<line>Albeit I make a hazard of my head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>What, drunk with choler? stay and pause awhile:</line>
<line>Here comes your uncle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter WORCESTER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Speak of Mortimer!</line>
<line>'Zounds, I will speak of him; and let my soul</line>
<line>Want mercy, if I do not join with him:</line>
<line>Yea, on his part I'll empty all these veins,</line>
<line>And shed my dear blood drop by drop in the dust,</line>
<line>But I will lift the down-trod Mortimer</line>
<line>As high in the air as this unthankful king,</line>
<line>As this ingrate and canker'd Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Brother, the king hath made your nephew mad.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Who struck this heat up after I was gone?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>He will, forsooth, have all my prisoners;</line>
<line>And when I urged the ransom once again</line>
<line>Of my wife's brother, then his cheek look'd pale,</line>
<line>And on my face he turn'd an eye of death,</line>
<line>Trembling even at the name of Mortimer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>I cannot blame him: was not he proclaim'd</line>
<line>By Richard that dead is the next of blood?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>He was; I heard the proclamation:</line>
<line>And then it was when the unhappy king,</line>
<line>--Whose wrongs in us God pardon!--did set forth</line>
<line>Upon his Irish expedition;</line>
<line>From whence he intercepted did return</line>
<line>To be deposed and shortly murdered.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>And for whose death we in the world's wide mouth</line>
<line>Live scandalized and foully spoken of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>But soft, I pray you; did King Richard then</line>
<line>Proclaim my brother Edmund Mortimer</line>
<line>Heir to the crown?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>He did; myself did hear it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Nay, then I cannot blame his cousin king,</line>
<line>That wished him on the barren mountains starve.</line>
<line>But shall it be that you, that set the crown</line>
<line>Upon the head of this forgetful man</line>
<line>And for his sake wear the detested blot</line>
<line>Of murderous subornation, shall it be,</line>
<line>That you a world of curses undergo,</line>
<line>Being the agents, or base second means,</line>
<line>The cords, the ladder, or the hangman rather?</line>
<line>O, pardon me that I descend so low,</line>
<line>To show the line and the predicament</line>
<line>Wherein you range under this subtle king;</line>
<line>Shall it for shame be spoken in these days,</line>
<line>Or fill up chronicles in time to come,</line>
<line>That men of your nobility and power</line>
<line>Did gage them both in an unjust behalf,</line>
<line>As both of you--God pardon it!--have done,</line>
<line>To put down Richard, that sweet lovely rose,</line>
<line>An plant this thorn, this canker, Bolingbroke?</line>
<line>And shall it in more shame be further spoken,</line>
<line>That you are fool'd, discarded and shook off</line>
<line>By him for whom these shames ye underwent?</line>
<line>No; yet time serves wherein you may redeem</line>
<line>Your banish'd honours and restore yourselves</line>
<line>Into the good thoughts of the world again,</line>
<line>Revenge the jeering and disdain'd contempt</line>
<line>Of this proud king, who studies day and night</line>
<line>To answer all the debt he owes to you</line>
<line>Even with the bloody payment of your deaths:</line>
<line>Therefore, I say--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Peace, cousin, say no more:</line>
<line>And now I will unclasp a secret book,</line>
<line>And to your quick-conceiving discontents</line>
<line>I'll read you matter deep and dangerous,</line>
<line>As full of peril and adventurous spirit</line>
<line>As to o'er-walk a current roaring loud</line>
<line>On the unsteadfast footing of a spear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>If he fall in, good night! or sink or swim:</line>
<line>Send danger from the east unto the west,</line>
<line>So honour cross it from the north to south,</line>
<line>And let them grapple: O, the blood more stirs</line>
<line>To rouse a lion than to start a hare!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Imagination of some great exploit</line>
<line>Drives him beyond the bounds of patience.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>By heaven, methinks it were an easy leap,</line>
<line>To pluck bright honour from the pale-faced moon,</line>
<line>Or dive into the bottom of the deep,</line>
<line>Where fathom-line could never touch the ground,</line>
<line>And pluck up drowned honour by the locks;</line>
<line>So he that doth redeem her thence might wear</line>
<line>Without corrival, all her dignities:</line>
<line>But out upon this half-faced fellowship!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>He apprehends a world of figures here,</line>
<line>But not the form of what he should attend.</line>
<line>Good cousin, give me audience for a while.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I cry you mercy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Those same noble Scots</line>
<line>That are your prisoners,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I'll keep them all;</line>
<line>By God, he shall not have a Scot of them;</line>
<line>No, if a Scot would save his soul, he shall not:</line>
<line>I'll keep them, by this hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>You start away</line>
<line>And lend no ear unto my purposes.</line>
<line>Those prisoners you shall keep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Nay, I will; that's flat:</line>
<line>He said he would not ransom Mortimer;</line>
<line>Forbad my tongue to speak of Mortimer;</line>
<line>But I will find him when he lies asleep,</line>
<line>And in his ear I'll holla 'Mortimer!'</line>
<line>Nay,</line>
<line>I'll have a starling shall be taught to speak</line>
<line>Nothing but 'Mortimer,' and give it him</line>
<line>To keep his anger still in motion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Hear you, cousin; a word.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>All studies here I solemnly defy,</line>
<line>Save how to gall and pinch this Bolingbroke:</line>
<line>And that same sword-and-buckler Prince of Wales,</line>
<line>But that I think his father loves him not</line>
<line>And would be glad he met with some mischance,</line>
<line>I would have him poison'd with a pot of ale.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Farewell, kinsman: I'll talk to you</line>
<line>When you are better temper'd to attend.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Why, what a wasp-stung and impatient fool</line>
<line>Art thou to break into this woman's mood,</line>
<line>Tying thine ear to no tongue but thine own!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Why, look you, I am whipp'd and scourged with rods,</line>
<line>Nettled and stung with pismires, when I hear</line>
<line>Of this vile politician, Bolingbroke.</line>
<line>In Richard's time,--what do you call the place?--</line>
<line>A plague upon it, it is in Gloucestershire;</line>
<line>'Twas where the madcap duke his uncle kept,</line>
<line>His uncle York; where I first bow'd my knee</line>
<line>Unto this king of smiles, this Bolingbroke,--</line>
<line>'Sblood!--</line>
<line>When you and he came back from Ravenspurgh.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>At Berkley castle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>You say true:</line>
<line>Why, what a candy deal of courtesy</line>
<line>This fawning greyhound then did proffer me!</line>
<line>Look,'when his infant fortune came to age,'</line>
<line>And 'gentle Harry Percy,' and 'kind cousin;'</line>
<line>O, the devil take such cozeners! God forgive me!</line>
<line>Good uncle, tell your tale; I have done.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Nay, if you have not, to it again;</line>
<line>We will stay your leisure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I have done, i' faith.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Then once more to your Scottish prisoners.</line>
<line>Deliver them up without their ransom straight,</line>
<line>And make the Douglas' son your only mean</line>
<line>For powers in Scotland; which, for divers reasons</line>
<line>Which I shall send you written, be assured,</line>
<line>Will easily be granted. You, my lord,</line>
<para role="stagedir">To Northumberland</para>
<line>Your son in Scotland being thus employ'd,</line>
<line>Shall secretly into the bosom creep</line>
<line>Of that same noble prelate, well beloved,</line>
<line>The archbishop.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Of York, is it not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>True; who bears hard</line>
<line>His brother's death at Bristol, the Lord Scroop.</line>
<line>I speak not this in estimation,</line>
<line>As what I think might be, but what I know</line>
<line>Is ruminated, plotted and set down,</line>
<line>And only stays but to behold the face</line>
<line>Of that occasion that shall bring it on.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I smell it: upon my life, it will do well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Before the game is afoot, thou still let'st slip.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Why, it cannot choose but be a noble plot;</line>
<line>And then the power of Scotland and of York,</line>
<line>To join with Mortimer, ha?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>And so they shall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>In faith, it is exceedingly well aim'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>And 'tis no little reason bids us speed,</line>
<line>To save our heads by raising of a head;</line>
<line>For, bear ourselves as even as we can,</line>
<line>The king will always think him in our debt,</line>
<line>And think we think ourselves unsatisfied,</line>
<line>Till he hath found a time to pay us home:</line>
<line>And see already how he doth begin</line>
<line>To make us strangers to his looks of love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>He does, he does: we'll be revenged on him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Cousin, farewell: no further go in this</line>
<line>Than I by letters shall direct your course.</line>
<line>When time is ripe, which will be suddenly,</line>
<line>I'll steal to Glendower and Lord Mortimer;</line>
<line>Where you and Douglas and our powers at once,</line>
<line>As I will fashion it, shall happily meet,</line>
<line>To bear our fortunes in our own strong arms,</line>
<line>Which now we hold at much uncertainty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Farewell, good brother: we shall thrive, I trust.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Uncle, Adieu: O, let the hours be short</line>
<line>Till fields and blows and groans applaud our sport!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT II</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Rochester. An inn yard.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Carrier with a lantern in his hand</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>Heigh-ho! an it be not four by the day, I'll be</line>
<line>hanged: Charles' wain is over the new chimney, and</line>
<line>yet our horse not packed. What, ostler!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Ostler</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>   Anon, anon.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>I prithee, Tom, beat Cut's saddle, put a few flocks</line>
<line>in the point; poor jade, is wrung in the withers out</line>
<line>of all cess.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter another Carrier</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Carrier</speaker>
<line>Peas and beans are as dank here as a dog, and that</line>
<line>is the next way to give poor jades the bots: this</line>
<line>house is turned upside down since Robin Ostler died.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>Poor fellow, never joyed since the price of oats</line>
<line>rose; it was the death of him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Carrier</speaker>
<line>I think this be the most villanous house in all</line>
<line>London road for fleas: I am stung like a tench.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>Like a tench! by the mass, there is ne'er a king</line>
<line>christen could be better bit than I have been since</line>
<line>the first cock.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Carrier</speaker>
<line>Why, they will allow us ne'er a jordan, and then we</line>
<line>leak in your chimney; and your chamber-lie breeds</line>
<line>fleas like a loach.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>What, ostler! come away and be hanged!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Carrier</speaker>
<line>I have a gammon of bacon and two razors of ginger,</line>
<line>to be delivered as far as Charing-cross.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>God's body! the turkeys in my pannier are quite</line>
<line>starved. What, ostler! A plague on thee! hast thou</line>
<line>never an eye in thy head? canst not hear? An</line>
<line>'twere not as good deed as drink, to break the pate</line>
<line>on thee, I am a very villain. Come, and be hanged!</line>
<line>hast thou no faith in thee?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter GADSHILL</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, carriers. What's o'clock?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>I think it be two o'clock.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>I pray thee lend me thy lantern, to see my gelding</line>
<line>in the stable.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Carrier</speaker>
<line>Nay, by God, soft; I know a trick worth two of that, i' faith.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>I pray thee, lend me thine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Carrier</speaker>
<line>Ay, when? can'st tell? Lend me thy lantern, quoth</line>
<line>he? marry, I'll see thee hanged first.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Sirrah carrier, what time do you mean to come to London?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Carrier</speaker>
<line>Time enough to go to bed with a candle, I warrant</line>
<line>thee. Come, neighbour Mugs, we'll call up the</line>
<line>gentleman: they will along with company, for they</line>
<line>have great charge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt carriers</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>What, ho! chamberlain!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Chamberlain</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  At hand, quoth pick-purse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>That's even as fair as--at hand, quoth the</line>
<line>chamberlain; for thou variest no more from picking</line>
<line>of purses than giving direction doth from labouring;</line>
<line>thou layest the plot how.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter Chamberlain</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Chamberlain</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, Master Gadshill. It holds current that</line>
<line>I told you yesternight: there's a franklin in the</line>
<line>wild of Kent hath brought three hundred marks with</line>
<line>him in gold: I heard him tell it to one of his</line>
<line>company last night at supper; a kind of auditor; one</line>
<line>that hath abundance of charge too, God knows what.</line>
<line>They are up already, and call for eggs and butter;</line>
<line>they will away presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Sirrah, if they meet not with Saint Nicholas'</line>
<line>clerks, I'll give thee this neck.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Chamberlain</speaker>
<line>No, I'll none of it: I pray thee keep that for the</line>
<line>hangman; for I know thou worshippest St. Nicholas</line>
<line>as truly as a man of falsehood may.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>What talkest thou to me of the hangman? if I hang,</line>
<line>I'll make a fat pair of gallows; for if I hang, old</line>
<line>Sir John hangs with me, and thou knowest he is no</line>
<line>starveling. Tut! there are other Trojans that thou</line>
<line>dreamest not of, the which for sport sake are</line>
<line>content to do the profession some grace; that would,</line>
<line>if matters should be looked into, for their own</line>
<line>credit sake, make all whole. I am joined with no</line>
<line>foot-land rakers, no long-staff sixpenny strikers,</line>
<line>none of these mad mustachio purple-hued malt-worms;</line>
<line>but with nobility and tranquillity, burgomasters and</line>
<line>great oneyers, such as can hold in, such as will</line>
<line>strike sooner than speak, and speak sooner than</line>
<line>drink, and drink sooner than pray: and yet, zounds,</line>
<line>I lie; for they pray continually to their saint, the</line>
<line>commonwealth; or rather, not pray to her, but prey</line>
<line>on her, for they ride up and down on her and make</line>
<line>her their boots.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Chamberlain</speaker>
<line>What, the commonwealth their boots? will she hold</line>
<line>out water in foul way?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>She will, she will; justice hath liquored her. We</line>
<line>steal as in a castle, cocksure; we have the receipt</line>
<line>of fern-seed, we walk invisible.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Chamberlain</speaker>
<line>Nay, by my faith, I think you are more beholding to</line>
<line>the night than to fern-seed for your walking invisible.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Give me thy hand: thou shalt have a share in our</line>
<line>purchase, as I am a true man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Chamberlain</speaker>
<line>Nay, rather let me have it, as you are a false thief.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Go to; 'homo' is a common name to all men. Bid the</line>
<line>ostler bring my gelding out of the stable. Farewell,</line>
<line>you muddy knave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The highway, near Gadshill.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PRINCE HENRY and POINS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Come, shelter, shelter: I have removed Falstaff's</line>
<line>horse, and he frets like a gummed velvet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Stand close.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter FALSTAFF</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Poins! Poins, and be hanged! Poins!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Peace, ye fat-kidneyed rascal! what a brawling dost</line>
<line>thou keep!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Where's Poins, Hal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>He is walked up to the top of the hill: I'll go seek him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I am accursed to rob in that thief's company: the</line>
<line>rascal hath removed my horse, and tied him I know</line>
<line>not where. If I travel but four foot by the squier</line>
<line>further afoot, I shall break my wind. Well, I doubt</line>
<line>not but to die a fair death for all this, if I</line>
<line>'scape hanging for killing that rogue. I have</line>
<line>forsworn his company hourly any time this two and</line>
<line>twenty years, and yet I am bewitched with the</line>
<line>rogue's company. If the rascal hath not given me</line>
<line>medicines to make me love him, I'll be hanged; it</line>
<line>could not be else: I have drunk medicines. Poins!</line>
<line>Hal! a plague upon you both! Bardolph! Peto!</line>
<line>I'll starve ere I'll rob a foot further. An 'twere</line>
<line>not as good a deed as drink, to turn true man and to</line>
<line>leave these rogues, I am the veriest varlet that</line>
<line>ever chewed with a tooth. Eight yards of uneven</line>
<line>ground is threescore and ten miles afoot with me;</line>
<line>and the stony-hearted villains know it well enough:</line>
<line>a plague upon it when thieves cannot be true one to another!</line>
<para role="stagedir">They whistle</para>
<line>Whew! A plague upon you all! Give me my horse, you</line>
<line>rogues; give me my horse, and be hanged!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Peace, ye fat-guts! lie down; lay thine ear close</line>
<line>to the ground and list if thou canst hear the tread</line>
<line>of travellers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Have you any levers to lift me up again, being down?</line>
<line>'Sblood, I'll not bear mine own flesh so far afoot</line>
<line>again for all the coin in thy father's exchequer.</line>
<line>What a plague mean ye to colt me thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou liest; thou art not colted, thou art uncolted.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I prithee, good Prince Hal, help me to my horse,</line>
<line>good king's son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Out, ye rogue! shall I be your ostler?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Go, hang thyself in thine own heir-apparent</line>
<line>garters! If I be ta'en, I'll peach for this. An I</line>
<line>have not ballads made on you all and sung to filthy</line>
<line>tunes, let a cup of sack be my poison: when a jest</line>
<line>is so forward, and afoot too! I hate it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter GADSHILL, BARDOLPH and PETO</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Stand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>So I do, against my will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>O, 'tis our setter: I know his voice. Bardolph,</line>
<line>what news?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Case ye, case ye; on with your vizards: there 's</line>
<line>money of the king's coming down the hill; 'tis going</line>
<line>to the king's exchequer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>You lie, ye rogue; 'tis going to the king's tavern.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>There's enough to make us all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>To be hanged.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Sirs, you four shall front them in the narrow lane;</line>
<line>Ned Poins and I will walk lower: if they 'scape</line>
<line>from your encounter, then they light on us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line>How many be there of them?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>Some eight or ten.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Zounds, will they not rob us?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, a coward, Sir John Paunch?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Indeed, I am not John of Gaunt, your grandfather;</line>
<line>but yet no coward, Hal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, we leave that to the proof.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Sirrah Jack, thy horse stands behind the hedge:</line>
<line>when thou needest him, there thou shalt find him.</line>
<line>Farewell, and stand fast.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Now cannot I strike him, if I should be hanged.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Ned, where are our disguises?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Here, hard by: stand close.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt PRINCE HENRY and POINS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Now, my masters, happy man be his dole, say I:</line>
<line>every man to his business.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter the Travellers</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Traveller</speaker>
<line>Come, neighbour: the boy shall lead our horses down</line>
<line>the hill; we'll walk afoot awhile, and ease our legs.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Thieves</speaker>
<line>Stand!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Travellers</speaker>
<line>Jesus bless us!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Strike; down with them; cut the villains' throats:</line>
<line>ah! whoreson caterpillars! bacon-fed knaves! they</line>
<line>hate us youth: down with them: fleece them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Travellers</speaker>
<line>O, we are undone, both we and ours for ever!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Hang ye, gorbellied knaves, are ye undone? No, ye</line>
<line>fat chuffs: I would your store were here! On,</line>
<line>bacons, on! What, ye knaves! young men must live.</line>
<line>You are Grand-jurors, are ye? we'll jure ye, 'faith.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Here they rob them and bind them. Exeunt</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter PRINCE HENRY and POINS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>The thieves have bound the true men. Now could thou</line>
<line>and I rob the thieves and go merrily to London, it</line>
<line>would be argument for a week, laughter for a month</line>
<line>and a good jest for ever.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Stand close; I hear them coming.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter the Thieves again</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Come, my masters, let us share, and then to horse</line>
<line>before day. An the Prince and Poins be not two</line>
<line>arrant cowards, there's no equity stirring: there's</line>
<line>no more valour in that Poins than in a wild-duck.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Your money!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Villains!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">As they are sharing, the Prince and Poins set upon
them; they all run away; and Falstaff, after a blow
or two, runs away too, leaving the booty behind them</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Got with much ease. Now merrily to horse:</line>
<line>The thieves are all scatter'd and possess'd with fear</line>
<line>So strongly that they dare not meet each other;</line>
<line>Each takes his fellow for an officer.</line>
<line>Away, good Ned. Falstaff sweats to death,</line>
<line>And lards the lean earth as he walks along:</line>
<line>Were 't not for laughing, I should pity him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>How the rogue roar'd!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Warkworth castle</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HOTSPUR, solus, reading a letter</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>'But for mine own part, my lord, I could be well</line>
<line>contented to be there, in respect of the love I bear</line>
<line>your house.' He could be contented: why is he not,</line>
<line>then? In respect of the love he bears our house:</line>
<line>he shows in this, he loves his own barn better than</line>
<line>he loves our house. Let me see some more. 'The</line>
<line>purpose you undertake is dangerous;'--why, that's</line>
<line>certain: 'tis dangerous to take a cold, to sleep, to</line>
<line>drink; but I tell you, my lord fool, out of this</line>
<line>nettle, danger, we pluck this flower, safety. 'The</line>
<line>purpose you undertake is dangerous; the friends you</line>
<line>have named uncertain; the time itself unsorted; and</line>
<line>your whole plot too light for the counterpoise of so</line>
<line>great an opposition.' Say you so, say you so? I say</line>
<line>unto you again, you are a shallow cowardly hind, and</line>
<line>you lie.  What a lack-brain is this! By the Lord,</line>
<line>our plot is a good plot as ever was laid; our</line>
<line>friends true and constant: a good plot, good</line>
<line>friends, and full of expectation; an excellent plot,</line>
<line>very good friends. What a frosty-spirited rogue is</line>
<line>this! Why, my lord of York commends the plot and the</line>
<line>general course of action. 'Zounds, an I were now by</line>
<line>this rascal, I could brain him with his lady's fan.</line>
<line>Is there not my father, my uncle and myself? lord</line>
<line>Edmund Mortimer, My lord of York and Owen Glendower?</line>
<line>is there not besides the Douglas? have I not all</line>
<line>their letters to meet me in arms by the ninth of the</line>
<line>next month? and are they not some of them set</line>
<line>forward already? What a pagan rascal is this! an</line>
<line>infidel! Ha! you shall see now in very sincerity</line>
<line>of fear and cold heart, will he to the king and lay</line>
<line>open all our proceedings. O, I could divide myself</line>
<line>and go to buffets, for moving such a dish of</line>
<line>skim milk with so honourable an action! Hang him!</line>
<line>let him tell the king: we are prepared. I will set</line>
<line>forward to-night.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter LADY PERCY</para>
<line>How now, Kate! I must leave you within these two hours.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>O, my good lord, why are you thus alone?</line>
<line>For what offence have I this fortnight been</line>
<line>A banish'd woman from my Harry's bed?</line>
<line>Tell me, sweet lord, what is't that takes from thee</line>
<line>Thy stomach, pleasure and thy golden sleep?</line>
<line>Why dost thou bend thine eyes upon the earth,</line>
<line>And start so often when thou sit'st alone?</line>
<line>Why hast thou lost the fresh blood in thy cheeks;</line>
<line>And given my treasures and my rights of thee</line>
<line>To thick-eyed musing and cursed melancholy?</line>
<line>In thy faint slumbers I by thee have watch'd,</line>
<line>And heard thee murmur tales of iron wars;</line>
<line>Speak terms of manage to thy bounding steed;</line>
<line>Cry 'Courage! to the field!' And thou hast talk'd</line>
<line>Of sallies and retires, of trenches, tents,</line>
<line>Of palisadoes, frontiers, parapets,</line>
<line>Of basilisks, of cannon, culverin,</line>
<line>Of prisoners' ransom and of soldiers slain,</line>
<line>And all the currents of a heady fight.</line>
<line>Thy spirit within thee hath been so at war</line>
<line>And thus hath so bestirr'd thee in thy sleep,</line>
<line>That beads of sweat have stood upon thy brow</line>
<line>Like bubbles in a late-disturbed stream;</line>
<line>And in thy face strange motions have appear'd,</line>
<line>Such as we see when men restrain their breath</line>
<line>On some great sudden hest. O, what portents are these?</line>
<line>Some heavy business hath my lord in hand,</line>
<line>And I must know it, else he loves me not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>What, ho!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Servant</para>
<line>Is Gilliams with the packet gone?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>He is, my lord, an hour ago.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Hath Butler brought those horses from the sheriff?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>One horse, my lord, he brought even now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>What horse? a roan, a crop-ear, is it not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>It is, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>That roan shall by my throne.</line>
<line>Well, I will back him straight: O esperance!</line>
<line>Bid Butler lead him forth into the park.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit Servant</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>But hear you, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>What say'st thou, my lady?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>What is it carries you away?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Why, my horse, my love, my horse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Out, you mad-headed ape!</line>
<line>A weasel hath not such a deal of spleen</line>
<line>As you are toss'd with. In faith,</line>
<line>I'll know your business, Harry, that I will.</line>
<line>I fear my brother Mortimer doth stir</line>
<line>About his title, and hath sent for you</line>
<line>To line his enterprise: but if you go,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>So far afoot, I shall be weary, love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Come, come, you paraquito, answer me</line>
<line>Directly unto this question that I ask:</line>
<line>In faith, I'll break thy little finger, Harry,</line>
<line>An if thou wilt not tell me all things true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Away,</line>
<line>Away, you trifler! Love! I love thee not,</line>
<line>I care not for thee, Kate: this is no world</line>
<line>To play with mammets and to tilt with lips:</line>
<line>We must have bloody noses and crack'd crowns,</line>
<line>And pass them current too. God's me, my horse!</line>
<line>What say'st thou, Kate? what would'st thou</line>
<line>have with me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Do you not love me? do you not, indeed?</line>
<line>Well, do not then; for since you love me not,</line>
<line>I will not love myself. Do you not love me?</line>
<line>Nay, tell me if you speak in jest or no.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Come, wilt thou see me ride?</line>
<line>And when I am on horseback, I will swear</line>
<line>I love thee infinitely. But hark you, Kate;</line>
<line>I must not have you henceforth question me</line>
<line>Whither I go, nor reason whereabout:</line>
<line>Whither I must, I must; and, to conclude,</line>
<line>This evening must I leave you, gentle Kate.</line>
<line>I know you wise, but yet no farther wise</line>
<line>Than Harry Percy's wife: constant you are,</line>
<line>But yet a woman: and for secrecy,</line>
<line>No lady closer; for I well believe</line>
<line>Thou wilt not utter what thou dost not know;</line>
<line>And so far will I trust thee, gentle Kate.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>How! so far?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Not an inch further. But hark you, Kate:</line>
<line>Whither I go, thither shall you go too;</line>
<line>To-day will I set forth, to-morrow you.</line>
<line>Will this content you, Kate?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>It must of force.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The Boar's-Head Tavern, Eastcheap.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PRINCE HENRY and POINS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Ned, prithee, come out of that fat room, and lend me</line>
<line>thy hand to laugh a little.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Where hast been, Hal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>With three or four loggerheads amongst three or four</line>
<line>score hogsheads. I have sounded the very</line>
<line>base-string of humility. Sirrah, I am sworn brother</line>
<line>to a leash of drawers; and can call them all by</line>
<line>their christen names, as Tom, Dick, and Francis.</line>
<line>They take it already upon their salvation, that</line>
<line>though I be but the prince of Wales, yet I am king</line>
<line>of courtesy; and tell me flatly I am no proud Jack,</line>
<line>like Falstaff, but a Corinthian, a lad of mettle, a</line>
<line>good boy, by the Lord, so they call me, and when I</line>
<line>am king of England, I shall command all the good</line>
<line>lads in Eastcheap. They call drinking deep, dyeing</line>
<line>scarlet; and when you breathe in your watering, they</line>
<line>cry  'hem!' and bid you play it off. To conclude, I</line>
<line>am so good a proficient in one quarter of an hour,</line>
<line>that I can drink with any tinker in his own language</line>
<line>during my life. I tell thee, Ned, thou hast lost</line>
<line>much honour, that thou wert not with me in this sweet</line>
<line>action. But, sweet Ned,--to sweeten which name of</line>
<line>Ned, I give thee this pennyworth of sugar, clapped</line>
<line>even now into my hand by an under-skinker, one that</line>
<line>never spake other English in his life than 'Eight</line>
<line>shillings and sixpence' and 'You are welcome,' with</line>
<line>this shrill addition, 'Anon, anon, sir! Score a pint</line>
<line>of bastard in the Half-Moon,' or so. But, Ned, to</line>
<line>drive away the time till Falstaff come, I prithee,</line>
<line>do thou stand in some by-room, while I question my</line>
<line>puny drawer to what end he gave me the sugar; and do</line>
<line>thou never leave calling 'Francis,' that his tale</line>
<line>to me may be nothing but 'Anon.' Step aside, and</line>
<line>I'll show thee a precedent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou art perfect.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit POINS</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter FRANCIS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Anon, anon, sir. Look down into the Pomgarnet, Ralph.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Come hither, Francis.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>My lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>How long hast thou to serve, Francis?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Forsooth, five years, and as much as to--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Anon, anon, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Five year! by'r lady, a long lease for the clinking</line>
<line>of pewter. But, Francis, darest thou be so valiant</line>
<line>as to play the coward with thy indenture and show it</line>
<line>a fair pair of heels and run from it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>O Lord, sir, I'll be sworn upon all the books in</line>
<line>England, I could find in my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Anon, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>How old art thou, Francis?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Let me see--about Michaelmas next I shall be--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Anon, sir. Pray stay a little, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Nay, but hark you, Francis: for the sugar thou</line>
<line>gavest me,'twas a pennyworth, wast't not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>O Lord, I would it had been two!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I will give thee for it a thousand pound: ask me</line>
<line>when thou wilt, and thou shalt have it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Anon, anon.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Anon, Francis? No, Francis; but to-morrow, Francis;</line>
<line>or, Francis, o' Thursday; or indeed, Francis, when</line>
<line>thou wilt. But, Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>My lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou rob this leathern jerkin, crystal-button,</line>
<line>not-pated, agate-ring, puke-stocking, caddis-garter,</line>
<line>smooth-tongue, Spanish-pouch,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>O Lord, sir, who do you mean?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, then, your brown bastard is your only drink;</line>
<line>for look you, Francis, your white canvas doublet</line>
<line>will sully: in Barbary, sir, it cannot come to so much.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>What, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  Francis!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Away, you rogue! dost thou not hear them call?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Here they both call him; the drawer stands amazed,
not knowing which way to go</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Vintner</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Vintner</speaker>
<line>What, standest thou still, and hearest such a</line>
<line>calling? Look to the guests within.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Francis</para>
<line>My lord, old Sir John, with half-a-dozen more, are</line>
<line>at the door: shall I let them in?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Let them alone awhile, and then open the door.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Vintner</para>
<line>Poins!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter POINS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Anon, anon, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Sirrah, Falstaff and the rest of the thieves are at</line>
<line>the door: shall we be merry?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>As merry as crickets, my lad. But hark ye; what</line>
<line>cunning match have you made with this jest of the</line>
<line>drawer? come, what's the issue?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I am now of all humours that have showed themselves</line>
<line>humours since the old days of goodman Adam to the</line>
<line>pupil age of this present twelve o'clock at midnight.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter FRANCIS</para>
<line>What's o'clock, Francis?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FRANCIS</speaker>
<line>Anon, anon, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>That ever this fellow should have fewer words than a</line>
<line>parrot, and yet the son of a woman! His industry is</line>
<line>upstairs and downstairs; his eloquence the parcel of</line>
<line>a reckoning. I am not yet of Percy's mind, the</line>
<line>Hotspur of the north; he that kills me some six or</line>
<line>seven dozen of Scots at a breakfast, washes his</line>
<line>hands, and says to his wife 'Fie upon this quiet</line>
<line>life! I want work.' 'O my sweet Harry,' says she,</line>
<line>'how many hast thou killed to-day?' 'Give my roan</line>
<line>horse a drench,' says he; and answers 'Some</line>
<line>fourteen,' an hour after; 'a trifle, a trifle.' I</line>
<line>prithee, call in Falstaff: I'll play Percy, and</line>
<line>that damned brawn shall play Dame Mortimer his</line>
<line>wife. 'Rivo!' says the drunkard. Call in ribs, call in tallow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter FALSTAFF, GADSHILL, BARDOLPH, and PETO;
FRANCIS following with wine</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Welcome, Jack: where hast thou been?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>A plague of all cowards, I say, and a vengeance too!</line>
<line>marry, and amen! Give me a cup of sack, boy. Ere I</line>
<line>lead this life long, I'll sew nether stocks and mend</line>
<line>them and foot them too. A plague of all cowards!</line>
<line>Give me a cup of sack, rogue. Is there no virtue extant?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">He drinks</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Didst thou never see Titan kiss a dish of butter?</line>
<line>pitiful-hearted Titan, that melted at the sweet tale</line>
<line>of the sun's! if thou didst, then behold that compound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>You rogue, here's lime in this sack too: there is</line>
<line>nothing but roguery to be found in villanous man:</line>
<line>yet a coward is worse than a cup of sack with lime</line>
<line>in it. A villanous coward! Go thy ways, old Jack;</line>
<line>die when thou wilt, if manhood, good manhood, be</line>
<line>not forgot upon the face of the earth, then am I a</line>
<line>shotten herring. There live not three good men</line>
<line>unhanged in England; and one of them is fat and</line>
<line>grows old: God help the while! a bad world, I say.</line>
<line>I would I were a weaver; I could sing psalms or any</line>
<line>thing. A plague of all cowards, I say still.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>How now, wool-sack! what mutter you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>A king's son! If I do not beat thee out of thy</line>
<line>kingdom with a dagger of lath, and drive all thy</line>
<line>subjects afore thee like a flock of wild-geese,</line>
<line>I'll never wear hair on my face more. You Prince of Wales!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, you whoreson round man, what's the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Are not you a coward? answer me to that: and Poins there?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>'Zounds, ye fat paunch, an ye call me coward, by the</line>
<line>Lord, I'll stab thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I call thee coward! I'll see thee damned ere I call</line>
<line>thee coward: but I would give a thousand pound I</line>
<line>could run as fast as thou canst. You are straight</line>
<line>enough in the shoulders, you care not who sees your</line>
<line>back: call you that backing of your friends? A</line>
<line>plague upon such backing! give me them that will</line>
<line>face me. Give me a cup of sack: I am a rogue, if I</line>
<line>drunk to-day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O villain! thy lips are scarce wiped since thou</line>
<line>drunkest last.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>All's one for that.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He drinks</para>
<line>A plague of all cowards, still say I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What's the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What's the matter! there be four of us here have</line>
<line>ta'en a thousand pound this day morning.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Where is it, Jack? where is it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Where is it! taken from us it is: a hundred upon</line>
<line>poor four of us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, a hundred, man?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I am a rogue, if I were not at half-sword with a</line>
<line>dozen of them two hours together. I have 'scaped by</line>
<line>miracle. I am eight times thrust through the</line>
<line>doublet, four through the hose; my buckler cut</line>
<line>through and through; my sword hacked like a</line>
<line>hand-saw--ecce signum! I never dealt better since</line>
<line>I was a man: all would not do. A plague of all</line>
<line>cowards! Let them speak: if they speak more or</line>
<line>less than truth, they are villains and the sons of darkness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Speak, sirs; how was it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>We four set upon some dozen--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Sixteen at least, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>And bound them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line>No, no, they were not bound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>You rogue, they were bound, every man of them; or I</line>
<line>am a Jew else, an Ebrew Jew.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GADSHILL</speaker>
<line>As we were sharing, some six or seven fresh men set upon us--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>And unbound the rest, and then come in the other.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, fought you with them all?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>All! I know not what you call all; but if I fought</line>
<line>not with fifty of them, I am a bunch of radish: if</line>
<line>there were not two or three and fifty upon poor old</line>
<line>Jack, then am I no two-legged creature.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Pray God you have not murdered some of them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Nay, that's past praying for: I have peppered two</line>
<line>of them; two I am sure I have paid, two rogues</line>
<line>in buckram suits. I tell thee what, Hal, if I tell</line>
<line>thee a lie, spit in my face, call me horse. Thou</line>
<line>knowest my old ward; here I lay and thus I bore my</line>
<line>point. Four rogues in buckram let drive at me--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, four? thou saidst but two even now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Four, Hal; I told thee four.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Ay, ay, he said four.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>These four came all a-front, and mainly thrust at</line>
<line>me. I made me no more ado but took all their seven</line>
<line>points in my target, thus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Seven? why, there were but four even now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>In buckram?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Ay, four, in buckram suits.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Seven, by these hilts, or I am a villain else.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Prithee, let him alone; we shall have more anon.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Dost thou hear me, Hal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Ay, and mark thee too, Jack.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Do so, for it is worth the listening to. These nine</line>
<line>in buckram that I told thee of--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>So, two more already.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Their points being broken,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Down fell their hose.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Began to give me ground: but I followed me close,</line>
<line>came in foot and hand; and with a thought seven of</line>
<line>the eleven I paid.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O monstrous! eleven buckram men grown out of two!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>But, as the devil would have it, three misbegotten</line>
<line>knaves in Kendal green came at my back and let drive</line>
<line>at me; for it was so dark, Hal, that thou couldst</line>
<line>not see thy hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>These lies are like their father that begets them;</line>
<line>gross as a mountain, open, palpable. Why, thou</line>
<line>clay-brained guts, thou knotty-pated fool, thou</line>
<line>whoreson, obscene, grease tallow-catch,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What, art thou mad? art thou mad? is not the truth</line>
<line>the truth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, how couldst thou know these men in Kendal</line>
<line>green, when it was so dark thou couldst not see thy</line>
<line>hand? come, tell us your reason: what sayest thou to this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Come, your reason, Jack, your reason.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What, upon compulsion? 'Zounds, an I were at the</line>
<line>strappado, or all the racks in the world, I would</line>
<line>not tell you on compulsion. Give you a reason on</line>
<line>compulsion! If reasons were as plentiful as</line>
<line>blackberries, I would give no man a reason upon</line>
<line>compulsion, I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I'll be no longer guilty of this sin; this sanguine</line>
<line>coward, this bed-presser, this horseback-breaker,</line>
<line>this huge hill of flesh,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Sblood, you starveling, you elf-skin, you dried</line>
<line>neat's tongue, you bull's pizzle, you stock-fish! O</line>
<line>for breath to utter what is like thee! you</line>
<line>tailor's-yard, you sheath, you bowcase; you vile</line>
<line>standing-tuck,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, breathe awhile, and then to it again: and</line>
<line>when thou hast tired thyself in base comparisons,</line>
<line>hear me speak but this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Mark, Jack.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>We two saw you four set on four and bound them, and</line>
<line>were masters of their wealth. Mark now, how a plain</line>
<line>tale shall put you down. Then did we two set on you</line>
<line>four; and, with a word, out-faced you from your</line>
<line>prize, and have it; yea, and can show it you here in</line>
<line>the house: and, Falstaff, you carried your guts</line>
<line>away as nimbly, with as quick dexterity, and roared</line>
<line>for mercy and still run and roared, as ever I heard</line>
<line>bull-calf. What a slave art thou, to hack thy sword</line>
<line>as thou hast done, and then say it was in fight!</line>
<line>What trick, what device, what starting-hole, canst</line>
<line>thou now find out to hide thee from this open and</line>
<line>apparent shame?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>Come, let's hear, Jack; what trick hast thou now?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>By the Lord, I knew ye as well as he that made ye.</line>
<line>Why, hear you, my masters: was it for me to kill the</line>
<line>heir-apparent? should I turn upon the true prince?</line>
<line>why, thou knowest I am as valiant as Hercules: but</line>
<line>beware instinct; the lion will not touch the true</line>
<line>prince. Instinct is a great matter; I was now a</line>
<line>coward on instinct. I shall think the better of</line>
<line>myself and thee during my life; I for a valiant</line>
<line>lion, and thou for a true prince. But, by the Lord,</line>
<line>lads, I am glad you have the money. Hostess, clap</line>
<line>to the doors: watch to-night, pray to-morrow.</line>
<line>Gallants, lads, boys, hearts of gold, all the titles</line>
<line>of good fellowship come to you! What, shall we be</line>
<line>merry? shall we have a play extempore?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Content; and the argument shall be thy running away.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Ah, no more of that, Hal, an thou lovest me!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter Hostess</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>O Jesu, my lord the prince!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>How now, my lady the hostess! what sayest thou to</line>
<line>me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Marry, my lord, there is a nobleman of the court at</line>
<line>door would speak with you: he says he comes from</line>
<line>your father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Give him as much as will make him a royal man, and</line>
<line>send him back again to my mother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What manner of man is he?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>An old man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What doth gravity out of his bed at midnight? Shall</line>
<line>I give him his answer?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Prithee, do, Jack.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Faith, and I'll send him packing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit FALSTAFF</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Now, sirs: by'r lady, you fought fair; so did you,</line>
<line>Peto; so did you, Bardolph: you are lions too, you</line>
<line>ran away upon instinct, you will not touch the true</line>
<line>prince; no, fie!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>'Faith, I ran when I saw others run.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>'Faith, tell me now in earnest, how came Falstaff's</line>
<line>sword so hacked?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line>Why, he hacked it with his dagger, and said he would</line>
<line>swear truth out of England but he would make you</line>
<line>believe it was done in fight, and persuaded us to do the like.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Yea, and to tickle our noses with spear-grass to</line>
<line>make them bleed, and then to beslubber our garments</line>
<line>with it and swear it was the blood of true men. I</line>
<line>did that I did not this seven year before, I blushed</line>
<line>to hear his monstrous devices.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O villain, thou stolest a cup of sack eighteen years</line>
<line>ago, and wert taken with the manner, and ever since</line>
<line>thou hast blushed extempore. Thou hadst fire and</line>
<line>sword on thy side, and yet thou rannest away: what</line>
<line>instinct hadst thou for it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>My lord, do you see these meteors? do you behold</line>
<line>these exhalations?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>What think you they portend?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Hot livers and cold purses.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Choler, my lord, if rightly taken.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>No, if rightly taken, halter.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter FALSTAFF</para>
<line>Here comes lean Jack, here comes bare-bone.</line>
<line>How now, my sweet creature of bombast!</line>
<line>How long is't ago, Jack, since thou sawest thine own knee?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>My own knee! when I was about thy years, Hal, I was</line>
<line>not an eagle's talon in the waist; I could have</line>
<line>crept into any alderman's thumb-ring: a plague of</line>
<line>sighing and grief! it blows a man up like a</line>
<line>bladder. There's villanous news abroad: here was</line>
<line>Sir John Bracy from your father; you must to the</line>
<line>court in the morning. That same mad fellow of the</line>
<line>north, Percy, and he of Wales, that gave Amamon the</line>
<line>bastinado and made Lucifer cuckold and swore the</line>
<line>devil his true liegeman upon the cross of a Welsh</line>
<line>hook--what a plague call you him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">POINS</speaker>
<line>O, Glendower.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Owen, Owen, the same; and his son-in-law Mortimer,</line>
<line>and old Northumberland, and that sprightly Scot of</line>
<line>Scots, Douglas, that runs o' horseback up a hill</line>
<line>perpendicular,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>He that rides at high speed and with his pistol</line>
<line>kills a sparrow flying.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>You have hit it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>So did he never the sparrow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, that rascal hath good mettle in him; he will not run.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, what a rascal art thou then, to praise him so</line>
<line>for running!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>O' horseback, ye cuckoo; but afoot he will not budge a foot.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Yes, Jack, upon instinct.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I grant ye, upon instinct. Well, he is there too,</line>
<line>and one Mordake, and a thousand blue-caps more:</line>
<line>Worcester is stolen away to-night; thy father's</line>
<line>beard is turned white with the news: you may buy</line>
<line>land now as cheap as stinking mackerel.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, then, it is like, if there come a hot June and</line>
<line>this civil buffeting hold, we shall buy maidenheads</line>
<line>as they buy hob-nails, by the hundreds.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>By the mass, lad, thou sayest true; it is like we</line>
<line>shall have good trading that way. But tell me, Hal,</line>
<line>art not thou horrible afeard? thou being</line>
<line>heir-apparent, could the world pick thee out three</line>
<line>such enemies again as that fiend Douglas, that</line>
<line>spirit Percy, and that devil Glendower? Art thou</line>
<line>not horribly afraid? doth not thy blood thrill at</line>
<line>it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Not a whit, i' faith; I lack some of thy instinct.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, thou wert be horribly chid tomorrow when thou</line>
<line>comest to thy father: if thou love me, practise an answer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Do thou stand for my father, and examine me upon the</line>
<line>particulars of my life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Shall I? content: this chair shall be my state,</line>
<line>this dagger my sceptre, and this cushion my crown.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thy state is taken for a joined-stool, thy golden</line>
<line>sceptre for a leaden dagger, and thy precious rich</line>
<line>crown for a pitiful bald crown!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, an the fire of grace be not quite out of thee,</line>
<line>now shalt thou be moved. Give me a cup of sack to</line>
<line>make my eyes look red, that it may be thought I have</line>
<line>wept; for I must speak in passion, and I will do it</line>
<line>in King Cambyses' vein.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, here is my leg.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>And here is my speech. Stand aside, nobility.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>O Jesu, this is excellent sport, i' faith!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Weep not, sweet queen; for trickling tears are vain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>O, the father, how he holds his countenance!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>For God's sake, lords, convey my tristful queen;</line>
<line>For tears do stop the flood-gates of her eyes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>O Jesu, he doth it as like one of these harlotry</line>
<line>players as ever I see!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Peace, good pint-pot; peace, good tickle-brain.</line>
<line>Harry, I do not only marvel where thou spendest thy</line>
<line>time, but also how thou art accompanied: for though</line>
<line>the camomile, the more it is trodden on the faster</line>
<line>it grows, yet youth, the more it is wasted the</line>
<line>sooner it wears. That thou art my son, I have</line>
<line>partly thy mother's word, partly my own opinion,</line>
<line>but chiefly a villanous trick of thine eye and a</line>
<line>foolish-hanging of thy nether lip, that doth warrant</line>
<line>me. If then thou be son to me, here lies the point;</line>
<line>why, being son to me, art thou so pointed at? Shall</line>
<line>the blessed sun of heaven prove a micher and eat</line>
<line>blackberries? a question not to be asked. Shall</line>
<line>the sun of England prove a thief and take purses? a</line>
<line>question to be asked. There is a thing, Harry,</line>
<line>which thou hast often heard of and it is known to</line>
<line>many in our land by the name of pitch: this pitch,</line>
<line>as ancient writers do report, doth defile; so doth</line>
<line>the company thou keepest: for, Harry, now I do not</line>
<line>speak to thee in drink but in tears, not in</line>
<line>pleasure but in passion, not in words only, but in</line>
<line>woes also: and yet there is a virtuous man whom I</line>
<line>have often noted in thy company, but I know not his name.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What manner of man, an it like your majesty?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>A goodly portly man, i' faith, and a corpulent; of a</line>
<line>cheerful look, a pleasing eye and a most noble</line>
<line>carriage; and, as I think, his age some fifty, or,</line>
<line>by'r lady, inclining to three score; and now I</line>
<line>remember me, his name is Falstaff: if that man</line>
<line>should be lewdly given, he deceiveth me; for, Harry,</line>
<line>I see virtue in his looks. If then the tree may be</line>
<line>known by the fruit, as the fruit by the tree, then,</line>
<line>peremptorily I speak it, there is virtue in that</line>
<line>Falstaff: him keep with, the rest banish. And tell</line>
<line>me now, thou naughty varlet, tell me, where hast</line>
<line>thou been this month?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Dost thou speak like a king? Do thou stand for me,</line>
<line>and I'll play my father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Depose me? if thou dost it half so gravely, so</line>
<line>majestically, both in word and matter, hang me up by</line>
<line>the heels for a rabbit-sucker or a poulter's hare.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Well, here I am set.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>And here I stand: judge, my masters.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Now, Harry, whence come you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>My noble lord, from Eastcheap.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>The complaints I hear of thee are grievous.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Sblood, my lord, they are false: nay, I'll tickle</line>
<line>ye for a young prince, i' faith.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Swearest thou, ungracious boy? henceforth ne'er look</line>
<line>on me. Thou art violently carried away from grace:</line>
<line>there is a devil haunts thee in the likeness of an</line>
<line>old fat man; a tun of man is thy companion. Why</line>
<line>dost thou converse with that trunk of humours, that</line>
<line>bolting-hutch of beastliness, that swollen parcel</line>
<line>of dropsies, that huge bombard of sack, that stuffed</line>
<line>cloak-bag of guts, that roasted Manningtree ox with</line>
<line>the pudding in his belly, that reverend vice, that</line>
<line>grey iniquity, that father ruffian, that vanity in</line>
<line>years? Wherein is he good, but to taste sack and</line>
<line>drink it? wherein neat and cleanly, but to carve a</line>
<line>capon and eat it? wherein cunning, but in craft?</line>
<line>wherein crafty, but in villany? wherein villanous,</line>
<line>but in all things? wherein worthy, but in nothing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I would your grace would take me with you: whom</line>
<line>means your grace?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>That villanous abominable misleader of youth,</line>
<line>Falstaff, that old white-bearded Satan.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>My lord, the man I know.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I know thou dost.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>But to say I know more harm in him than in myself,</line>
<line>were to say more than I know. That he is old, the</line>
<line>more the pity, his white hairs do witness it; but</line>
<line>that he is, saving your reverence, a whoremaster,</line>
<line>that I utterly deny. If sack and sugar be a fault,</line>
<line>God help the wicked! if to be old and merry be a</line>
<line>sin, then many an old host that I know is damned: if</line>
<line>to be fat be to be hated, then Pharaoh's lean kine</line>
<line>are to be loved. No, my good lord; banish Peto,</line>
<line>banish Bardolph, banish Poins: but for sweet Jack</line>
<line>Falstaff, kind Jack Falstaff, true Jack Falstaff,</line>
<line>valiant Jack Falstaff, and therefore more valiant,</line>
<line>being, as he is, old Jack Falstaff, banish not him</line>
<line>thy Harry's company, banish not him thy Harry's</line>
<line>company: banish plump Jack, and banish all the world.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I do, I will.</line>
<para role="stagedir">A knocking heard</para>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Hostess, FRANCIS, and BARDOLPH</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter BARDOLPH, running</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>O, my lord, my lord! the sheriff with a most</line>
<line>monstrous watch is at the door.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Out, ye rogue! Play out the play: I have much to</line>
<line>say in the behalf of that Falstaff.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter the Hostess</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>O Jesu, my lord, my lord!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Heigh, heigh! the devil rides upon a fiddlestick:</line>
<line>what's the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>The sheriff and all the watch are at the door: they</line>
<line>are come to search the house. Shall I let them in?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Dost thou hear, Hal? never call a true piece of</line>
<line>gold a counterfeit: thou art essentially mad,</line>
<line>without seeming so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>And thou a natural coward, without instinct.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I deny your major: if you will deny the sheriff,</line>
<line>so; if not, let him enter: if I become not a cart</line>
<line>as well as another man, a plague on my bringing up!</line>
<line>I hope I shall as soon be strangled with a halter as another.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Go, hide thee behind the arras: the rest walk up</line>
<line>above. Now, my masters, for a true face and good</line>
<line>conscience.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Both which I have had: but their date is out, and</line>
<line>therefore I'll hide me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Call in the sheriff.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all except PRINCE HENRY and PETO</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Sheriff and the Carrier</para>
<line>Now, master sheriff, what is your will with me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Sheriff</speaker>
<line>First, pardon me, my lord. A hue and cry</line>
<line>Hath follow'd certain men unto this house.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What men?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Sheriff</speaker>
<line>One of them is well known, my gracious lord,</line>
<line>A gross fat man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Carrier</speaker>
<line>As fat as butter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>The man, I do assure you, is not here;</line>
<line>For I myself at this time have employ'd him.</line>
<line>And, sheriff, I will engage my word to thee</line>
<line>That I will, by to-morrow dinner-time,</line>
<line>Send him to answer thee, or any man,</line>
<line>For any thing he shall be charged withal:</line>
<line>And so let me entreat you leave the house.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Sheriff</speaker>
<line>I will, my lord. There are two gentlemen</line>
<line>Have in this robbery lost three hundred marks.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>It may be so: if he have robb'd these men,</line>
<line>He shall be answerable; and so farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Sheriff</speaker>
<line>Good night, my noble lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I think it is good morrow, is it not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Sheriff</speaker>
<line>Indeed, my lord, I think it be two o'clock.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Sheriff and Carrier</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>This oily rascal is known as well as Paul's. Go,</line>
<line>call him forth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line>Falstaff!--Fast asleep behind the arras, and</line>
<line>snorting like a horse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Hark, how hard he fetches breath. Search his pockets.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He searcheth his pockets, and findeth certain papers</para>
<line>What hast thou found?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line>Nothing but papers, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Let's see what they be: read them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Reads</phrase>  Item, A capon,. . 2s. 2d.</line>
<line>Item, Sauce,. . . 4d.</line>
<line>Item, Sack, two gallons, 5s. 8d.</line>
<line>Item, Anchovies and sack after supper, 2s. 6d.</line>
<line>Item, Bread,        ob.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O monstrous! but one half-penny-worth of bread to</line>
<line>this intolerable deal of sack! What there is else,</line>
<line>keep close; we'll read it at more advantage: there</line>
<line>let him sleep till day. I'll to the court in the</line>
<line>morning. We must all to the wars, and thy place</line>
<line>shall be honourable. I'll procure this fat rogue a</line>
<line>charge of foot; and I know his death will be a</line>
<line>march of twelve-score. The money shall be paid</line>
<line>back again with advantage. Be with me betimes in</line>
<line>the morning; and so, good morrow, Peto.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PETO</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, good my lord.</line>

</linegroup></dialogue>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT III</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Bangor. The Archdeacon's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HOTSPUR, WORCESTER, MORTIMER, and GLENDOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>These promises are fair, the parties sure,</line>
<line>And our induction full of prosperous hope.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Lord Mortimer, and cousin Glendower,</line>
<line>Will you sit down?</line>
<line>And uncle Worcester: a plague upon it!</line>
<line>I have forgot the map.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>No, here it is.</line>
<line>Sit, cousin Percy; sit, good cousin Hotspur,</line>
<line>For by that name as oft as Lancaster</line>
<line>Doth speak of you, his cheek looks pale and with</line>
<line>A rising sigh he wisheth you in heaven.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>And you in hell, as oft as he hears Owen Glendower spoke of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>I cannot blame him: at my nativity</line>
<line>The front of heaven was full of fiery shapes,</line>
<line>Of burning cressets; and at my birth</line>
<line>The frame and huge foundation of the earth</line>
<line>Shaked like a coward.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Why, so it would have done at the same season, if</line>
<line>your mother's cat had but kittened, though yourself</line>
<line>had never been born.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>I say the earth did shake when I was born.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>And I say the earth was not of my mind,</line>
<line>If you suppose as fearing you it shook.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>The heavens were all on fire, the earth did tremble.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>O, then the earth shook to see the heavens on fire,</line>
<line>And not in fear of your nativity.</line>
<line>Diseased nature oftentimes breaks forth</line>
<line>In strange eruptions; oft the teeming earth</line>
<line>Is with a kind of colic pinch'd and vex'd</line>
<line>By the imprisoning of unruly wind</line>
<line>Within her womb; which, for enlargement striving,</line>
<line>Shakes the old beldam earth and topples down</line>
<line>Steeples and moss-grown towers. At your birth</line>
<line>Our grandam earth, having this distemperature,</line>
<line>In passion shook.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Cousin, of many men</line>
<line>I do not bear these crossings. Give me leave</line>
<line>To tell you once again that at my birth</line>
<line>The front of heaven was full of fiery shapes,</line>
<line>The goats ran from the mountains, and the herds</line>
<line>Were strangely clamorous to the frighted fields.</line>
<line>These signs have mark'd me extraordinary;</line>
<line>And all the courses of my life do show</line>
<line>I am not in the roll of common men.</line>
<line>Where is he living, clipp'd in with the sea</line>
<line>That chides the banks of England, Scotland, Wales,</line>
<line>Which calls me pupil, or hath read to me?</line>
<line>And bring him out that is but woman's son</line>
<line>Can trace me in the tedious ways of art</line>
<line>And hold me pace in deep experiments.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I think there's no man speaks better Welsh.</line>
<line>I'll to dinner.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>Peace, cousin Percy; you will make him mad.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>I can call spirits from the vasty deep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Why, so can I, or so can any man;</line>
<line>But will they come when you do call for them?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Why, I can teach you, cousin, to command</line>
<line>The devil.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>And I can teach thee, coz, to shame the devil</line>
<line>By telling truth: tell truth and shame the devil.</line>
<line>If thou have power to raise him, bring him hither,</line>
<line>And I'll be sworn I have power to shame him hence.</line>
<line>O, while you live, tell truth and shame the devil!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>Come, come, no more of this unprofitable chat.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Three times hath Henry Bolingbroke made head</line>
<line>Against my power; thrice from the banks of Wye</line>
<line>And sandy-bottom'd Severn have I sent him</line>
<line>Bootless home and weather-beaten back.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Home without boots, and in foul weather too!</line>
<line>How 'scapes he agues, in the devil's name?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Come, here's the map: shall we divide our right</line>
<line>According to our threefold order ta'en?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>The archdeacon hath divided it</line>
<line>Into three limits very equally:</line>
<line>England, from Trent and Severn hitherto,</line>
<line>By south and east is to my part assign'd:</line>
<line>All westward, Wales beyond the Severn shore,</line>
<line>And all the fertile land within that bound,</line>
<line>To Owen Glendower: and, dear coz, to you</line>
<line>The remnant northward, lying off from Trent.</line>
<line>And our indentures tripartite are drawn;</line>
<line>Which being sealed interchangeably,</line>
<line>A business that this night may execute,</line>
<line>To-morrow, cousin Percy, you and I</line>
<line>And my good Lord of Worcester will set forth</line>
<line>To meet your father and the Scottish power,</line>
<line>As is appointed us, at Shrewsbury.</line>
<line>My father Glendower is not ready yet,</line>
<line>Not shall we need his help these fourteen days.</line>
<line>Within that space you may have drawn together</line>
<line>Your tenants, friends and neighbouring gentlemen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>A shorter time shall send me to you, lords:</line>
<line>And in my conduct shall your ladies come;</line>
<line>From whom you now must steal and take no leave,</line>
<line>For there will be a world of water shed</line>
<line>Upon the parting of your wives and you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Methinks my moiety, north from Burton here,</line>
<line>In quantity equals not one of yours:</line>
<line>See how this river comes me cranking in,</line>
<line>And cuts me from the best of all my land</line>
<line>A huge half-moon, a monstrous cantle out.</line>
<line>I'll have the current in this place damm'd up;</line>
<line>And here the smug and silver Trent shall run</line>
<line>In a new channel, fair and evenly;</line>
<line>It shall not wind with such a deep indent,</line>
<line>To rob me of so rich a bottom here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Not wind? it shall, it must; you see it doth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>Yea, but</line>
<line>Mark how he bears his course, and runs me up</line>
<line>With like advantage on the other side;</line>
<line>Gelding the opposed continent as much</line>
<line>As on the other side it takes from you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Yea, but a little charge will trench him here</line>
<line>And on this north side win this cape of land;</line>
<line>And then he runs straight and even.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I'll have it so: a little charge will do it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>I'll not have it alter'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Will not you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>No, nor you shall not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Who shall say me nay?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Why, that will I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Let me not understand you, then; speak it in Welsh.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>I can speak English, lord, as well as you;</line>
<line>For I was train'd up in the English court;</line>
<line>Where, being but young, I framed to the harp</line>
<line>Many an English ditty lovely well</line>
<line>And gave the tongue a helpful ornament,</line>
<line>A virtue that was never seen in you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Marry,</line>
<line>And I am glad of it with all my heart:</line>
<line>I had rather be a kitten and cry mew</line>
<line>Than one of these same metre ballad-mongers;</line>
<line>I had rather hear a brazen canstick turn'd,</line>
<line>Or a dry wheel grate on the axle-tree;</line>
<line>And that would set my teeth nothing on edge,</line>
<line>Nothing so much as mincing poetry:</line>
<line>'Tis like the forced gait of a shuffling nag.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Come, you shall have Trent turn'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I do not care: I'll give thrice so much land</line>
<line>To any well-deserving friend;</line>
<line>But in the way of bargain, mark ye me,</line>
<line>I'll cavil on the ninth part of a hair.</line>
<line>Are the indentures drawn? shall we be gone?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>The moon shines fair; you may away by night:</line>
<line>I'll haste the writer and withal</line>
<line>Break with your wives of your departure hence:</line>
<line>I am afraid my daughter will run mad,</line>
<line>So much she doteth on her Mortimer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit GLENDOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>Fie, cousin Percy! how you cross my father!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I cannot choose: sometime he angers me</line>
<line>With telling me of the mouldwarp and the ant,</line>
<line>Of the dreamer Merlin and his prophecies,</line>
<line>And of a dragon and a finless fish,</line>
<line>A clip-wing'd griffin and a moulten raven,</line>
<line>A couching lion and a ramping cat,</line>
<line>And such a deal of skimble-skamble stuff</line>
<line>As puts me from my faith. I tell you what;</line>
<line>He held me last night at least nine hours</line>
<line>In reckoning up the several devils' names</line>
<line>That were his lackeys: I cried 'hum,' and 'well, go to,'</line>
<line>But mark'd him not a word. O, he is as tedious</line>
<line>As a tired horse, a railing wife;</line>
<line>Worse than a smoky house: I had rather live</line>
<line>With cheese and garlic in a windmill, far,</line>
<line>Than feed on cates and have him talk to me</line>
<line>In any summer-house in Christendom.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>In faith, he is a worthy gentleman,</line>
<line>Exceedingly well read, and profited</line>
<line>In strange concealments, valiant as a lion</line>
<line>And as wondrous affable and as bountiful</line>
<line>As mines of India. Shall I tell you, cousin?</line>
<line>He holds your temper in a high respect</line>
<line>And curbs himself even of his natural scope</line>
<line>When you come 'cross his humour; faith, he does:</line>
<line>I warrant you, that man is not alive</line>
<line>Might so have tempted him as you have done,</line>
<line>Without the taste of danger and reproof:</line>
<line>But do not use it oft, let me entreat you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>In faith, my lord, you are too wilful-blame;</line>
<line>And since your coming hither have done enough</line>
<line>To put him quite beside his patience.</line>
<line>You must needs learn, lord, to amend this fault:</line>
<line>Though sometimes it show greatness, courage, blood,--</line>
<line>And that's the dearest grace it renders you,--</line>
<line>Yet oftentimes it doth present harsh rage,</line>
<line>Defect of manners, want of government,</line>
<line>Pride, haughtiness, opinion and disdain:</line>
<line>The least of which haunting a nobleman</line>
<line>Loseth men's hearts and leaves behind a stain</line>
<line>Upon the beauty of all parts besides,</line>
<line>Beguiling them of commendation.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Well, I am school'd: good manners be your speed!</line>
<line>Here come our wives, and let us take our leave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter GLENDOWER with the ladies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>This is the deadly spite that angers me;</line>
<line>My wife can speak no English, I no Welsh.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>My daughter weeps: she will not part with you;</line>
<line>She'll be a soldier too, she'll to the wars.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>Good father, tell her that she and my aunt Percy</line>
<line>Shall follow in your conduct speedily.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Glendower speaks to her in Welsh, and she
answers him in the same</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>She is desperate here; a peevish self-wind harlotry,</line>
<line>one that no persuasion can do good upon.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The lady speaks in Welsh</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>I understand thy looks: that pretty Welsh</line>
<line>Which thou pour'st down from these swelling heavens</line>
<line>I am too perfect in; and, but for shame,</line>
<line>In such a parley should I answer thee.</line>
<para role="stagedir">The lady speaks again in Welsh</para>
<line>I understand thy kisses and thou mine,</line>
<line>And that's a feeling disputation:</line>
<line>But I will never be a truant, love,</line>
<line>Till I have learned thy language; for thy tongue</line>
<line>Makes Welsh as sweet as ditties highly penn'd,</line>
<line>Sung by a fair queen in a summer's bower,</line>
<line>With ravishing division, to her lute.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Nay, if you melt, then will she run mad.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The lady speaks again in Welsh</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>O, I am ignorance itself in this!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>She bids you on the wanton rushes lay you down</line>
<line>And rest your gentle head upon her lap,</line>
<line>And she will sing the song that pleaseth you</line>
<line>And on your eyelids crown the god of sleep.</line>
<line>Charming your blood with pleasing heaviness,</line>
<line>Making such difference 'twixt wake and sleep</line>
<line>As is the difference betwixt day and night</line>
<line>The hour before the heavenly-harness'd team</line>
<line>Begins his golden progress in the east.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>With all my heart I'll sit and hear her sing:</line>
<line>By that time will our book, I think, be drawn</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Do so;</line>
<line>And those musicians that shall play to you</line>
<line>Hang in the air a thousand leagues from hence,</line>
<line>And straight they shall be here: sit, and attend.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Come, Kate, thou art perfect in lying down: come,</line>
<line>quick, quick, that I may lay my head in thy lap.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Go, ye giddy goose.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The music plays</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Now I perceive the devil understands Welsh;</line>
<line>And 'tis no marvel he is so humorous.</line>
<line>By'r lady, he is a good musician.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Then should you be nothing but musical for you are</line>
<line>altogether governed by humours. Lie still, ye thief,</line>
<line>and hear the lady sing in Welsh.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I had rather hear Lady, my brach, howl in Irish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Wouldst thou have thy head broken?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Then be still.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Neither;'tis a woman's fault.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Now God help thee!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>To the Welsh lady's bed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>What's that?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Peace! she sings.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Here the lady sings a Welsh song</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Come, Kate, I'll have your song too.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Not mine, in good sooth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Not yours, in good sooth! Heart! you swear like a</line>
<line>comfit-maker's wife. 'Not you, in good sooth,' and</line>
<line>'as true as I live,' and 'as God shall mend me,' and</line>
<line>'as sure as day,'</line>
<line>And givest such sarcenet surety for thy oaths,</line>
<line>As if thou never walk'st further than Finsbury.</line>
<line>Swear me, Kate, like a lady as thou art,</line>
<line>A good mouth-filling oath, and leave 'in sooth,'</line>
<line>And such protest of pepper-gingerbread,</line>
<line>To velvet-guards and Sunday-citizens.</line>
<line>Come, sing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LADY PERCY</speaker>
<line>I will not sing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>'Tis the next way to turn tailor, or be red-breast</line>
<line>teacher. An the indentures be drawn, I'll away</line>
<line>within these two hours; and so, come in when ye will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GLENDOWER</speaker>
<line>Come, come, Lord Mortimer; you are as slow</line>
<line>As hot Lord Percy is on fire to go.</line>
<line>By this our book is drawn; we'll but seal,</line>
<line>And then to horse immediately.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MORTIMER</speaker>
<line>With all my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  London. The palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING HENRY IV, PRINCE HENRY, and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Lords, give us leave; the Prince of Wales and I</line>
<line>Must have some private conference; but be near at hand,</line>
<line>For we shall presently have need of you.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Lords</para>
<line>I know not whether God will have it so,</line>
<line>For some displeasing service I have done,</line>
<line>That, in his secret doom, out of my blood</line>
<line>He'll breed revengement and a scourge for me;</line>
<line>But thou dost in thy passages of life</line>
<line>Make me believe that thou art only mark'd</line>
<line>For the hot vengeance and the rod of heaven</line>
<line>To punish my mistreadings. Tell me else,</line>
<line>Could such inordinate and low desires,</line>
<line>Such poor, such bare, such lewd, such mean attempts,</line>
<line>Such barren pleasures, rude society,</line>
<line>As thou art match'd withal and grafted to,</line>
<line>Accompany the greatness of thy blood</line>
<line>And hold their level with thy princely heart?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>So please your majesty, I would I could</line>
<line>Quit all offences with as clear excuse</line>
<line>As well as I am doubtless I can purge</line>
<line>Myself of many I am charged withal:</line>
<line>Yet such extenuation let me beg,</line>
<line>As, in reproof of many tales devised,</line>
<line>which oft the ear of greatness needs must hear,</line>
<line>By smiling pick-thanks and base news-mongers,</line>
<line>I may, for some things true, wherein my youth</line>
<line>Hath faulty wander'd and irregular,</line>
<line>Find pardon on my true submission.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>God pardon thee! yet let me wonder, Harry,</line>
<line>At thy affections, which do hold a wing</line>
<line>Quite from the flight of all thy ancestors.</line>
<line>Thy place in council thou hast rudely lost.</line>
<line>Which by thy younger brother is supplied,</line>
<line>And art almost an alien to the hearts</line>
<line>Of all the court and princes of my blood:</line>
<line>The hope and expectation of thy time</line>
<line>Is ruin'd, and the soul of every man</line>
<line>Prophetically doth forethink thy fall.</line>
<line>Had I so lavish of my presence been,</line>
<line>So common-hackney'd in the eyes of men,</line>
<line>So stale and cheap to vulgar company,</line>
<line>Opinion, that did help me to the crown,</line>
<line>Had still kept loyal to possession</line>
<line>And left me in reputeless banishment,</line>
<line>A fellow of no mark nor likelihood.</line>
<line>By being seldom seen, I could not stir</line>
<line>But like a comet I was wonder'd at;</line>
<line>That men would tell their children 'This is he;'</line>
<line>Others would say 'Where, which is Bolingbroke?'</line>
<line>And then I stole all courtesy from heaven,</line>
<line>And dress'd myself in such humility</line>
<line>That I did pluck allegiance from men's hearts,</line>
<line>Loud shouts and salutations from their mouths,</line>
<line>Even in the presence of the crowned king.</line>
<line>Thus did I keep my person fresh and new;</line>
<line>My presence, like a robe pontifical,</line>
<line>Ne'er seen but wonder'd at: and so my state,</line>
<line>Seldom but sumptuous, showed like a feast</line>
<line>And won by rareness such solemnity.</line>
<line>The skipping king, he ambled up and down</line>
<line>With shallow jesters and rash bavin wits,</line>
<line>Soon kindled and soon burnt; carded his state,</line>
<line>Mingled his royalty with capering fools,</line>
<line>Had his great name profaned with their scorns</line>
<line>And gave his countenance, against his name,</line>
<line>To laugh at gibing boys and stand the push</line>
<line>Of every beardless vain comparative,</line>
<line>Grew a companion to the common streets,</line>
<line>Enfeoff'd himself to popularity;</line>
<line>That, being daily swallow'd by men's eyes,</line>
<line>They surfeited with honey and began</line>
<line>To loathe the taste of sweetness, whereof a little</line>
<line>More than a little is by much too much.</line>
<line>So when he had occasion to be seen,</line>
<line>He was but as the cuckoo is in June,</line>
<line>Heard, not regarded; seen, but with such eyes</line>
<line>As, sick and blunted with community,</line>
<line>Afford no extraordinary gaze,</line>
<line>Such as is bent on sun-like majesty</line>
<line>When it shines seldom in admiring eyes;</line>
<line>But rather drowzed and hung their eyelids down,</line>
<line>Slept in his face and render'd such aspect</line>
<line>As cloudy men use to their adversaries,</line>
<line>Being with his presence glutted, gorged and full.</line>
<line>And in that very line, Harry, standest thou;</line>
<line>For thou has lost thy princely privilege</line>
<line>With vile participation: not an eye</line>
<line>But is a-weary of thy common sight,</line>
<line>Save mine, which hath desired to see thee more;</line>
<line>Which now doth that I would not have it do,</line>
<line>Make blind itself with foolish tenderness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I shall hereafter, my thrice gracious lord,</line>
<line>Be more myself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>For all the world</line>
<line>As thou art to this hour was Richard then</line>
<line>When I from France set foot at Ravenspurgh,</line>
<line>And even as I was then is Percy now.</line>
<line>Now, by my sceptre and my soul to boot,</line>
<line>He hath more worthy interest to the state</line>
<line>Than thou the shadow of succession;</line>
<line>For of no right, nor colour like to right,</line>
<line>He doth fill fields with harness in the realm,</line>
<line>Turns head against the lion's armed jaws,</line>
<line>And, being no more in debt to years than thou,</line>
<line>Leads ancient lords and reverend bishops on</line>
<line>To bloody battles and to bruising arms.</line>
<line>What never-dying honour hath he got</line>
<line>Against renowned Douglas! whose high deeds,</line>
<line>Whose hot incursions and great name in arms</line>
<line>Holds from all soldiers chief majority</line>
<line>And military title capital</line>
<line>Through all the kingdoms that acknowledge Christ:</line>
<line>Thrice hath this Hotspur, Mars in swathling clothes,</line>
<line>This infant warrior, in his enterprises</line>
<line>Discomfited great Douglas, ta'en him once,</line>
<line>Enlarged him and made a friend of him,</line>
<line>To fill the mouth of deep defiance up</line>
<line>And shake the peace and safety of our throne.</line>
<line>And what say you to this? Percy, Northumberland,</line>
<line>The Archbishop's grace of York, Douglas, Mortimer,</line>
<line>Capitulate against us and are up.</line>
<line>But wherefore do I tell these news to thee?</line>
<line>Why, Harry, do I tell thee of my foes,</line>
<line>Which art my near'st and dearest enemy?</line>
<line>Thou that art like enough, through vassal fear,</line>
<line>Base inclination and the start of spleen</line>
<line>To fight against me under Percy's pay,</line>
<line>To dog his heels and curtsy at his frowns,</line>
<line>To show how much thou art degenerate.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Do not think so; you shall not find it so:</line>
<line>And God forgive them that so much have sway'd</line>
<line>Your majesty's good thoughts away from me!</line>
<line>I will redeem all this on Percy's head</line>
<line>And in the closing of some glorious day</line>
<line>Be bold to tell you that I am your son;</line>
<line>When I will wear a garment all of blood</line>
<line>And stain my favours in a bloody mask,</line>
<line>Which, wash'd away, shall scour my shame with it:</line>
<line>And that shall be the day, whene'er it lights,</line>
<line>That this same child of honour and renown,</line>
<line>This gallant Hotspur, this all-praised knight,</line>
<line>And your unthought-of Harry chance to meet.</line>
<line>For every honour sitting on his helm,</line>
<line>Would they were multitudes, and on my head</line>
<line>My shames redoubled! for the time will come,</line>
<line>That I shall make this northern youth exchange</line>
<line>His glorious deeds for my indignities.</line>
<line>Percy is but my factor, good my lord,</line>
<line>To engross up glorious deeds on my behalf;</line>
<line>And I will call him to so strict account,</line>
<line>That he shall render every glory up,</line>
<line>Yea, even the slightest worship of his time,</line>
<line>Or I will tear the reckoning from his heart.</line>
<line>This, in the name of God, I promise here:</line>
<line>The which if He be pleased I shall perform,</line>
<line>I do beseech your majesty may salve</line>
<line>The long-grown wounds of my intemperance:</line>
<line>If not, the end of life cancels all bands;</line>
<line>And I will die a hundred thousand deaths</line>
<line>Ere break the smallest parcel of this vow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>A hundred thousand rebels die in this:</line>
<line>Thou shalt have charge and sovereign trust herein.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter BLUNT</para>
<line>How now, good Blunt? thy looks are full of speed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>So hath the business that I come to speak of.</line>
<line>Lord Mortimer of Scotland hath sent word</line>
<line>That Douglas and the English rebels met</line>
<line>The eleventh of this month at Shrewsbury</line>
<line>A mighty and a fearful head they are,</line>
<line>If promises be kept on every hand,</line>
<line>As ever offer'd foul play in the state.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>The Earl of Westmoreland set forth to-day;</line>
<line>With him my son, Lord John of Lancaster;</line>
<line>For this advertisement is five days old:</line>
<line>On Wednesday next, Harry, you shall set forward;</line>
<line>On Thursday we ourselves will march: our meeting</line>
<line>Is Bridgenorth: and, Harry, you shall march</line>
<line>Through Gloucestershire; by which account,</line>
<line>Our business valued, some twelve days hence</line>
<line>Our general forces at Bridgenorth shall meet.</line>
<line>Our hands are full of business: let's away;</line>
<line>Advantage feeds him fat, while men delay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene">
<title>Scene III  Eastcheap. The Boar's-Head Tavern.</title>

<para role="stagedir">Enter FALSTAFF and BARDOLPH</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Bardolph, am I not fallen away vilely since this last</line>
<line>action? do I not bate? do I not dwindle? Why my</line>
<line>skin hangs about me like an like an old lady's loose</line>
<line>gown; I am withered like an old apple-john. Well,</line>
<line>I'll repent, and that suddenly, while I am in some</line>
<line>liking; I shall be out of heart shortly, and then I</line>
<line>shall have no strength to repent. An I have not</line>
<line>forgotten what the inside of a church is made of, I</line>
<line>am a peppercorn, a brewer's horse: the inside of a</line>
<line>church! Company, villanous company, hath been the</line>
<line>spoil of me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Sir John, you are so fretful, you cannot live long.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Why, there is it: come sing me a bawdy song; make</line>
<line>me merry. I was as virtuously given as a gentleman</line>
<line>need to be; virtuous enough; swore little; diced not</line>
<line>above seven times a week; went to a bawdy-house once</line>
<line>in a quarter--of an hour; paid money that I</line>
<line>borrowed, three of four times; lived well and in</line>
<line>good compass: and now I live out of all order, out</line>
<line>of all compass.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Why, you are so fat, Sir John, that you must needs</line>
<line>be out of all compass, out of all reasonable</line>
<line>compass, Sir John.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Do thou amend thy face, and I'll amend my life:</line>
<line>thou art our admiral, thou bearest the lantern in</line>
<line>the poop, but 'tis in the nose of thee; thou art the</line>
<line>Knight of the Burning Lamp.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Why, Sir John, my face does you no harm.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>No, I'll be sworn; I make as good use of it as many</line>
<line>a man doth of a Death's-head or a memento mori: I</line>
<line>never see thy face but I think upon hell-fire and</line>
<line>Dives that lived in purple; for there he is in his</line>
<line>robes, burning, burning. If thou wert any way</line>
<line>given to virtue, I would swear by thy face; my oath</line>
<line>should be 'By this fire, that's God's angel:' but</line>
<line>thou art altogether given over; and wert indeed, but</line>
<line>for the light in thy face, the son of utter</line>
<line>darkness. When thou rannest up Gadshill in the</line>
<line>night to catch my horse, if I did not think thou</line>
<line>hadst been an ignis fatuus or a ball of wildfire,</line>
<line>there's no purchase in money. O, thou art a</line>
<line>perpetual triumph, an everlasting bonfire-light!</line>
<line>Thou hast saved me a thousand marks in links and</line>
<line>torches, walking with thee in the night betwixt</line>
<line>tavern and tavern: but the sack that thou hast</line>
<line>drunk me would have bought me lights as good cheap</line>
<line>at the dearest chandler's in Europe. I have</line>
<line>maintained that salamander of yours with fire any</line>
<line>time this two and thirty years; God reward me for</line>
<line>it!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>'Sblood, I would my face were in your belly!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>God-a-mercy! so should I be sure to be heart-burned.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Hostess</para>
<line>How now, Dame Partlet the hen! have you inquired</line>
<line>yet who picked my pocket?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Why, Sir John, what do you think, Sir John? do you</line>
<line>think I keep thieves in my house? I have searched,</line>
<line>I have inquired, so has my husband, man by man, boy</line>
<line>by boy, servant by servant: the tithe of a hair</line>
<line>was never lost in my house before.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Ye lie, hostess: Bardolph was shaved and lost many</line>
<line>a hair; and I'll be sworn my pocket was picked. Go</line>
<line>to, you are a woman, go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Who, I? no; I defy thee: God's light, I was never</line>
<line>called so in mine own house before.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Go to, I know you well enough.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>No, Sir John; You do not know me, Sir John. I know</line>
<line>you, Sir John: you owe me money, Sir John; and now</line>
<line>you pick a quarrel to beguile me of it: I bought</line>
<line>you a dozen of shirts to your back.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Dowlas, filthy dowlas: I have given them away to</line>
<line>bakers' wives, and they have made bolters of them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Now, as I am a true woman, holland of eight</line>
<line>shillings an ell. You owe money here besides, Sir</line>
<line>John, for your diet and by-drinkings, and money lent</line>
<line>you, four and twenty pound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>He had his part of it; let him pay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>He? alas, he is poor; he hath nothing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>How! poor? look upon his face; what call you rich?</line>
<line>let them coin his nose, let them coin his cheeks:</line>
<line>Ill not pay a denier. What, will you make a younker</line>
<line>of me? shall I not take mine case in mine inn but I</line>
<line>shall have my pocket picked? I have lost a</line>
<line>seal-ring of my grandfather's worth forty mark.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>O Jesu, I have heard the prince tell him, I know not</line>
<line>how oft, that ring was copper!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>How! the prince is a Jack, a sneak-cup: 'sblood, an</line>
<line>he were here, I would cudgel him like a dog, if he</line>
<line>would say so.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PRINCE HENRY and PETO, marching, and FALSTAFF
meets them playing on his truncheon like a life</para>
<line>How now, lad! is the wind in that door, i' faith?</line>
<line>must we all march?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Yea, two and two, Newgate fashion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>My lord, I pray you, hear me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What sayest thou, Mistress Quickly? How doth thy</line>
<line>husband? I love him well; he is an honest man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Good my lord, hear me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Prithee, let her alone, and list to me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What sayest thou, Jack?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>The other night I fell asleep here behind the arras</line>
<line>and had my pocket picked: this house is turned</line>
<line>bawdy-house; they pick pockets.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What didst thou lose, Jack?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou believe me, Hal? three or four bonds of</line>
<line>forty pound apiece, and a seal-ring of my</line>
<line>grandfather's.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>A trifle, some eight-penny matter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>So I told him, my lord; and I said I heard your</line>
<line>grace say so: and, my lord, he speaks most vilely</line>
<line>of you, like a foul-mouthed man as he is; and said</line>
<line>he would cudgel you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What! he did not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>There's neither faith, truth, nor womanhood in me else.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>There's no more faith in thee than in a stewed</line>
<line>prune; nor no more truth in thee than in a drawn</line>
<line>fox; and for womanhood, Maid Marian may be the</line>
<line>deputy's wife of the ward to thee. Go, you thing,</line>
<line>go</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Say, what thing? what thing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What thing! why, a thing to thank God on.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>I am no thing to thank God on, I would thou</line>
<line>shouldst know it; I am an honest man's wife: and,</line>
<line>setting thy knighthood aside, thou art a knave to</line>
<line>call me so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Setting thy womanhood aside, thou art a beast to say</line>
<line>otherwise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Say, what beast, thou knave, thou?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What beast! why, an otter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>An otter, Sir John! Why an otter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Why, she's neither fish nor flesh; a man knows not</line>
<line>where to have her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Thou art an unjust man in saying so: thou or any</line>
<line>man knows where to have me, thou knave, thou!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou sayest true, hostess; and he slanders thee most grossly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>So he doth you, my lord; and said this other day you</line>
<line>ought him a thousand pound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Sirrah, do I owe you a thousand pound?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>A thousand pound, Ha! a million: thy love is worth</line>
<line>a million: thou owest me thy love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Hostess</speaker>
<line>Nay, my lord, he called you Jack, and said he would</line>
<line>cudgel you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Did I, Bardolph?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Indeed, Sir John, you said so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Yea, if he said my ring was copper.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I say 'tis copper: darest thou be as good as thy word now?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Why, Hal, thou knowest, as thou art but man, I dare:</line>
<line>but as thou art prince, I fear thee as I fear the</line>
<line>roaring of a lion's whelp.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>And why not as the lion?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>The king is to be feared as the lion: dost thou</line>
<line>think I'll fear thee as I fear thy father? nay, an</line>
<line>I do, I pray God my girdle break.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O, if it should, how would thy guts fall about thy</line>
<line>knees! But, sirrah, there's no room for faith,</line>
<line>truth, nor honesty in this bosom of thine; it is all</line>
<line>filled up with guts and midriff. Charge an honest</line>
<line>woman with picking thy pocket! why, thou whoreson,</line>
<line>impudent, embossed rascal, if there were anything in</line>
<line>thy pocket but tavern-reckonings, memorandums of</line>
<line>bawdy-houses, and one poor penny-worth of</line>
<line>sugar-candy to make thee long-winded, if thy pocket</line>
<line>were enriched with any other injuries but these, I</line>
<line>am a villain: and yet you will stand to if; you will</line>
<line>not pocket up wrong: art thou not ashamed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Dost thou hear, Hal? thou knowest in the state of</line>
<line>innocency Adam fell; and what should poor Jack</line>
<line>Falstaff do in the days of villany? Thou seest I</line>
<line>have more flesh than another man, and therefore more</line>
<line>frailty. You confess then, you picked my pocket?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>It appears so by the story.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Hostess, I forgive thee: go, make ready breakfast;</line>
<line>love thy husband, look to thy servants, cherish thy</line>
<line>guests: thou shalt find me tractable to any honest</line>
<line>reason: thou seest I am pacified still. Nay,</line>
<line>prithee, be gone.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Hostess</para>
<line>Now Hal, to the news at court: for the robbery,</line>
<line>lad, how is that answered?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O, my sweet beef, I must still be good angel to</line>
<line>thee: the money is paid back again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>O, I do not like that paying back; 'tis a double labour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I am good friends with my father and may do any thing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Rob me the exchequer the first thing thou doest, and</line>
<line>do it with unwashed hands too.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Do, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I have procured thee, Jack, a charge of foot.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I would it had been of horse. Where shall I find</line>
<line>one that can steal well? O for a fine thief, of the</line>
<line>age of two and twenty or thereabouts! I am</line>
<line>heinously unprovided. Well, God be thanked for</line>
<line>these rebels, they offend none but the virtuous: I</line>
<line>laud them, I praise them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Bardolph!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>My lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Go bear this letter to Lord John of Lancaster, to my</line>
<line>brother John; this to my Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Bardolph</para>
<line>Go, Peto, to horse, to horse; for thou and I have</line>
<line>thirty miles to ride yet ere dinner time.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Peto</para>
<line>Jack, meet me to-morrow in the temple hall at two</line>
<line>o'clock in the afternoon.</line>
<line>There shalt thou know thy charge; and there receive</line>
<line>Money and order for their furniture.</line>
<line>The land is burning; Percy stands on high;</line>
<line>And either we or they must lower lie.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit PRINCE HENRY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Rare words! brave world! Hostess, my breakfast, come!</line>
<line>O, I could wish this tavern were my drum!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT IV</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  The rebel camp near Shrewsbury.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HOTSPUR, WORCESTER, and DOUGLAS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Well said, my noble Scot: if speaking truth</line>
<line>In this fine age were not thought flattery,</line>
<line>Such attribution should the Douglas have,</line>
<line>As not a soldier of this season's stamp</line>
<line>Should go so general current through the world.</line>
<line>By God, I cannot flatter; I do defy</line>
<line>The tongues of soothers; but a braver place</line>
<line>In my heart's love hath no man than yourself:</line>
<line>Nay, task me to my word; approve me, lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Thou art the king of honour:</line>
<line>No man so potent breathes upon the ground</line>
<line>But I will beard him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Do so, and 'tis well.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Messenger with letters</para>
<line>What letters hast thou there?--I can but thank you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>These letters come from your father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Letters from him! why comes he not himself?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>He cannot come, my lord; he is grievous sick.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>'Zounds! how has he the leisure to be sick</line>
<line>In such a rustling time? Who leads his power?</line>
<line>Under whose government come they along?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>His letters bear his mind, not I, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>I prithee, tell me, doth he keep his bed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>He did, my lord, four days ere I set forth;</line>
<line>And at the time of my departure thence</line>
<line>He was much fear'd by his physicians.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>I would the state of time had first been whole</line>
<line>Ere he by sickness had been visited:</line>
<line>His health was never better worth than now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Sick now! droop now! this sickness doth infect</line>
<line>The very life-blood of our enterprise;</line>
<line>'Tis catching hither, even to our camp.</line>
<line>He writes me here, that inward sickness--</line>
<line>And that his friends by deputation could not</line>
<line>So soon be drawn, nor did he think it meet</line>
<line>To lay so dangerous and dear a trust</line>
<line>On any soul removed but on his own.</line>
<line>Yet doth he give us bold advertisement,</line>
<line>That with our small conjunction we should on,</line>
<line>To see how fortune is disposed to us;</line>
<line>For, as he writes, there is no quailing now.</line>
<line>Because the king is certainly possess'd</line>
<line>Of all our purposes. What say you to it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Your father's sickness is a maim to us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>A perilous gash, a very limb lopp'd off:</line>
<line>And yet, in faith, it is not; his present want</line>
<line>Seems more than we shall find it: were it good</line>
<line>To set the exact wealth of all our states</line>
<line>All at one cast? to set so rich a main</line>
<line>On the nice hazard of one doubtful hour?</line>
<line>It were not good; for therein should we read</line>
<line>The very bottom and the soul of hope,</line>
<line>The very list, the very utmost bound</line>
<line>Of all our fortunes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>'Faith, and so we should;</line>
<line>Where now remains a sweet reversion:</line>
<line>We may boldly spend upon the hope of what</line>
<line>Is to come in:</line>
<line>A comfort of retirement lives in this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>A rendezvous, a home to fly unto.</line>
<line>If that the devil and mischance look big</line>
<line>Upon the maidenhead of our affairs.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>But yet I would your father had been here.</line>
<line>The quality and hair of our attempt</line>
<line>Brooks no division: it will be thought</line>
<line>By some, that know not why he is away,</line>
<line>That wisdom, loyalty and mere dislike</line>
<line>Of our proceedings kept the earl from hence:</line>
<line>And think how such an apprehension</line>
<line>May turn the tide of fearful faction</line>
<line>And breed a kind of question in our cause;</line>
<line>For well you know we of the offering side</line>
<line>Must keep aloof from strict arbitrement,</line>
<line>And stop all sight-holes, every loop from whence</line>
<line>The eye of reason may pry in upon us:</line>
<line>This absence of your father's draws a curtain,</line>
<line>That shows the ignorant a kind of fear</line>
<line>Before not dreamt of.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>You strain too far.</line>
<line>I rather of his absence make this use:</line>
<line>It lends a lustre and more great opinion,</line>
<line>A larger dare to our great enterprise,</line>
<line>Than if the earl were here; for men must think,</line>
<line>If we without his help can make a head</line>
<line>To push against a kingdom, with his help</line>
<line>We shall o'erturn it topsy-turvy down.</line>
<line>Yet all goes well, yet all our joints are whole.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>As heart can think: there is not such a word</line>
<line>Spoke of in Scotland as this term of fear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter SIR RICHARD VERNON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>My cousin Vernon, welcome, by my soul.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Pray God my news be worth a welcome, lord.</line>
<line>The Earl of Westmoreland, seven thousand strong,</line>
<line>Is marching hitherwards; with him Prince John.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>No harm: what more?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>And further, I have learn'd,</line>
<line>The king himself in person is set forth,</line>
<line>Or hitherwards intended speedily,</line>
<line>With strong and mighty preparation.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>He shall be welcome too. Where is his son,</line>
<line>The nimble-footed madcap Prince of Wales,</line>
<line>And his comrades, that daff'd the world aside,</line>
<line>And bid it pass?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>All furnish'd, all in arms;</line>
<line>All plumed like estridges that with the wind</line>
<line>Baited like eagles having lately bathed;</line>
<line>Glittering in golden coats, like images;</line>
<line>As full of spirit as the month of May,</line>
<line>And gorgeous as the sun at midsummer;</line>
<line>Wanton as youthful goats, wild as young bulls.</line>
<line>I saw young Harry, with his beaver on,</line>
<line>His cuisses on his thighs, gallantly arm'd</line>
<line>Rise from the ground like feather'd Mercury,</line>
<line>And vaulted with such ease into his seat,</line>
<line>As if an angel dropp'd down from the clouds,</line>
<line>To turn and wind a fiery Pegasus</line>
<line>And witch the world with noble horsemanship.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>No more, no more: worse than the sun in March,</line>
<line>This praise doth nourish agues. Let them come:</line>
<line>They come like sacrifices in their trim,</line>
<line>And to the fire-eyed maid of smoky war</line>
<line>All hot and bleeding will we offer them:</line>
<line>The mailed Mars shall on his altar sit</line>
<line>Up to the ears in blood. I am on fire</line>
<line>To hear this rich reprisal is so nigh</line>
<line>And yet not ours. Come, let me taste my horse,</line>
<line>Who is to bear me like a thunderbolt</line>
<line>Against the bosom of the Prince of Wales:</line>
<line>Harry to Harry shall, hot horse to horse,</line>
<line>Meet and ne'er part till one drop down a corse.</line>
<line>O that Glendower were come!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>There is more news:</line>
<line>I learn'd in Worcester, as I rode along,</line>
<line>He cannot draw his power this fourteen days.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>That's the worst tidings that I hear of yet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Ay, by my faith, that bears a frosty sound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>What may the king's whole battle reach unto?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>To thirty thousand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Forty let it be:</line>
<line>My father and Glendower being both away,</line>
<line>The powers of us may serve so great a day</line>
<line>Come, let us take a muster speedily:</line>
<line>Doomsday is near; die all, die merrily.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Talk not of dying: I am out of fear</line>
<line>Of death or death's hand for this one-half year.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  A public road near Coventry.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter FALSTAFF and BARDOLPH</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Bardolph, get thee before to Coventry; fill me a</line>
<line>bottle of sack: our soldiers shall march through;</line>
<line>we'll to Sutton Co'fil' tonight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>Will you give me money, captain?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Lay out, lay out.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>This bottle makes an angel.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>An if it do, take it for thy labour; and if it make</line>
<line>twenty, take them all; I'll answer the coinage. Bid</line>
<line>my lieutenant Peto meet me at town's end.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BARDOLPH</speaker>
<line>I will, captain: farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>If I be not ashamed of my soldiers, I am a soused</line>
<line>gurnet. I have misused the king's press damnably.</line>
<line>I have got, in exchange of a hundred and fifty</line>
<line>soldiers, three hundred and odd pounds. I press me</line>
<line>none but good house-holders, yeoman's sons; inquire</line>
<line>me out contracted bachelors, such as had been asked</line>
<line>twice on the banns; such a commodity of warm slaves,</line>
<line>as had as lieve hear the devil as a drum; such as</line>
<line>fear the report of a caliver worse than a struck</line>
<line>fowl or a hurt wild-duck. I pressed me none but such</line>
<line>toasts-and-butter, with hearts in their bellies no</line>
<line>bigger than pins' heads, and they have bought out</line>
<line>their services; and now my whole charge consists of</line>
<line>ancients, corporals, lieutenants, gentlemen of</line>
<line>companies, slaves as ragged as Lazarus in the</line>
<line>painted cloth, where the glutton's dogs licked his</line>
<line>sores; and such as indeed were never soldiers, but</line>
<line>discarded unjust serving-men, younger sons to</line>
<line>younger brothers, revolted tapsters and ostlers</line>
<line>trade-fallen, the cankers of a calm world and a</line>
<line>long peace, ten times more dishonourable ragged than</line>
<line>an old faced ancient: and such have I, to fill up</line>
<line>the rooms of them that have bought out their</line>
<line>services, that you would think that I had a hundred</line>
<line>and fifty tattered prodigals lately come from</line>
<line>swine-keeping, from eating draff and husks. A mad</line>
<line>fellow met me on the way and told me I had unloaded</line>
<line>all the gibbets and pressed the dead bodies. No eye</line>
<line>hath seen such scarecrows. I'll not march through</line>
<line>Coventry with them, that's flat: nay, and the</line>
<line>villains march wide betwixt the legs, as if they had</line>
<line>gyves on; for indeed I had the most of them out of</line>
<line>prison. There's but a shirt and a half in all my</line>
<line>company; and the half shirt is two napkins tacked</line>
<line>together and thrown over the shoulders like an</line>
<line>herald's coat without sleeves; and the shirt, to say</line>
<line>the truth, stolen from my host at Saint Alban's, or</line>
<line>the red-nose innkeeper of Daventry. But that's all</line>
<line>one; they'll find linen enough on every hedge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter the PRINCE and WESTMORELAND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>How now, blown Jack! how now, quilt!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What, Hal! how now, mad wag! what a devil dost thou</line>
<line>in Warwickshire? My good Lord of Westmoreland, I</line>
<line>cry you mercy: I thought your honour had already been</line>
<line>at Shrewsbury.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>Faith, Sir John,'tis more than time that I were</line>
<line>there, and you too; but my powers are there already.</line>
<line>The king, I can tell you, looks for us all: we must</line>
<line>away all night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Tut, never fear me: I am as vigilant as a cat to</line>
<line>steal cream.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I think, to steal cream indeed, for thy theft hath</line>
<line>already made thee butter. But tell me, Jack, whose</line>
<line>fellows are these that come after?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Mine, Hal, mine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I did never see such pitiful rascals.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Tut, tut; good enough to toss; food for powder, food</line>
<line>for powder; they'll fill a pit as well as better:</line>
<line>tush, man, mortal men, mortal men.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>Ay, but, Sir John, methinks they are exceeding poor</line>
<line>and bare, too beggarly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Faith, for their poverty, I know not where they had</line>
<line>that; and for their bareness, I am sure they never</line>
<line>learned that of me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>No I'll be sworn; unless you call three fingers on</line>
<line>the ribs bare. But, sirrah, make haste: Percy is</line>
<line>already in the field.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>What, is the king encamped?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>He is, Sir John: I fear we shall stay too long.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well,</line>
<line>To the latter end of a fray and the beginning of a feast</line>
<line>Fits a dull fighter and a keen guest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The rebel camp near Shrewsbury.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HOTSPUR, WORCESTER, DOUGLAS, and VERNON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>We'll fight with him to-night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>It may not be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>You give him then the advantage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Not a whit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Why say you so? looks he not for supply?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>So do we.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>His is certain, ours is doubtful.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Good cousin, be advised; stir not tonight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Do not, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>You do not counsel well:</line>
<line>You speak it out of fear and cold heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Do me no slander, Douglas: by my life,</line>
<line>And I dare well maintain it with my life,</line>
<line>If well-respected honour bid me on,</line>
<line>I hold as little counsel with weak fear</line>
<line>As you, my lord, or any Scot that this day lives:</line>
<line>Let it be seen to-morrow in the battle</line>
<line>Which of us fears.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Yea, or to-night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Content.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>To-night, say I.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Come, come it nay not be. I wonder much,</line>
<line>Being men of such great leading as you are,</line>
<line>That you foresee not what impediments</line>
<line>Drag back our expedition: certain horse</line>
<line>Of my cousin Vernon's are not yet come up:</line>
<line>Your uncle Worcester's horse came but today;</line>
<line>And now their pride and mettle is asleep,</line>
<line>Their courage with hard labour tame and dull,</line>
<line>That not a horse is half the half of himself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>So are the horses of the enemy</line>
<line>In general, journey-bated and brought low:</line>
<line>The better part of ours are full of rest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>The number of the king exceedeth ours:</line>
<line>For God's sake. cousin, stay till all come in.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The trumpet sounds a parley</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SIR WALTER BLUNT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>I come with gracious offers from the king,</line>
<line>if you vouchsafe me hearing and respect.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Welcome, Sir Walter Blunt; and would to God</line>
<line>You were of our determination!</line>
<line>Some of us love you well; and even those some</line>
<line>Envy your great deservings and good name,</line>
<line>Because you are not of our quality,</line>
<line>But stand against us like an enemy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>And God defend but still I should stand so,</line>
<line>So long as out of limit and true rule</line>
<line>You stand against anointed majesty.</line>
<line>But to my charge. The king hath sent to know</line>
<line>The nature of your griefs, and whereupon</line>
<line>You conjure from the breast of civil peace</line>
<line>Such bold hostility, teaching his duteous land</line>
<line>Audacious cruelty. If that the king</line>
<line>Have any way your good deserts forgot,</line>
<line>Which he confesseth to be manifold,</line>
<line>He bids you name your griefs; and with all speed</line>
<line>You shall have your desires with interest</line>
<line>And pardon absolute for yourself and these</line>
<line>Herein misled by your suggestion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>The king is kind; and well we know the king</line>
<line>Knows at what time to promise, when to pay.</line>
<line>My father and my uncle and myself</line>
<line>Did give him that same royalty he wears;</line>
<line>And when he was not six and twenty strong,</line>
<line>Sick in the world's regard, wretched and low,</line>
<line>A poor unminded outlaw sneaking home,</line>
<line>My father gave him welcome to the shore;</line>
<line>And when he heard him swear and vow to God</line>
<line>He came but to be Duke of Lancaster,</line>
<line>To sue his livery and beg his peace,</line>
<line>With tears of innocency and terms of zeal,</line>
<line>My father, in kind heart and pity moved,</line>
<line>Swore him assistance and perform'd it too.</line>
<line>Now when the lords and barons of the realm</line>
<line>Perceived Northumberland did lean to him,</line>
<line>The more and less came in with cap and knee;</line>
<line>Met him in boroughs, cities, villages,</line>
<line>Attended him on bridges, stood in lanes,</line>
<line>Laid gifts before him, proffer'd him their oaths,</line>
<line>Gave him their heirs, as pages follow'd him</line>
<line>Even at the heels in golden multitudes.</line>
<line>He presently, as greatness knows itself,</line>
<line>Steps me a little higher than his vow</line>
<line>Made to my father, while his blood was poor,</line>
<line>Upon the naked shore at Ravenspurgh;</line>
<line>And now, forsooth, takes on him to reform</line>
<line>Some certain edicts and some strait decrees</line>
<line>That lie too heavy on the commonwealth,</line>
<line>Cries out upon abuses, seems to weep</line>
<line>Over his country's wrongs; and by this face,</line>
<line>This seeming brow of justice, did he win</line>
<line>The hearts of all that he did angle for;</line>
<line>Proceeded further; cut me off the heads</line>
<line>Of all the favourites that the absent king</line>
<line>In deputation left behind him here,</line>
<line>When he was personal in the Irish war.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>Tut, I came not to hear this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Then to the point.</line>
<line>In short time after, he deposed the king;</line>
<line>Soon after that, deprived him of his life;</line>
<line>And in the neck of that, task'd the whole state:</line>
<line>To make that worse, suffer'd his kinsman March,</line>
<line>Who is, if every owner were well placed,</line>
<line>Indeed his king, to be engaged in Wales,</line>
<line>There without ransom to lie forfeited;</line>
<line>Disgraced me in my happy victories,</line>
<line>Sought to entrap me by intelligence;</line>
<line>Rated mine uncle from the council-board;</line>
<line>In rage dismiss'd my father from the court;</line>
<line>Broke oath on oath, committed wrong on wrong,</line>
<line>And in conclusion drove us to seek out</line>
<line>This head of safety; and withal to pry</line>
<line>Into his title, the which we find</line>
<line>Too indirect for long continuance.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>Shall I return this answer to the king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Not so, Sir Walter: we'll withdraw awhile.</line>
<line>Go to the king; and let there be impawn'd</line>
<line>Some surety for a safe return again,</line>
<line>And in the morning early shall my uncle</line>
<line>Bring him our purposes: and so farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>I would you would accept of grace and love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>And may be so we shall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>Pray God you do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  York. The ARCHBISHOP'S palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF YORK and SIR MICHAEL</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Hie, good Sir Michael; bear this sealed brief</line>
<line>With winged haste to the lord marshal;</line>
<line>This to my cousin Scroop, and all the rest</line>
<line>To whom they are directed. If you knew</line>
<line>How much they do to import, you would make haste.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
<line>My good lord,</line>
<line>I guess their tenor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Like enough you do.</line>
<line>To-morrow, good Sir Michael, is a day</line>
<line>Wherein the fortune of ten thousand men</line>
<line>Must bide the touch; for, sir, at Shrewsbury,</line>
<line>As I am truly given to understand,</line>
<line>The king with mighty and quick-raised power</line>
<line>Meets with Lord Harry: and, I fear, Sir Michael,</line>
<line>What with the sickness of Northumberland,</line>
<line>Whose power was in the first proportion,</line>
<line>And what with Owen Glendower's absence thence,</line>
<line>Who with them was a rated sinew too</line>
<line>And comes not in, o'er-ruled by prophecies,</line>
<line>I fear the power of Percy is too weak</line>
<line>To wage an instant trial with the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
<line>Why, my good lord, you need not fear;</line>
<line>There is Douglas and Lord Mortimer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
<line>No, Mortimer is not there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
<line>But there is Mordake, Vernon, Lord Harry Percy,</line>
<line>And there is my Lord of Worcester and a head</line>
<line>Of gallant warriors, noble gentlemen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
<line>And so there is: but yet the king hath drawn</line>
<line>The special head of all the land together:</line>
<line>The Prince of Wales, Lord John of Lancaster,</line>
<line>The noble Westmoreland and warlike Blunt;</line>
<line>And moe corrivals and dear men</line>
<line>Of estimation and command in arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
<line>Doubt not, my lord, they shall be well opposed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I hope no less, yet needful 'tis to fear;</line>
<line>And, to prevent the worst, Sir Michael, speed:</line>
<line>For if Lord Percy thrive not, ere the king</line>
<line>Dismiss his power, he means to visit us,</line>
<line>For he hath heard of our confederacy,</line>
<line>And 'tis but wisdom to make strong against him:</line>
<line>Therefore make haste. I must go write again</line>
<line>To other friends; and so farewell, Sir Michael.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT V</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  KING HENRY IV's camp near Shrewsbury.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING HENRY, PRINCE HENRY, Lord John of
LANCASTER, EARL OF WESTMORELAND, SIR WALTER BLUNT,
and FALSTAFF</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>How bloodily the sun begins to peer</line>
<line>Above yon busky hill! the day looks pale</line>
<line>At his distemperature.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>The southern wind</line>
<line>Doth play the trumpet to his purposes,</line>
<line>And by his hollow whistling in the leaves</line>
<line>Foretells a tempest and a blustering day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Then with the losers let it sympathize,</line>
<line>For nothing can seem foul to those that win.</line>
<para role="stagedir">The trumpet sounds</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter WORCESTER and VERNON</para>
<line>How now, my Lord of Worcester! 'tis not well</line>
<line>That you and I should meet upon such terms</line>
<line>As now we meet. You have deceived our trust,</line>
<line>And made us doff our easy robes of peace,</line>
<line>To crush our old limbs in ungentle steel:</line>
<line>This is not well, my lord, this is not well.</line>
<line>What say you to it? will you again unknit</line>
<line>This curlish knot of all-abhorred war?</line>
<line>And move in that obedient orb again</line>
<line>Where you did give a fair and natural light,</line>
<line>And be no more an exhaled meteor,</line>
<line>A prodigy of fear and a portent</line>
<line>Of broached mischief to the unborn times?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Hear me, my liege:</line>
<line>For mine own part, I could be well content</line>
<line>To entertain the lag-end of my life</line>
<line>With quiet hours; for I do protest,</line>
<line>I have not sought the day of this dislike.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>You have not sought it! how comes it, then?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Rebellion lay in his way, and he found it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Peace, chewet, peace!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>It pleased your majesty to turn your looks</line>
<line>Of favour from myself and all our house;</line>
<line>And yet I must remember you, my lord,</line>
<line>We were the first and dearest of your friends.</line>
<line>For you my staff of office did I break</line>
<line>In Richard's time; and posted day and night</line>
<line>to meet you on the way, and kiss your hand,</line>
<line>When yet you were in place and in account</line>
<line>Nothing so strong and fortunate as I.</line>
<line>It was myself, my brother and his son,</line>
<line>That brought you home and boldly did outdare</line>
<line>The dangers of the time. You swore to us,</line>
<line>And you did swear that oath at Doncaster,</line>
<line>That you did nothing purpose 'gainst the state;</line>
<line>Nor claim no further than your new-fall'n right,</line>
<line>The seat of Gaunt, dukedom of Lancaster:</line>
<line>To this we swore our aid. But in short space</line>
<line>It rain'd down fortune showering on your head;</line>
<line>And such a flood of greatness fell on you,</line>
<line>What with our help, what with the absent king,</line>
<line>What with the injuries of a wanton time,</line>
<line>The seeming sufferances that you had borne,</line>
<line>And the contrarious winds that held the king</line>
<line>So long in his unlucky Irish wars</line>
<line>That all in England did repute him dead:</line>
<line>And from this swarm of fair advantages</line>
<line>You took occasion to be quickly woo'd</line>
<line>To gripe the general sway into your hand;</line>
<line>Forget your oath to us at Doncaster;</line>
<line>And being fed by us you used us so</line>
<line>As that ungentle hull, the cuckoo's bird,</line>
<line>Useth the sparrow; did oppress our nest;</line>
<line>Grew by our feeding to so great a bulk</line>
<line>That even our love durst not come near your sight</line>
<line>For fear of swallowing; but with nimble wing</line>
<line>We were enforced, for safety sake, to fly</line>
<line>Out of sight and raise this present head;</line>
<line>Whereby we stand opposed by such means</line>
<line>As you yourself have forged against yourself</line>
<line>By unkind usage, dangerous countenance,</line>
<line>And violation of all faith and troth</line>
<line>Sworn to us in your younger enterprise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>These things indeed you have articulate,</line>
<line>Proclaim'd at market-crosses, read in churches,</line>
<line>To face the garment of rebellion</line>
<line>With some fine colour that may please the eye</line>
<line>Of fickle changelings and poor discontents,</line>
<line>Which gape and rub the elbow at the news</line>
<line>Of hurlyburly innovation:</line>
<line>And never yet did insurrection want</line>
<line>Such water-colours to impaint his cause;</line>
<line>Nor moody beggars, starving for a time</line>
<line>Of pellmell havoc and confusion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>In both your armies there is many a soul</line>
<line>Shall pay full dearly for this encounter,</line>
<line>If once they join in trial. Tell your nephew,</line>
<line>The Prince of Wales doth join with all the world</line>
<line>In praise of Henry Percy: by my hopes,</line>
<line>This present enterprise set off his head,</line>
<line>I do not think a braver gentleman,</line>
<line>More active-valiant or more valiant-young,</line>
<line>More daring or more bold, is now alive</line>
<line>To grace this latter age with noble deeds.</line>
<line>For my part, I may speak it to my shame,</line>
<line>I have a truant been to chivalry;</line>
<line>And so I hear he doth account me too;</line>
<line>Yet this before my father's majesty--</line>
<line>I am content that he shall take the odds</line>
<line>Of his great name and estimation,</line>
<line>And will, to save the blood on either side,</line>
<line>Try fortune with him in a single fight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>And, Prince of Wales, so dare we venture thee,</line>
<line>Albeit considerations infinite</line>
<line>Do make against it. No, good Worcester, no,</line>
<line>We love our people well; even those we love</line>
<line>That are misled upon your cousin's part;</line>
<line>And, will they take the offer of our grace,</line>
<line>Both he and they and you, every man</line>
<line>Shall be my friend again and I'll be his:</line>
<line>So tell your cousin, and bring me word</line>
<line>What he will do: but if he will not yield,</line>
<line>Rebuke and dread correction wait on us</line>
<line>And they shall do their office. So, be gone;</line>
<line>We will not now be troubled with reply:</line>
<line>We offer fair; take it advisedly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt WORCESTER and VERNON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>It will not be accepted, on my life:</line>
<line>The Douglas and the Hotspur both together</line>
<line>Are confident against the world in arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Hence, therefore, every leader to his charge;</line>
<line>For, on their answer, will we set on them:</line>
<line>And God befriend us, as our cause is just!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all but PRINCE HENRY and FALSTAFF</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Hal, if thou see me down in the battle and bestride</line>
<line>me, so; 'tis a point of friendship.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Nothing but a colossus can do thee that friendship.</line>
<line>Say thy prayers, and farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I  would 'twere bed-time, Hal, and all well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, thou owest God a death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit PRINCE HENRY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>'Tis not due yet; I would be loath to pay him before</line>
<line>his day. What need I be so forward with him that</line>
<line>calls not on me? Well, 'tis no matter; honour pricks</line>
<line>me on. Yea, but how if honour prick me off when I</line>
<line>come on? how then? Can honour set to a leg? no: or</line>
<line>an arm? no: or take away the grief of a wound? no.</line>
<line>Honour hath no skill in surgery, then? no. What is</line>
<line>honour? a word. What is in that word honour? what</line>
<line>is that honour? air. A trim reckoning! Who hath it?</line>
<line>he that died o' Wednesday. Doth he feel it? no.</line>
<line>Doth he hear it? no. 'Tis insensible, then. Yea,</line>
<line>to the dead. But will it not live with the living?</line>
<line>no. Why? detraction will not suffer it. Therefore</line>
<line>I'll none of it. Honour is a mere scutcheon: and so</line>
<line>ends my catechism.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The rebel camp.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter WORCESTER and VERNON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>O, no, my nephew must not know, Sir Richard,</line>
<line>The liberal and kind offer of the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>'Twere best he did.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>Then are we all undone.</line>
<line>It is not possible, it cannot be,</line>
<line>The king should keep his word in loving us;</line>
<line>He will suspect us still and find a time</line>
<line>To punish this offence in other faults:</line>
<line>Suspicion all our lives shall be stuck full of eyes;</line>
<line>For treason is but trusted like the fox,</line>
<line>Who, ne'er so tame, so cherish'd and lock'd up,</line>
<line>Will have a wild trick of his ancestors.</line>
<line>Look how we can, or sad or merrily,</line>
<line>Interpretation will misquote our looks,</line>
<line>And we shall feed like oxen at a stall,</line>
<line>The better cherish'd, still the nearer death.</line>
<line>My nephew's trespass may be well forgot;</line>
<line>it hath the excuse of youth and heat of blood,</line>
<line>And an adopted name of privilege,</line>
<line>A hair-brain'd Hotspur, govern'd by a spleen:</line>
<line>All his offences live upon my head</line>
<line>And on his father's; we did train him on,</line>
<line>And, his corruption being ta'en from us,</line>
<line>We, as the spring of all, shall pay for all.</line>
<line>Therefore, good cousin, let not Harry know,</line>
<line>In any case, the offer of the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>Deliver what you will; I'll say 'tis so.</line>
<line>Here comes your cousin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HOTSPUR and DOUGLAS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>My uncle is return'd:</line>
<line>Deliver up my Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
<line>Uncle, what news?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>The king will bid you battle presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Defy him by the Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Lord Douglas, go you and tell him so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Marry, and shall, and very willingly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>There is no seeming mercy in the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Did you beg any? God forbid!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>I told him gently of our grievances,</line>
<line>Of his oath-breaking; which he mended thus,</line>
<line>By now forswearing that he is forsworn:</line>
<line>He calls us rebels, traitors; and will scourge</line>
<line>With haughty arms this hateful name in us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter the EARL OF DOUGLAS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Arm, gentlemen; to arms! for I have thrown</line>
<line>A brave defiance in King Henry's teeth,</line>
<line>And Westmoreland, that was engaged, did bear it;</line>
<line>Which cannot choose but bring him quickly on.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>The Prince of Wales stepp'd forth before the king,</line>
<line>And, nephew, challenged you to single fight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>O, would the quarrel lay upon our heads,</line>
<line>And that no man might draw short breath today</line>
<line>But I and Harry Monmouth! Tell me, tell me,</line>
<line>How show'd his tasking? seem'd it in contempt?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">VERNON</speaker>
<line>No, by my soul; I never in my life</line>
<line>Did hear a challenge urged more modestly,</line>
<line>Unless a brother should a brother dare</line>
<line>To gentle exercise and proof of arms.</line>
<line>He gave you all the duties of a man;</line>
<line>Trimm'd up your praises with a princely tongue,</line>
<line>Spoke to your deservings like a chronicle,</line>
<line>Making you ever better than his praise</line>
<line>By still dispraising praise valued in you;</line>
<line>And, which became him like a prince indeed,</line>
<line>He made a blushing cital of himself;</line>
<line>And chid his truant youth with such a grace</line>
<line>As if he master'd there a double spirit.</line>
<line>Of teaching and of learning instantly.</line>
<line>There did he pause: but let me tell the world,</line>
<line>If he outlive the envy of this day,</line>
<line>England did never owe so sweet a hope,</line>
<line>So much misconstrued in his wantonness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Cousin, I think thou art enamoured</line>
<line>On his follies: never did I hear</line>
<line>Of any prince so wild a libertine.</line>
<line>But be he as he will, yet once ere night</line>
<line>I will embrace him with a soldier's arm,</line>
<line>That he shall shrink under my courtesy.</line>
<line>Arm, arm with speed: and, fellows, soldiers, friends,</line>
<line>Better consider what you have to do</line>
<line>Than I, that have not well the gift of tongue,</line>
<line>Can lift your blood up with persuasion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Messenger</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>My lord, here are letters for you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I cannot read them now.</line>
<line>O gentlemen, the time of life is short!</line>
<line>To spend that shortness basely were too long,</line>
<line>If life did ride upon a dial's point,</line>
<line>Still ending at the arrival of an hour.</line>
<line>An if we live, we live to tread on kings;</line>
<line>If die, brave death, when princes die with us!</line>
<line>Now, for our consciences, the arms are fair,</line>
<line>When the intent of bearing them is just.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter another Messenger</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>My lord, prepare; the king comes on apace.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I thank him, that he cuts me from my tale,</line>
<line>For I profess not talking; only this--</line>
<line>Let each man do his best: and here draw I</line>
<line>A sword, whose temper I intend to stain</line>
<line>With the best blood that I can meet withal</line>
<line>In the adventure of this perilous day.</line>
<line>Now, Esperance! Percy! and set on.</line>
<line>Sound all the lofty instruments of war,</line>
<line>And by that music let us all embrace;</line>
<line>For, heaven to earth, some of us never shall</line>
<line>A second time do such a courtesy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The trumpets sound. They embrace, and exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Plain between the camps.</title>
<para role="stagedir">KING HENRY enters with his power. Alarum to the
battle. Then enter DOUGLAS and SIR WALTER BLUNT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>What is thy name, that in the battle thus</line>
<line>Thou crossest me? what honour dost thou seek</line>
<line>Upon my head?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Know then, my name is Douglas;</line>
<line>And I do haunt thee in the battle thus</line>
<line>Because some tell me that thou art a king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>They tell thee true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>The Lord of Stafford dear to-day hath bought</line>
<line>Thy likeness, for instead of thee, King Harry,</line>
<line>This sword hath ended him: so shall it thee,</line>
<line>Unless thou yield thee as my prisoner.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
<line>I was not born a yielder, thou proud Scot;</line>
<line>And thou shalt find a king that will revenge</line>
<line>Lord Stafford's death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They fight. DOUGLAS kills SIR WALTER BLUNT.
Enter HOTSPUR</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>O Douglas, hadst thou fought at Holmedon thus,</line>
<line>never had triumph'd upon a Scot.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>All's done, all's won; here breathless lies the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Where?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>This, Douglas? no: I know this face full well:</line>
<line>A gallant knight he was, his name was Blunt;</line>
<line>Semblably furnish'd like the king himself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>A fool go with thy soul, whither it goes!</line>
<line>A borrow'd title hast thou bought too dear:</line>
<line>Why didst thou tell me that thou wert a king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>The king hath many marching in his coats.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Now, by my sword, I will kill all his coats;</line>
<line>I'll murder all his wardrobe, piece by piece,</line>
<line>Until I meet the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Up, and away!</line>
<line>Our soldiers stand full fairly for the day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
<para role="stagedir">Alarum. Enter FALSTAFF, solus</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Though I could 'scape shot-free at London, I fear</line>
<line>the shot here; here's no scoring but upon the pate.</line>
<line>Soft! who are you? Sir Walter Blunt: there's honour</line>
<line>for you! here's no vanity! I am as hot as moulten</line>
<line>lead, and as heavy too: God keep lead out of me! I</line>
<line>need no more weight than mine own bowels. I have</line>
<line>led my ragamuffins where they are peppered: there's</line>
<line>not three of my hundred and fifty left alive; and</line>
<line>they are for the town's end, to beg during life.</line>
<line>But who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter PRINCE HENRY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, stand'st thou idle here? lend me thy sword:</line>
<line>Many a nobleman lies stark and stiff</line>
<line>Under the hoofs of vaunting enemies,</line>
<line>Whose deaths are yet unrevenged: I prithee,</line>
<line>lend me thy sword.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>O Hal, I prithee, give me leave to breathe awhile.</line>
<line>Turk Gregory never did such deeds in arms as I have</line>
<line>done this day. I have paid Percy, I have made him sure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>He is, indeed; and living to kill thee. I prithee,</line>
<line>lend me thy sword.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Nay, before God, Hal, if Percy be alive, thou get'st</line>
<line>not my sword; but take my pistol, if thou wilt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Give it to me: what, is it in the case?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Ay, Hal; 'tis hot, 'tis hot; there's that will sack a city.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">PRINCE HENRY draws it out, and finds it to be a
bottle of sack</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>What, is it a time to jest and dally now?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">He throws the bottle at him. Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well, if Percy be alive, I'll pierce him. If he do</line>
<line>come in my way, so: if he do not, if I come in his</line>
<line>willingly, let him make a carbonado of me. I like</line>
<line>not such grinning honour as Sir Walter hath: give me</line>
<line>life: which if I can save, so; if not, honour comes</line>
<line>unlooked for, and there's an end.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit FALSTAFF</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the field.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Alarum. Excursions. Enter PRINCE HENRY, LORD JOHN
OF LANCASTER, and EARL OF WESTMORELAND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>I prithee,</line>
<line>Harry, withdraw thyself; thou bleed'st too much.</line>
<line>Lord John of Lancaster, go you with him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LANCASTER</speaker>
<line>Not I, my lord, unless I did bleed too.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I beseech your majesty, make up,</line>
<line>Lest your retirement do amaze your friends.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>I will do so.</line>
<line>My Lord of Westmoreland, lead him to his tent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">WESTMORELAND</speaker>
<line>Come, my lord, I'll lead you to your tent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Lead me, my lord? I do not need your help:</line>
<line>And God forbid a shallow scratch should drive</line>
<line>The Prince of Wales from such a field as this,</line>
<line>Where stain'd nobility lies trodden on,</line>
<line>and rebels' arms triumph in massacres!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LANCASTER</speaker>
<line>We breathe too long: come, cousin Westmoreland,</line>
<line>Our duty this way lies; for God's sake come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt LANCASTER and WESTMORELAND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>By God, thou hast deceived me, Lancaster;</line>
<line>I did not think thee lord of such a spirit:</line>
<line>Before, I loved thee as a brother, John;</line>
<line>But now, I do respect thee as my soul.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>I saw him hold Lord Percy at the point</line>
<line>With lustier maintenance than I did look for</line>
<line>Of such an ungrown warrior.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O, this boy</line>
<line>Lends mettle to us all!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DOUGLAS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>Another king! they grow like Hydra's heads:</line>
<line>I am the Douglas, fatal to all those</line>
<line>That wear those colours on them: what art thou,</line>
<line>That counterfeit'st the person of a king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>The king himself; who, Douglas, grieves at heart</line>
<line>So many of his shadows thou hast met</line>
<line>And not the very king. I have two boys</line>
<line>Seek Percy and thyself about the field:</line>
<line>But, seeing thou fall'st on me so luckily,</line>
<line>I will assay thee: so, defend thyself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
<line>I fear thou art another counterfeit;</line>
<line>And yet, in faith, thou bear'st thee like a king:</line>
<line>But mine I am sure thou art, whoe'er thou be,</line>
<line>And thus I win thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They fight. KING HENRY being in danger, PRINCE
HENRY enters</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Hold up thy head, vile Scot, or thou art like</line>
<line>Never to hold it up again! the spirits</line>
<line>Of valiant Shirley, Stafford, Blunt, are in my arms:</line>
<line>It is the Prince of Wales that threatens thee;</line>
<line>Who never promiseth but he means to pay.</line>
<para role="stagedir">They fight: DOUGLAS flies</para>
<line>Cheerly, my lord how fares your grace?</line>
<line>Sir Nicholas Gawsey hath for succor sent,</line>
<line>And so hath Clifton: I'll to Clifton straight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Stay, and breathe awhile:</line>
<line>Thou hast redeem'd thy lost opinion,</line>
<line>And show'd thou makest some tender of my life,</line>
<line>In this fair rescue thou hast brought to me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>O God! they did me too much injury</line>
<line>That ever said I hearken'd for your death.</line>
<line>If it were so, I might have let alone</line>
<line>The insulting hand of Douglas over you,</line>
<line>Which would have been as speedy in your end</line>
<line>As all the poisonous potions in the world</line>
<line>And saved the treacherous labour of your son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Make up to Clifton: I'll to Sir Nicholas Gawsey.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HOTSPUR</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>If I mistake not, thou art Harry Monmouth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Thou speak'st as if I would deny my name.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>My name is Harry Percy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, then I see</line>
<line>A very valiant rebel of the name.</line>
<line>I am the Prince of Wales; and think not, Percy,</line>
<line>To share with me in glory any more:</line>
<line>Two stars keep not their motion in one sphere;</line>
<line>Nor can one England brook a double reign,</line>
<line>Of Harry Percy and the Prince of Wales.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>Nor shall it, Harry; for the hour is come</line>
<line>To end the one of us; and would to God</line>
<line>Thy name in arms were now as great as mine!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I'll make it greater ere I part from thee;</line>
<line>And all the budding honours on thy crest</line>
<line>I'll crop, to make a garland for my head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>I can no longer brook thy vanities.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They fight</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter FALSTAFF</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Well said, Hal! to it Hal! Nay, you shall find no</line>
<line>boy's play here, I can tell you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter DOUGLAS; he fights with FALSTAFF,
who falls down as if he were dead, and exit
DOUGLAS. HOTSPUR is wounded, and falls</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HOTSPUR</speaker>
<line>O, Harry, thou hast robb'd me of my youth!</line>
<line>I better brook the loss of brittle life</line>
<line>Than those proud titles thou hast won of me;</line>
<line>They wound my thoughts worse than sword my flesh:</line>
<line>But thought's the slave of life, and life time's fool;</line>
<line>And time, that takes survey of all the world,</line>
<line>Must have a stop. O, I could prophesy,</line>
<line>But that the earthy and cold hand of death</line>
<line>Lies on my tongue: no, Percy, thou art dust</line>
<line>And food for--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Dies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>For worms, brave Percy: fare thee well, great heart!</line>
<line>Ill-weaved ambition, how much art thou shrunk!</line>
<line>When that this body did contain a spirit,</line>
<line>A kingdom for it was too small a bound;</line>
<line>But now two paces of the vilest earth</line>
<line>Is room enough: this earth that bears thee dead</line>
<line>Bears not alive so stout a gentleman.</line>
<line>If thou wert sensible of courtesy,</line>
<line>I should not make so dear a show of zeal:</line>
<line>But let my favours hide thy mangled face;</line>
<line>And, even in thy behalf, I'll thank myself</line>
<line>For doing these fair rites of tenderness.</line>
<line>Adieu, and take thy praise with thee to heaven!</line>
<line>Thy ignominy sleep with thee in the grave,</line>
<line>But not remember'd in thy epitaph!</line>
<para role="stagedir">He spieth FALSTAFF on the ground</para>
<line>What, old acquaintance! could not all this flesh</line>
<line>Keep in a little life? Poor Jack, farewell!</line>
<line>I could have better spared a better man:</line>
<line>O, I should have a heavy miss of thee,</line>
<line>If I were much in love with vanity!</line>
<line>Death hath not struck so fat a deer to-day,</line>
<line>Though many dearer, in this bloody fray.</line>
<line>Embowell'd will I see thee by and by:</line>
<line>Till then in blood by noble Percy lie.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit PRINCE HENRY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Rising up</phrase>  Embowelled! if thou embowel me to-day,</line>
<line>I'll give you leave to powder me and eat me too</line>
<line>to-morrow. 'Sblood,'twas time to counterfeit, or</line>
<line>that hot termagant Scot had paid me scot and lot too.</line>
<line>Counterfeit? I lie, I am no counterfeit: to die,</line>
<line>is to be a counterfeit; for he is but the</line>
<line>counterfeit of a man who hath not the life of a man:</line>
<line>but to counterfeit dying, when a man thereby</line>
<line>liveth, is to be no counterfeit, but the true and</line>
<line>perfect image of life indeed. The better part of</line>
<line>valour is discretion; in the which better part I</line>
<line>have saved my life.'Zounds, I am afraid of this</line>
<line>gunpowder Percy, though he be dead: how, if he</line>
<line>should counterfeit too and rise? by my faith, I am</line>
<line>afraid he would prove the better counterfeit.</line>
<line>Therefore I'll make him sure; yea, and I'll swear I</line>
<line>killed him. Why may not he rise as well as I?</line>
<line>Nothing confutes me but eyes, and nobody sees me.</line>
<line>Therefore, sirrah,</line>
<para role="stagedir">Stabbing him</para>
<line>with a new wound in your thigh, come you along with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Takes up HOTSPUR on his back</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter PRINCE HENRY and LORD JOHN OF LANCASTER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Come, brother John; full bravely hast thou flesh'd</line>
<line>Thy maiden sword.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LANCASTER</speaker>
<line>But, soft! whom have we here?</line>
<line>Did you not tell me this fat man was dead?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>I did; I saw him dead,</line>
<line>Breathless and bleeding on the ground. Art</line>
<line>thou alive?</line>
<line>Or is it fantasy that plays upon our eyesight?</line>
<line>I prithee, speak; we will not trust our eyes</line>
<line>Without our ears: thou art not what thou seem'st.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>No, that's certain; I am not a double man: but if I</line>
<line>be not Jack Falstaff, then am I a Jack. There is Percy:</line>
<para role="stagedir">Throwing the body down</para>
<line>if your father will do me any honour, so; if not, let</line>
<line>him kill the next Percy himself. I look to be either</line>
<line>earl or duke, I can assure you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Why, Percy I killed myself and saw thee dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>Didst thou? Lord, Lord, how this world is given to</line>
<line>lying! I grant you I was down and out of breath;</line>
<line>and so was he: but we rose both at an instant and</line>
<line>fought a long hour by Shrewsbury clock. If I may be</line>
<line>believed, so; if not, let them that should reward</line>
<line>valour bear the sin upon their own heads. I'll take</line>
<line>it upon my death, I gave him this wound in the</line>
<line>thigh: if the man were alive and would deny it,</line>
<line>'zounds, I would make him eat a piece of my sword.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LANCASTER</speaker>
<line>This is the strangest tale that ever I heard.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>This is the strangest fellow, brother John.</line>
<line>Come, bring your luggage nobly on your back:</line>
<line>For my part, if a lie may do thee grace,</line>
<line>I'll gild it with the happiest terms I have.</line>
<para role="stagedir">A retreat is sounded</para>
<line>The trumpet sounds retreat; the day is ours.</line>
<line>Come, brother, let us to the highest of the field,</line>
<line>To see what friends are living, who are dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt PRINCE HENRY and LANCASTER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">FALSTAFF</speaker>
<line>I'll follow, as they say, for reward. He that</line>
<line>rewards me, God reward him! If I do grow great,</line>
<line>I'll grow less; for I'll purge, and leave sack, and</line>
<line>live cleanly as a nobleman should do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE V.  Another part of the field.</title>
<para role="stagedir">The trumpets sound. Enter KING HENRY IV, PRINCE
HENRY, LORD JOHN LANCASTER, EARL OF WESTMORELAND,
with WORCESTER and VERNON prisoners</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Thus ever did rebellion find rebuke.</line>
<line>Ill-spirited Worcester! did not we send grace,</line>
<line>Pardon and terms of love to all of you?</line>
<line>And wouldst thou turn our offers contrary?</line>
<line>Misuse the tenor of thy kinsman's trust?</line>
<line>Three knights upon our party slain to-day,</line>
<line>A noble earl and many a creature else</line>
<line>Had been alive this hour,</line>
<line>If like a Christian thou hadst truly borne</line>
<line>Betwixt our armies true intelligence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
<line>What I have done my safety urged me to;</line>
<line>And I embrace this fortune patiently,</line>
<line>Since not to be avoided it falls on me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Bear Worcester to the death and Vernon too:</line>
<line>Other offenders we will pause upon.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt WORCESTER and VERNON, guarded</para>
<line>How goes the field?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>The noble Scot, Lord Douglas, when he saw</line>
<line>The fortune of the day quite turn'd from him,</line>
<line>The noble Percy slain, and all his men</line>
<line>Upon the foot of fear, fled with the rest;</line>
<line>And falling from a hill, he was so bruised</line>
<line>That the pursuers took him. At my tent</line>
<line>The Douglas is; and I beseech your grace</line>
<line>I may dispose of him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>With all my heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
<line>Then, brother John of Lancaster, to you</line>
<line>This honourable bounty shall belong:</line>
<line>Go to the Douglas, and deliver him</line>
<line>Up to his pleasure, ransomless and free:</line>
<line>His valour shown upon our crests to-day</line>
<line>Hath taught us how to cherish such high deeds</line>
<line>Even in the bosom of our adversaries.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LANCASTER</speaker>
<line>I thank your grace for this high courtesy,</line>
<line>Which I shall give away immediately.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING HENRY IV</speaker>
<line>Then this remains, that we divide our power.</line>
<line>You, son John, and my cousin Westmoreland</line>
<line>Towards York shall bend you with your dearest speed,</line>
<line>To meet Northumberland and the prelate Scroop,</line>
<line>Who, as we hear, are busily in arms:</line>
<line>Myself and you, son Harry, will towards Wales,</line>
<line>To fight with Glendower and the Earl of March.</line>
<line>Rebellion in this land shall lose his sway,</line>
<line>Meeting the cheque of such another day:</line>
<line>And since this business so fair is done,</line>
<line>Let us not leave till all our own be won.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>