<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="publishers.rnc" type="compact"?><book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" role="play">
<title>Pericles, Prince of Tyre</title>

<info><author><personname><firstname>William</firstname><surname>Shakespeare</surname></personname></author><legalnotice>
<para>ASCII text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</para>
<para>SGML markup by Jon Bosak, 1992-1994.</para>
<para>XML version by Jon Bosak, 1996-1999.</para>
<para>The XML markup in this version is Copyright © 1999 Jon Bosak.
This work may freely be distributed on condition that it not be
modified or altered in any way.</para>
</legalnotice>     <copyright><year>2008</year><holder>Scott Hudson</holder></copyright></info>

<preface>
<title>Dramatis Personae</title>

<para><personname role="persona">ANTIOCHUS, king of Antioch.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">PERICLES, prince of Tyre.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">HELICANUS</personname><personname role="persona">ESCANES</personname></member><member>two lords of Tyre.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">SIMONIDES, king of Pentapolis.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">CLEON, governor of Tarsus.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LYSIMACHUS, governor of Mytilene.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">CERIMON, a lord of Ephesus.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">THALIARD, a lord of Antioch.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">PHILEMON, servant to Cerimon.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LEONINE, servant to Dionyza.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Marshal. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">A Pandar. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">BOULT, his servant.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">The Daughter of Antiochus. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DIONYZA, wife to Cleon.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">THAISA, daughter to Simonides.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">MARINA, daughter to Pericles and Thaisa.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LYCHORIDA, nurse to Marina.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">A Bawd. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, Sailors, Pirates, Fishermen, and Messengers. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DIANA</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">GOWER, as Chorus.</personname></para>
    
    <para role="scndescr">SCENE  Dispersedly in various countries.</para>
</preface>



<chapter role="act"><title>ACT I</title>

<section role="prologue"><title>[Prologue]</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER</para>
<para role="stagedir">Before the palace of Antioch</para>
<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup><speaker role="speaker">[GOWER]</speaker>
<line>To sing a song that old was sung,</line>
<line>From ashes ancient Gower is come;</line>
<line>Assuming man's infirmities,</line>
<line>To glad your ear, and please your eyes.</line>
<line>It hath been sung at festivals,</line>
<line>On ember-eves and holy-ales;</line>
<line>And lords and ladies in their lives</line>
<line>Have read it for restoratives:</line>
<line>The purchase is to make men glorious;</line>
<line>Et bonum quo antiquius, eo melius.</line>
<line>If you, born in these latter times,</line>
<line>When wit's more ripe, accept my rhymes.</line>
<line>And that to hear an old man sing</line>
<line>May to your wishes pleasure bring</line>
<line>I life would wish, and that I might</line>
<line>Waste it for you, like taper-light.</line>
<line>This Antioch, then, Antiochus the Great</line>
<line>Built up, this city, for his chiefest seat:</line>
<line>The fairest in all Syria,</line>
<line>I tell you what mine authors say:</line>
<line>This king unto him took a fere,</line>
<line>Who died and left a female heir,</line>
<line>So buxom, blithe, and full of face,</line>
<line>As heaven had lent her all his grace;</line>
<line>With whom the father liking took,</line>
<line>And her to incest did provoke:</line>
<line>Bad child; worse father! to entice his own</line>
<line>To evil should be done by none:</line>
<line>But custom what they did begin</line>
<line>Was with long use account no sin.</line>
<line>The beauty of this sinful dame</line>
<line>Made many princes thither frame,</line>
<line>To seek her as a bed-fellow,</line>
<line>In marriage-pleasures play-fellow:</line>
<line>Which to prevent he made a law,</line>
<line>To keep her still, and men in awe,</line>
<line>That whoso ask'd her for his wife,</line>
<line>His riddle told not, lost his life:</line>
<line>So for her many a wight did die,</line>
<line>As yon grim looks do testify.</line>
<line>What now ensues, to the judgment of your eye</line>
<line>I give, my cause who best can justify.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Antioch. A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter ANTIOCHUS, Prince PERICLES, and followers</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Young prince of Tyre, you have at large received</line>
<line>The danger of the task you undertake.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I have, Antiochus, and, with a soul</line>
<line>Embolden'd with the glory of her praise,</line>
<line>Think death no hazard in this enterprise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Bring in our daughter, clothed like a bride,</line>
<line>For the embracements even of Jove himself;</line>
<line>At whose conception, till Lucina reign'd,</line>
<line>Nature this dowry gave, to glad her presence,</line>
<line>The senate-house of planets all did sit,</line>
<line>To knit in her their best perfections.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Music. Enter the Daughter of ANTIOCHUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>See where she comes, apparell'd like the spring,</line>
<line>Graces her subjects, and her thoughts the king</line>
<line>Of every virtue gives renown to men!</line>
<line>Her face the book of praises, where is read</line>
<line>Nothing but curious pleasures, as from thence</line>
<line>Sorrow were ever razed and testy wrath</line>
<line>Could never be her mild companion.</line>
<line>You gods that made me man, and sway in love,</line>
<line>That have inflamed desire in my breast</line>
<line>To taste the fruit of yon celestial tree,</line>
<line>Or die in the adventure, be my helps,</line>
<line>As I am son and servant to your will,</line>
<line>To compass such a boundless happiness!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Prince Pericles,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>That would be son to great Antiochus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Before thee stands this fair Hesperides,</line>
<line>With golden fruit, but dangerous to be touch'd;</line>
<line>For death-like dragons here affright thee hard:</line>
<line>Her face, like heaven, enticeth thee to view</line>
<line>Her countless glory, which desert must gain;</line>
<line>And which, without desert, because thine eye</line>
<line>Presumes to reach, all thy whole heap must die.</line>
<line>Yon sometimes famous princes, like thyself,</line>
<line>Drawn by report, adventurous by desire,</line>
<line>Tell thee, with speechless tongues and semblance pale,</line>
<line>That without covering, save yon field of stars,</line>
<line>Here they stand martyrs, slain in Cupid's wars;</line>
<line>And with dead cheeks advise thee to desist</line>
<line>For going on death's net, whom none resist.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Antiochus, I thank thee, who hath taught</line>
<line>My frail mortality to know itself,</line>
<line>And by those fearful objects to prepare</line>
<line>This body, like to them, to what I must;</line>
<line>For death remember'd should be like a mirror,</line>
<line>Who tells us life's but breath, to trust it error.</line>
<line>I'll make my will then, and, as sick men do</line>
<line>Who know the world, see heaven, but, feeling woe,</line>
<line>Gripe not at earthly joys as erst they did;</line>
<line>So I bequeath a happy peace to you</line>
<line>And all good men, as every prince should do;</line>
<line>My riches to the earth from whence they came;</line>
<line>But my unspotted fire of love to you.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To the Daughter of ANTIOCHUS</para>
<line>Thus ready for the way of life or death,</line>
<line>I wait the sharpest blow, Antiochus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Scorning advice, read the conclusion then:</line>
<line>Which read and not expounded, 'tis decreed,</line>
<line>As these before thee thou thyself shalt bleed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Daughter</speaker>
<line>Of all say'd yet, mayst thou prove prosperous!</line>
<line>Of all say'd yet, I wish thee happiness!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Like a bold champion, I assume the lists,</line>
<line>Nor ask advice of any other thought</line>
<line>But faithfulness and courage.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He reads the riddle</para>
<line>I am no viper, yet I feed</line>
<line>On mother's flesh which did me breed.</line>
<line>I sought a husband, in which labour</line>
<line>I found that kindness in a father:</line>
<line>He's father, son, and husband mild;</line>
<line>I mother, wife, and yet his child.</line>
<line>How they may be, and yet in two,</line>
<line>As you will live, resolve it you.</line>
<line>Sharp physic is the last: but, O you powers</line>
<line>That give heaven countless eyes to view men's acts,</line>
<line>Why cloud they not their sights perpetually,</line>
<line>If this be true, which makes me pale to read it?</line>
<line>Fair glass of light, I loved you, and could still,</line>
<para role="stagedir">Takes hold of the hand of the Daughter of ANTIOCHUS</para>
<line>Were not this glorious casket stored with ill:</line>
<line>But I must tell you, now my thoughts revolt</line>
<line>For he's no man on whom perfections wait</line>
<line>That, knowing sin within, will touch the gate.</line>
<line>You are a fair viol, and your sense the strings;</line>
<line>Who, finger'd to make man his lawful music,</line>
<line>Would draw heaven down, and all the gods, to hearken:</line>
<line>But being play'd upon before your time,</line>
<line>Hell only danceth at so harsh a chime.</line>
<line>Good sooth, I care not for you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Prince Pericles, touch not, upon thy life.</line>
<line>For that's an article within our law,</line>
<line>As dangerous as the rest. Your time's expired:</line>
<line>Either expound now, or receive your sentence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Great king,</line>
<line>Few love to hear the sins they love to act;</line>
<line>'Twould braid yourself too near for me to tell it.</line>
<line>Who has a book of all that monarchs do,</line>
<line>He's more secure to keep it shut than shown:</line>
<line>For vice repeated is like the wandering wind.</line>
<line>Blows dust in other's eyes, to spread itself;</line>
<line>And yet the end of all is bought thus dear,</line>
<line>The breath is gone, and the sore eyes see clear:</line>
<line>To stop the air would hurt them. The blind mole casts</line>
<line>Copp'd hills towards heaven, to tell the earth is throng'd</line>
<line>By man's oppression; and the poor worm doth die for't.</line>
<line>Kings are earth's gods; in vice their law's</line>
<line>their will;</line>
<line>And if Jove stray, who dares say Jove doth ill?</line>
<line>It is enough you know; and it is fit,</line>
<line>What being more known grows worse, to smother it.</line>
<line>All love the womb that their first being bred,</line>
<line>Then give my tongue like leave to love my head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Heaven, that I had thy head! he has found</line>
<line>the meaning:</line>
<line>But I will gloze with him.--Young prince of Tyre,</line>
<line>Though by the tenor of our strict edict,</line>
<line>Your exposition misinterpreting,</line>
<line>We might proceed to cancel of your days;</line>
<line>Yet hope, succeeding from so fair a tree</line>
<line>As your fair self, doth tune us otherwise:</line>
<line>Forty days longer we do respite you;</line>
<line>If by which time our secret be undone,</line>
<line>This mercy shows we'll joy in such a son:</line>
<line>And until then your entertain shall be</line>
<line>As doth befit our honour and your worth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all but PERICLES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>How courtesy would seem to cover sin,</line>
<line>When what is done is like an hypocrite,</line>
<line>The which is good in nothing but in sight!</line>
<line>If it be true that I interpret false,</line>
<line>Then were it certain you were not so bad</line>
<line>As with foul incest to abuse your soul;</line>
<line>Where now you're both a father and a son,</line>
<line>By your untimely claspings with your child,</line>
<line>Which pleasure fits an husband, not a father;</line>
<line>And she an eater of her mother's flesh,</line>
<line>By the defiling of her parent's bed;</line>
<line>And both like serpents are, who though they feed</line>
<line>On sweetest flowers, yet they poison breed.</line>
<line>Antioch, farewell! for wisdom sees, those men</line>
<line>Blush not in actions blacker than the night,</line>
<line>Will shun no course to keep them from the light.</line>
<line>One sin, I know, another doth provoke;</line>
<line>Murder's as near to lust as flame to smoke:</line>
<line>Poison and treason are the hands of sin,</line>
<line>Ay, and the targets, to put off the shame:</line>
<line>Then, lest my lie be cropp'd to keep you clear,</line>
<line>By flight I'll shun the danger which I fear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter ANTIOCHUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>He hath found the meaning, for which we mean</line>
<line>To have his head.</line>
<line>He must not live to trumpet forth my infamy,</line>
<line>Nor tell the world Antiochus doth sin</line>
<line>In such a loathed manner;</line>
<line>And therefore instantly this prince must die:</line>
<line>For by his fall my honour must keep high.</line>
<line>Who attends us there?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter THALIARD</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line>Doth your highness call?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Thaliard,</line>
<line>You are of our chamber, and our mind partakes</line>
<line>Her private actions to your secrecy;</line>
<line>And for your faithfulness we will advance you.</line>
<line>Thaliard, behold, here's poison, and here's gold;</line>
<line>We hate the prince of Tyre, and thou must kill him:</line>
<line>It fits thee not to ask the reason why,</line>
<line>Because we bid it. Say, is it done?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line>My lord,</line>
<line>'Tis done.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Enough.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Messenger</para>
<line>Let your breath cool yourself, telling your haste.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>My lord, prince Pericles is fled.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>As thou</line>
<line>Wilt live, fly after: and like an arrow shot</line>
<line>From a well-experienced archer hits the mark</line>
<line>His eye doth level at, so thou ne'er return</line>
<line>Unless thou say 'Prince Pericles is dead.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line>My lord,</line>
<line>If I can get him within my pistol's length,</line>
<line>I'll make him sure enough: so, farewell to your highness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ANTIOCHUS</speaker>
<line>Thaliard, adieu!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit THALIARD</para>
<line>Till Pericles be dead,</line>
<line>My heart can lend no succor to my head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  Tyre. A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To Lords without</phrase>  Let none disturb us.--Why should</line>
<line>this change of thoughts,</line>
<line>The sad companion, dull-eyed melancholy,</line>
<line>Be my so used a guest as not an hour,</line>
<line>In the day's glorious walk, or peaceful night,</line>
<line>The tomb where grief should sleep, can breed me quiet?</line>
<line>Here pleasures court mine eyes, and mine eyes shun them,</line>
<line>And danger, which I fear'd, is at Antioch,</line>
<line>Whose aim seems far too short to hit me here:</line>
<line>Yet neither pleasure's art can joy my spirits,</line>
<line>Nor yet the other's distance comfort me.</line>
<line>Then it is thus: the passions of the mind,</line>
<line>That have their first conception by mis-dread,</line>
<line>Have after-nourishment and life by care;</line>
<line>And what was first but fear what might be done,</line>
<line>Grows elder now and cares it be not done.</line>
<line>And so with me: the great Antiochus,</line>
<line>'Gainst whom I am too little to contend,</line>
<line>Since he's so great can make his will his act,</line>
<line>Will think me speaking, though I swear to silence;</line>
<line>Nor boots it me to say I honour him.</line>
<line>If he suspect I may dishonour him:</line>
<line>And what may make him blush in being known,</line>
<line>He'll stop the course by which it might be known;</line>
<line>With hostile forces he'll o'erspread the land,</line>
<line>And with the ostent of war will look so huge,</line>
<line>Amazement shall drive courage from the state;</line>
<line>Our men be vanquish'd ere they do resist,</line>
<line>And subjects punish'd that ne'er thought offence:</line>
<line>Which care of them, not pity of myself,</line>
<line>Who am no more but as the tops of trees,</line>
<line>Which fence the roots they grow by and defend them,</line>
<line>Makes both my body pine and soul to languish,</line>
<line>And punish that before that he would punish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HELICANUS, with other Lords</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>Joy and all comfort in your sacred breast!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Lord</speaker>
<line>And keep your mind, till you return to us,</line>
<line>Peaceful and comfortable!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Peace, peace, and give experience tongue.</line>
<line>They do abuse the king that flatter him:</line>
<line>For flattery is the bellows blows up sin;</line>
<line>The thing which is flatter'd, but a spark,</line>
<line>To which that blast gives heat and stronger glowing;</line>
<line>Whereas reproof, obedient and in order,</line>
<line>Fits kings, as they are men, for they may err.</line>
<line>When Signior Sooth here does proclaim a peace,</line>
<line>He flatters you, makes war upon your life.</line>
<line>Prince, pardon me, or strike me, if you please;</line>
<line>I cannot be much lower than my knees.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>All leave us else; but let your cares o'erlook</line>
<line>What shipping and what lading's in our haven,</line>
<line>And then return to us.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Lords</para>
<line>Helicanus, thou</line>
<line>Hast moved us: what seest thou in our looks?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>An angry brow, dread lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>If there be such a dart in princes' frowns,</line>
<line>How durst thy tongue move anger to our face?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>How dare the plants look up to heaven, from whence</line>
<line>They have their nourishment?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Thou know'st I have power</line>
<line>To take thy life from thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Kneeling</phrase></line>
<line>I have ground the axe myself;</line>
<line>Do you but strike the blow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Rise, prithee, rise.</line>
<line>Sit down: thou art no flatterer:</line>
<line>I thank thee for it; and heaven forbid</line>
<line>That kings should let their ears hear their</line>
<line>faults hid!</line>
<line>Fit counsellor and servant for a prince,</line>
<line>Who by thy wisdom makest a prince thy servant,</line>
<line>What wouldst thou have me do?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>To bear with patience</line>
<line>Such griefs as you yourself do lay upon yourself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Thou speak'st like a physician, Helicanus,</line>
<line>That minister'st a potion unto me</line>
<line>That thou wouldst tremble to receive thyself.</line>
<line>Attend me, then: I went to Antioch,</line>
<line>Where as thou know'st, against the face of death,</line>
<line>I sought the purchase of a glorious beauty.</line>
<line>From whence an issue I might propagate,</line>
<line>Are arms to princes, and bring joys to subjects.</line>
<line>Her face was to mine eye beyond all wonder;</line>
<line>The rest--hark in thine ear--as black as incest:</line>
<line>Which by my knowledge found, the sinful father</line>
<line>Seem'd not to strike, but smooth: but thou</line>
<line>know'st this,</line>
<line>'Tis time to fear when tyrants seem to kiss.</line>
<line>Such fear so grew in me, I hither fled,</line>
<line>Under the covering of a careful night,</line>
<line>Who seem'd my good protector; and, being here,</line>
<line>Bethought me what was past, what might succeed.</line>
<line>I knew him tyrannous; and tyrants' fears</line>
<line>Decrease not, but grow faster than the years:</line>
<line>And should he doubt it, as no doubt he doth,</line>
<line>That I should open to the listening air</line>
<line>How many worthy princes' bloods were shed,</line>
<line>To keep his bed of blackness unlaid ope,</line>
<line>To lop that doubt, he'll fill this land with arms,</line>
<line>And make pretence of wrong that I have done him:</line>
<line>When all, for mine, if I may call offence,</line>
<line>Must feel war's blow, who spares not innocence:</line>
<line>Which love to all, of which thyself art one,</line>
<line>Who now reprovest me for it,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Alas, sir!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Drew sleep out of mine eyes, blood from my cheeks,</line>
<line>Musings into my mind, with thousand doubts</line>
<line>How I might stop this tempest ere it came;</line>
<line>And finding little comfort to relieve them,</line>
<line>I thought it princely charity to grieve them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Well, my lord, since you have given me leave to speak.</line>
<line>Freely will I speak. Antiochus you fear,</line>
<line>And justly too, I think, you fear the tyrant,</line>
<line>Who either by public war or private treason</line>
<line>Will take away your life.</line>
<line>Therefore, my lord, go travel for a while,</line>
<line>Till that his rage and anger be forgot,</line>
<line>Or till the Destinies do cut his thread of life.</line>
<line>Your rule direct to any; if to me.</line>
<line>Day serves not light more faithful than I'll be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I do not doubt thy faith;</line>
<line>But should he wrong my liberties in my absence?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>We'll mingle our bloods together in the earth,</line>
<line>From whence we had our being and our birth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Tyre, I now look from thee then, and to Tarsus</line>
<line>Intend my travel, where I'll hear from thee;</line>
<line>And by whose letters I'll dispose myself.</line>
<line>The care I had and have of subjects' good</line>
<line>On thee I lay whose wisdom's strength can bear it.</line>
<line>I'll take thy word for faith, not ask thine oath:</line>
<line>Who shuns not to break one will sure crack both:</line>
<line>But in our orbs we'll live so round and safe,</line>
<line>That time of both this truth shall ne'er convince,</line>
<line>Thou show'dst a subject's shine, I a true prince.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Tyre. An ante-chamber in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter THALIARD</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line>So, this is Tyre, and this the court. Here must I</line>
<line>kill King Pericles; and if I do it not, I am sure to</line>
<line>be hanged at home: 'tis dangerous. Well, I perceive</line>
<line>he was a wise fellow, and had good discretion, that,</line>
<line>being bid to ask what he would of the king, desired</line>
<line>he might know none of his secrets: now do I see he</line>
<line>had some reason for't; for if a king bid a man be a</line>
<line>villain, he's bound by the indenture of his oath to</line>
<line>be one! Hush! here come the lords of Tyre.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HELICANUS and ESCANES, with other Lords of Tyre</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>You shall not need, my fellow peers of Tyre,</line>
<line>Further to question me of your king's departure:</line>
<line>His seal'd commission, left in trust with me,</line>
<line>Doth speak sufficiently he's gone to travel.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  How! the king gone!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>If further yet you will be satisfied,</line>
<line>Why, as it were unlicensed of your loves,</line>
<line>He would depart, I'll give some light unto you.</line>
<line>Being at Antioch--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>          What from Antioch?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Royal Antiochus--on what cause I know not--</line>
<line>Took some displeasure at him; at least he judged so:</line>
<line>And doubting lest that he had err'd or sinn'd,</line>
<line>To show his sorrow, he'ld correct himself;</line>
<line>So puts himself unto the shipman's toil,</line>
<line>With whom each minute threatens life or death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Well, I perceive</line>
<line>I shall not be hang'd now, although I would;</line>
<line>But since he's gone, the king's seas must please:</line>
<line>He 'scaped the land, to perish at the sea.</line>
<line>I'll present myself. Peace to the lords of Tyre!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Lord Thaliard from Antiochus is welcome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THALIARD</speaker>
<line>From him I come</line>
<line>With message unto princely Pericles;</line>
<line>But since my landing I have understood</line>
<line>Your lord has betook himself to unknown travels,</line>
<line>My message must return from whence it came.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>We have no reason to desire it,</line>
<line>Commended to our master, not to us:</line>
<line>Yet, ere you shall depart, this we desire,</line>
<line>As friends to Antioch, we may feast in Tyre.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  Tarsus. A room in the Governor's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CLEON, the governor of Tarsus, with DIONYZA,
and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>My Dionyza, shall we rest us here,</line>
<line>And by relating tales of others' griefs,</line>
<line>See if 'twill teach us to forget our own?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>That were to blow at fire in hope to quench it;</line>
<line>For who digs hills because they do aspire</line>
<line>Throws down one mountain to cast up a higher.</line>
<line>O my distressed lord, even such our griefs are;</line>
<line>Here they're but felt, and seen with mischief's eyes,</line>
<line>But like to groves, being topp'd, they higher rise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>O Dionyza,</line>
<line>Who wanteth food, and will not say he wants it,</line>
<line>Or can conceal his hunger till he famish?</line>
<line>Our tongues and sorrows do sound deep</line>
<line>Our woes into the air; our eyes do weep,</line>
<line>Till tongues fetch breath that may proclaim them louder;</line>
<line>That, if heaven slumber while their creatures want,</line>
<line>They may awake their helps to comfort them.</line>
<line>I'll then discourse our woes, felt several years,</line>
<line>And wanting breath to speak help me with tears.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>I'll do my best, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>This Tarsus, o'er which I have the government,</line>
<line>A city on whom plenty held full hand,</line>
<line>For riches strew'd herself even in the streets;</line>
<line>Whose towers bore heads so high they kiss'd the clouds,</line>
<line>And strangers ne'er beheld but wondered at;</line>
<line>Whose men and dames so jetted and adorn'd,</line>
<line>Like one another's glass to trim them by:</line>
<line>Their tables were stored full, to glad the sight,</line>
<line>And not so much to feed on as delight;</line>
<line>All poverty was scorn'd, and pride so great,</line>
<line>The name of help grew odious to repeat.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>O, 'tis too true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>But see what heaven can do! By this our change,</line>
<line>These mouths, who but of late, earth, sea, and air,</line>
<line>Were all too little to content and please,</line>
<line>Although they gave their creatures in abundance,</line>
<line>As houses are defiled for want of use,</line>
<line>They are now starved for want of exercise:</line>
<line>Those palates who, not yet two summers younger,</line>
<line>Must have inventions to delight the taste,</line>
<line>Would now be glad of bread, and beg for it:</line>
<line>Those mothers who, to nousle up their babes,</line>
<line>Thought nought too curious, are ready now</line>
<line>To eat those little darlings whom they loved.</line>
<line>So sharp are hunger's teeth, that man and wife</line>
<line>Draw lots who first shall die to lengthen life:</line>
<line>Here stands a lord, and there a lady weeping;</line>
<line>Here many sink, yet those which see them fall</line>
<line>Have scarce strength left to give them burial.</line>
<line>Is not this true?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Our cheeks and hollow eyes do witness it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>O, let those cities that of plenty's cup</line>
<line>And her prosperities so largely taste,</line>
<line>With their superfluous riots, hear these tears!</line>
<line>The misery of Tarsus may be theirs.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Lord</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord</speaker>
<line>Where's the lord governor?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Here.</line>
<line>Speak out thy sorrows which thou bring'st in haste,</line>
<line>For comfort is too far for us to expect.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord</speaker>
<line>We have descried, upon our neighbouring shore,</line>
<line>A portly sail of ships make hitherward.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>I thought as much.</line>
<line>One sorrow never comes but brings an heir,</line>
<line>That may succeed as his inheritor;</line>
<line>And so in ours: some neighbouring nation,</line>
<line>Taking advantage of our misery,</line>
<line>Hath stuff'd these hollow vessels with their power,</line>
<line>To beat us down, the which are down already;</line>
<line>And make a conquest of unhappy me,</line>
<line>Whereas no glory's got to overcome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord</speaker>
<line>That's the least fear; for, by the semblance</line>
<line>Of their white flags display'd, they bring us peace,</line>
<line>And come to us as favourers, not as foes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Thou speak'st like him's untutor'd to repeat:</line>
<line>Who makes the fairest show means most deceit.</line>
<line>But bring they what they will and what they can,</line>
<line>What need we fear?</line>
<line>The ground's the lowest, and we are half way there.</line>
<line>Go tell their general we attend him here,</line>
<line>To know for what he comes, and whence he comes,</line>
<line>And what he craves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord</speaker>
<line>I go, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Welcome is peace, if he on peace consist;</line>
<line>If wars, we are unable to resist.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES with Attendants</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Lord governor, for so we hear you are,</line>
<line>Let not our ships and number of our men</line>
<line>Be like a beacon fired to amaze your eyes.</line>
<line>We have heard your miseries as far as Tyre,</line>
<line>And seen the desolation of your streets:</line>
<line>Nor come we to add sorrow to your tears,</line>
<line>But to relieve them of their heavy load;</line>
<line>And these our ships, you happily may think</line>
<line>Are like the Trojan horse was stuff'd within</line>
<line>With bloody veins, expecting overthrow,</line>
<line>Are stored with corn to make your needy bread,</line>
<line>And give them life whom hunger starved half dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All</speaker>
<line>The gods of Greece protect you!</line>
<line>And we'll pray for you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Arise, I pray you, rise:</line>
<line>We do not look for reverence, but to love,</line>
<line>And harbourage for ourself, our ships, and men.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>The which when any shall not gratify,</line>
<line>Or pay you with unthankfulness in thought,</line>
<line>Be it our wives, our children, or ourselves,</line>
<line>The curse of heaven and men succeed their evils!</line>
<line>Till when,--the which I hope shall ne'er be seen,--</line>
<line>Your grace is welcome to our town and us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Which welcome we'll accept; feast here awhile,</line>
<line>Until our stars that frown lend us a smile.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT II</title>

<section role="prologue"><title>[Prologue]</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>Here have you seen a mighty king</line>
<line>His child, I wis, to incest bring;</line>
<line>A better prince and benign lord,</line>
<line>That will prove awful both in deed and word.</line>
<line>Be quiet then as men should be,</line>
<line>Till he hath pass'd necessity.</line>
<line>I'll show you those in troubles reign,</line>
<line>Losing a mite, a mountain gain.</line>
<line>The good in conversation,</line>
<line>To whom I give my benison,</line>
<line>Is still at Tarsus, where each man</line>
<line>Thinks all is writ he speken can;</line>
<line>And, to remember what he does,</line>
<line>Build his statue to make him glorious:</line>
<line>But tidings to the contrary</line>
<line>Are brought your eyes; what need speak I?</line>
<bridgehead role="subhead">DUMB SHOW.</bridgehead>
<para role="stagedir">Enter at one door PERICLES talking with CLEON; all
the train with them. Enter at another door a
Gentleman, with a letter to PERICLES; PERICLES
shows the letter to CLEON; gives the Messenger a
reward, and knights him. Exit PERICLES at one
door, and CLEON at another</para>
<line>Good Helicane, that stay'd at home,</line>
<line>Not to eat honey like a drone</line>
<line>From others' labours; for though he strive</line>
<line>To killen bad, keep good alive;</line>
<line>And to fulfil his prince' desire,</line>
<line>Sends word of all that haps in Tyre:</line>
<line>How Thaliard came full bent with sin</line>
<line>And had intent to murder him;</line>
<line>And that in Tarsus was not best</line>
<line>Longer for him to make his rest.</line>
<line>He, doing so, put forth to seas,</line>
<line>Where when men been, there's seldom ease;</line>
<line>For now the wind begins to blow;</line>
<line>Thunder above and deeps below</line>
<line>Make such unquiet, that the ship</line>
<line>Should house him safe is wreck'd and split;</line>
<line>And he, good prince, having all lost,</line>
<line>By waves from coast to coast is tost:</line>
<line>All perishen of man, of pelf,</line>
<line>Ne aught escapen but himself;</line>
<line>Till fortune, tired with doing bad,</line>
<line>Threw him ashore, to give him glad:</line>
<line>And here he comes. What shall be next,</line>
<line>Pardon old Gower,--this longs the text.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Pentapolis. An open place by the sea-side.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES, wet</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Yet cease your ire, you angry stars of heaven!</line>
<line>Wind, rain, and thunder, remember, earthly man</line>
<line>Is but a substance that must yield to you;</line>
<line>And I, as fits my nature, do obey you:</line>
<line>Alas, the sea hath cast me on the rocks,</line>
<line>Wash'd me from shore to shore, and left me breath</line>
<line>Nothing to think on but ensuing death:</line>
<line>Let it suffice the greatness of your powers</line>
<line>To have bereft a prince of all his fortunes;</line>
<line>And having thrown him from your watery grave,</line>
<line>Here to have death in peace is all he'll crave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter three FISHERMEN</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>What, ho, Pilch!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Ha, come and bring away the nets!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>What, Patch-breech, I say!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Fisherman</speaker>
<line>What say you, master?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Look how thou stirrest now! come away, or I'll</line>
<line>fetch thee with a wanion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Faith, master, I am thinking of the poor men that</line>
<line>were cast away before us even now.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Alas, poor souls, it grieved my heart to hear what</line>
<line>pitiful cries they made to us to help them, when,</line>
<line>well-a-day, we could scarce help ourselves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Nay, master, said not I as much when I saw the</line>
<line>porpus how he bounced and tumbled? they say</line>
<line>they're half fish, half flesh: a plague on them,</line>
<line>they ne'er come but I look to be washed. Master, I</line>
<line>marvel how the fishes live in the sea.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Why, as men do a-land; the great ones eat up the</line>
<line>little ones: I can compare our rich misers to</line>
<line>nothing so fitly as to a whale; a' plays and</line>
<line>tumbles, driving the poor fry before him, and at</line>
<line>last devours them all at a mouthful: such whales</line>
<line>have I heard on o' the land, who never leave gaping</line>
<line>till they've swallowed the whole parish, church,</line>
<line>steeple, bells, and all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  A pretty moral.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Fisherman</speaker>
<line>But, master, if I had been the sexton, I would have</line>
<line>been that day in the belfry.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Why, man?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Because he should have swallowed me too: and when I</line>
<line>had been in his belly, I would have kept such a</line>
<line>jangling of the bells, that he should never have</line>
<line>left, till he cast bells, steeple, church, and</line>
<line>parish up again. But if the good King Simonides</line>
<line>were of my mind,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Simonides!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Fisherman</speaker>
<line>We would purge the land of these drones, that rob</line>
<line>the bee of her honey.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  How from the finny subject of the sea</line>
<line>These fishers tell the infirmities of men;</line>
<line>And from their watery empire recollect</line>
<line>All that may men approve or men detect!</line>
<line>Peace be at your labour, honest fishermen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Honest! good fellow, what's that? If it be a day</line>
<line>fits you, search out of the calendar, and nobody</line>
<line>look after it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>May see the sea hath cast upon your coast.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>What a drunken knave was the sea to cast thee in our</line>
<line>way!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>A man whom both the waters and the wind,</line>
<line>In that vast tennis-court, have made the ball</line>
<line>For them to play upon, entreats you pity him:</line>
<line>He asks of you, that never used to beg.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>No, friend, cannot you beg? Here's them in our</line>
<line>country Greece gets more with begging than we can do</line>
<line>with working.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Canst thou catch any fishes, then?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I never practised it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Nay, then thou wilt starve, sure; for here's nothing</line>
<line>to be got now-a-days, unless thou canst fish for't.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>What I have been I have forgot to know;</line>
<line>But what I am, want teaches me to think on:</line>
<line>A man throng'd up with cold: my veins are chill,</line>
<line>And have no more of life than may suffice</line>
<line>To give my tongue that heat to ask your help;</line>
<line>Which if you shall refuse, when I am dead,</line>
<line>For that I am a man, pray see me buried.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Die quoth-a? Now gods forbid! I have a gown here;</line>
<line>come, put it on; keep thee warm. Now, afore me, a</line>
<line>handsome fellow! Come, thou shalt go home, and</line>
<line>we'll have flesh for holidays, fish for</line>
<line>fasting-days, and moreo'er puddings and flap-jacks,</line>
<line>and thou shalt be welcome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I thank you, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Hark you, my friend; you said you could not beg.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I did but crave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>But crave! Then I'll turn craver too, and so I</line>
<line>shall 'scape whipping.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Why, are all your beggars whipped, then?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>O, not all, my friend, not all; for if all your</line>
<line>beggars were whipped, I would wish no better office</line>
<line>than to be beadle. But, master, I'll go draw up the</line>
<line>net.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit with Third Fisherman</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  How well this honest mirth becomes their labour!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Hark you, sir, do you know where ye are?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Not well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Why, I'll tell you: this is called Pentapolis, and</line>
<line>our king the good Simonides.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>The good King Simonides, do you call him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Ay, sir; and he deserves so to be called for his</line>
<line>peaceable reign and good government.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>He is a happy king, since he gains from his subjects</line>
<line>the name of good by his government. How far is his</line>
<line>court distant from this shore?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Marry, sir, half a day's journey: and I'll tell</line>
<line>you, he hath a fair daughter, and to-morrow is her</line>
<line>birth-day; and there are princes and knights come</line>
<line>from all parts of the world to just and tourney for her love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Were my fortunes equal to my desires, I could wish</line>
<line>to make one there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>O, sir, things must be as they may; and what a man</line>
<line>cannot get, he may lawfully deal for--his wife's soul.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter Second and Third Fishermen, drawing up a net</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Help, master, help! here's a fish hangs in the net,</line>
<line>like a poor man's right in the law; 'twill hardly</line>
<line>come out. Ha! bots on't, 'tis come at last, and</line>
<line>'tis turned to a rusty armour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>An armour, friends! I pray you, let me see it.</line>
<line>Thanks, fortune, yet, that, after all my crosses,</line>
<line>Thou givest me somewhat to repair myself;</line>
<line>And though it was mine own, part of my heritage,</line>
<line>Which my dead father did bequeath to me.</line>
<line>With this strict charge, even as he left his life,</line>
<line>'Keep it, my Pericles; it hath been a shield</line>
<line>Twixt me and death;'--and pointed to this brace;--</line>
<line>'For that it saved me, keep it; in like necessity--</line>
<line>The which the gods protect thee from!--may</line>
<line>defend thee.'</line>
<line>It kept where I kept, I so dearly loved it;</line>
<line>Till the rough seas, that spare not any man,</line>
<line>Took it in rage, though calm'd have given't again:</line>
<line>I thank thee for't: my shipwreck now's no ill,</line>
<line>Since I have here my father's gift in's will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>What mean you, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>To beg of you, kind friends, this coat of worth,</line>
<line>For it was sometime target to a king;</line>
<line>I know it by this mark. He loved me dearly,</line>
<line>And for his sake I wish the having of it;</line>
<line>And that you'ld guide me to your sovereign's court,</line>
<line>Where with it I may appear a gentleman;</line>
<line>And if that ever my low fortune's better,</line>
<line>I'll pay your bounties; till then rest your debtor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Why, wilt thou tourney for the lady?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I'll show the virtue I have borne in arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Why, do 'e take it, and the gods give thee good on't!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>Ay, but hark you, my friend; 'twas we that made up</line>
<line>this garment through the rough seams of the waters:</line>
<line>there are certain condolements, certain vails. I</line>
<line>hope, sir, if you thrive, you'll remember from</line>
<line>whence you had it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Believe 't, I will.</line>
<line>By your furtherance I am clothed in steel;</line>
<line>And, spite of all the rapture of the sea,</line>
<line>This jewel holds his building on my arm:</line>
<line>Unto thy value I will mount myself</line>
<line>Upon a courser, whose delightful steps</line>
<line>Shall make the gazer joy to see him tread.</line>
<line>Only, my friend, I yet am unprovided</line>
<line>Of a pair of bases.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Fisherman</speaker>
<line>We'll sure provide: thou shalt have my best gown to</line>
<line>make thee a pair; and I'll bring thee to the court myself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Then honour be but a goal to my will,</line>
<line>This day I'll rise, or else add ill to ill.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The same. A public way or platform leading to the lists. A pavilion by the side of it for the reception of King, Princess, Lords, &amp;c.</title>

<para role="stagedir">Enter SIMONIDES, THAISA, Lords, and Attendants</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Are the knights ready to begin the triumph?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>They are, my liege;</line>
<line>And stay your coming to present themselves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Return them, we are ready; and our daughter,</line>
<line>In honour of whose birth these triumphs are,</line>
<line>Sits here, like beauty's child, whom nature gat</line>
<line>For men to see, and seeing wonder at.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit a Lord</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>It pleaseth you, my royal father, to express</line>
<line>My commendations great, whose merit's less.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>It's fit it should be so; for princes are</line>
<line>A model which heaven makes like to itself:</line>
<line>As jewels lose their glory if neglected,</line>
<line>So princes their renowns if not respected.</line>
<line>'Tis now your honour, daughter, to explain</line>
<line>The labour of each knight in his device.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Which, to preserve mine honour, I'll perform.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Knight; he passes over, and his Squire
presents his shield to the Princess</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Who is the first that doth prefer himself?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>A knight of Sparta, my renowned father;</line>
<line>And the device he bears upon his shield</line>
<line>Is a black Ethiope reaching at the sun</line>
<line>The word, 'Lux tua vita mihi.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>He loves you well that holds his life of you.</line>
<para role="stagedir">The Second Knight passes over</para>
<line>Who is the second that presents himself?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>A prince of Macedon, my royal father;</line>
<line>And the device he bears upon his shield</line>
<line>Is an arm'd knight that's conquer'd by a lady;</line>
<line>The motto thus, in Spanish, 'Piu por dulzura que por fuerza.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The Third Knight passes over</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>And what's the third?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>The third of Antioch;</line>
<line>And his device, a wreath of chivalry;</line>
<line>The word, 'Me pompae provexit apex.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The Fourth Knight passes over</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>What is the fourth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>A burning torch that's turned upside down;</line>
<line>The word, 'Quod me alit, me extinguit.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Which shows that beauty hath his power and will,</line>
<line>Which can as well inflame as it can kill.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The Fifth Knight passes over</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>The fifth, an hand environed with clouds,</line>
<line>Holding out gold that's by the touchstone tried;</line>
<line>The motto thus, 'Sic spectanda fides.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The Sixth Knight, PERICLES, passes over</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>And what's</line>
<line>The sixth and last, the which the knight himself</line>
<line>With such a graceful courtesy deliver'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>He seems to be a stranger; but his present is</line>
<line>A wither'd branch, that's only green at top;</line>
<line>The motto, 'In hac spe vivo.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>A pretty moral;</line>
<line>From the dejected state wherein he is,</line>
<line>He hopes by you his fortunes yet may flourish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>He had need mean better than his outward show</line>
<line>Can any way speak in his just commend;</line>
<line>For by his rusty outside he appears</line>
<line>To have practised more the whipstock than the lance.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Lord</speaker>
<line>He well may be a stranger, for he comes</line>
<line>To an honour'd triumph strangely furnished.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Lord</speaker>
<line>And on set purpose let his armour rust</line>
<line>Until this day, to scour it in the dust.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Opinion's but a fool, that makes us scan</line>
<line>The outward habit by the inward man.</line>
<line>But stay, the knights are coming: we will withdraw</line>
<line>Into the gallery.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
<para role="stagedir">Great shouts within and all cry 'The mean knight!'</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The same. A hall of state: a banquet prepared.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SIMONIDES, THAISA, Lords, Attendants, and
Knights, from tilting</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Knights,</line>
<line>To say you're welcome were superfluous.</line>
<line>To place upon the volume of your deeds,</line>
<line>As in a title-page, your worth in arms,</line>
<line>Were more than you expect, or more than's fit,</line>
<line>Since every worth in show commends itself.</line>
<line>Prepare for mirth, for mirth becomes a feast:</line>
<line>You are princes and my guests.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>But you, my knight and guest;</line>
<line>To whom this wreath of victory I give,</line>
<line>And crown you king of this day's happiness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>'Tis more by fortune, lady, than by merit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Call it by what you will, the day is yours;</line>
<line>And here, I hope, is none that envies it.</line>
<line>In framing an artist, art hath thus decreed,</line>
<line>To make some good, but others to exceed;</line>
<line>And you are her labour'd scholar. Come, queen o'</line>
<line>the feast,--</line>
<line>For, daughter, so you are,--here take your place:</line>
<line>Marshal the rest, as they deserve their grace.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KNIGHTS</speaker>
<line>We are honour'd much by good Simonides.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Your presence glads our days: honour we love;</line>
<line>For who hates honour hates the gods above.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Marshal</speaker>
<line>Sir, yonder is your place.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Some other is more fit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Knight</speaker>
<line>Contend not, sir; for we are gentlemen</line>
<line>That neither in our hearts nor outward eyes</line>
<line>Envy the great nor do the low despise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>You are right courteous knights.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Sit, sir, sit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>By Jove, I wonder, that is king of thoughts,</line>
<line>These cates resist me, she but thought upon.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>By Juno, that is queen of marriage,</line>
<line>All viands that I eat do seem unsavoury.</line>
<line>Wishing him my meat. Sure, he's a gallant gentleman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>He's but a country gentleman;</line>
<line>Has done no more than other knights have done;</line>
<line>Has broken a staff or so; so let it pass.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>To me he seems like diamond to glass.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Yon king's to me like to my father's picture,</line>
<line>Which tells me in that glory once he was;</line>
<line>Had princes sit, like stars, about his throne,</line>
<line>And he the sun, for them to reverence;</line>
<line>None that beheld him, but, like lesser lights,</line>
<line>Did vail their crowns to his supremacy:</line>
<line>Where now his son's like a glow-worm in the night,</line>
<line>The which hath fire in darkness, none in light:</line>
<line>Whereby I see that Time's the king of men,</line>
<line>He's both their parent, and he is their grave,</line>
<line>And gives them what he will, not what they crave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>What, are you merry, knights?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Knights</speaker>
<line>Who can be other in this royal presence?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Here, with a cup that's stored unto the brim,--</line>
<line>As you do love, fill to your mistress' lips,--</line>
<line>We drink this health to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KNIGHTS</speaker>
<line>We thank your grace.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Yet pause awhile:</line>
<line>Yon knight doth sit too melancholy,</line>
<line>As if the entertainment in our court</line>
<line>Had not a show might countervail his worth.</line>
<line>Note it not you, Thaisa?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>What is it</line>
<line>To me, my father?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>O, attend, my daughter:</line>
<line>Princes in this should live like gods above,</line>
<line>Who freely give to every one that comes</line>
<line>To honour them:</line>
<line>And princes not doing so are like to gnats,</line>
<line>Which make a sound, but kill'd are wonder'd at.</line>
<line>Therefore to make his entrance more sweet,</line>
<line>Here, say we drink this standing-bowl of wine to him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Alas, my father, it befits not me</line>
<line>Unto a stranger knight to be so bold:</line>
<line>He may my proffer take for an offence,</line>
<line>Since men take women's gifts for impudence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>How!</line>
<line>Do as I bid you, or you'll move me else.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Now, by the gods, he could not please me better.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>And furthermore tell him, we desire to know of him,</line>
<line>Of whence he is, his name and parentage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>The king my father, sir, has drunk to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I thank him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Wishing it so much blood unto your life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I thank both him and you, and pledge him freely.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>And further he desires to know of you,</line>
<line>Of whence you are, your name and parentage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>A gentleman of Tyre; my name, Pericles;</line>
<line>My education been in arts and arms;</line>
<line>Who, looking for adventures in the world,</line>
<line>Was by the rough seas reft of ships and men,</line>
<line>And after shipwreck driven upon this shore.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>He thanks your grace; names himself Pericles,</line>
<line>A gentleman of Tyre,</line>
<line>Who only by misfortune of the seas</line>
<line>Bereft of ships and men, cast on this shore.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Now, by the gods, I pity his misfortune,</line>
<line>And will awake him from his melancholy.</line>
<line>Come, gentlemen, we sit too long on trifles,</line>
<line>And waste the time, which looks for other revels.</line>
<line>Even in your armours, as you are address'd,</line>
<line>Will very well become a soldier's dance.</line>
<line>I will not have excuse, with saying this</line>
<line>Loud music is too harsh for ladies' heads,</line>
<line>Since they love men in arms as well as beds.</line>
<para role="stagedir">The Knights dance</para>
<line>So, this was well ask'd,'twas so well perform'd.</line>
<line>Come, sir;</line>
<line>Here is a lady that wants breathing too:</line>
<line>And I have heard, you knights of Tyre</line>
<line>Are excellent in making ladies trip;</line>
<line>And that their measures are as excellent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>In those that practise them they are, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>O, that's as much as you would be denied</line>
<line>Of your fair courtesy.</line>
<para role="stagedir">The Knights and Ladies dance</para>
<line>Unclasp, unclasp:</line>
<line>Thanks, gentlemen, to all; all have done well.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To PERICLES</para>
<line>But you the best. Pages and lights, to conduct</line>
<line>These knights unto their several lodgings!</line>
<para role="stagedir">To PERICLES</para>
<line>Yours, sir,</line>
<line>We have given order to be next our own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I am at your grace's pleasure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Princes, it is too late to talk of love;</line>
<line>And that's the mark I know you level at:</line>
<line>Therefore each one betake him to his rest;</line>
<line>To-morrow all for speeding do their best.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  Tyre. A room in the Governor's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HELICANUS and ESCANES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>No, Escanes, know this of me,</line>
<line>Antiochus from incest lived not free:</line>
<line>For which, the most high gods not minding longer</line>
<line>To withhold the vengeance that they had in store,</line>
<line>Due to this heinous capital offence,</line>
<line>Even in the height and pride of all his glory,</line>
<line>When he was seated in a chariot</line>
<line>Of an inestimable value, and his daughter with him,</line>
<line>A fire from heaven came and shrivell'd up</line>
<line>Their bodies, even to loathing; for they so stunk,</line>
<line>That all those eyes adored them ere their fall</line>
<line>Scorn now their hand should give them burial.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ESCANES</speaker>
<line>'Twas very strange.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>And yet but justice; for though</line>
<line>This king were great, his greatness was no guard</line>
<line>To bar heaven's shaft, but sin had his reward.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">ESCANES</speaker>
<line>'Tis very true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter two or three Lords</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>See, not a man in private conference</line>
<line>Or council has respect with him but he.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Lord</speaker>
<line>It shall no longer grieve without reproof.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Lord</speaker>
<line>And cursed be he that will not second it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>Follow me, then. Lord Helicane, a word.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>With me? and welcome: happy day, my lords.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>Know that our griefs are risen to the top,</line>
<line>And now at length they overflow their banks.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Your griefs! for what? wrong not your prince you love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>Wrong not yourself, then, noble Helicane;</line>
<line>But if the prince do live, let us salute him,</line>
<line>Or know what ground's made happy by his breath.</line>
<line>If in the world he live, we'll seek him out;</line>
<line>If in his grave he rest, we'll find him there;</line>
<line>And be resolved he lives to govern us,</line>
<line>Or dead, give's cause to mourn his funeral,</line>
<line>And leave us to our free election.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Lord</speaker>
<line>Whose death indeed's the strongest in our censure:</line>
<line>And knowing this kingdom is without a head,--</line>
<line>Like goodly buildings left without a roof</line>
<line>Soon fall to ruin,--your noble self,</line>
<line>That best know how to rule and how to reign,</line>
<line>We thus submit unto,--our sovereign.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All</speaker>
<line>Live, noble Helicane!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>For honour's cause, forbear your suffrages:</line>
<line>If that you love Prince Pericles, forbear.</line>
<line>Take I your wish, I leap into the seas,</line>
<line>Where's hourly trouble for a minute's ease.</line>
<line>A twelvemonth longer, let me entreat you to</line>
<line>Forbear the absence of your king:</line>
<line>If in which time expired, he not return,</line>
<line>I shall with aged patience bear your yoke.</line>
<line>But if I cannot win you to this love,</line>
<line>Go search like nobles, like noble subjects,</line>
<line>And in your search spend your adventurous worth;</line>
<line>Whom if you find, and win unto return,</line>
<line>You shall like diamonds sit about his crown.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>To wisdom he's a fool that will not yield;</line>
<line>And since Lord Helicane enjoineth us,</line>
<line>We with our travels will endeavour us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Then you love us, we you, and we'll clasp hands:</line>
<line>When peers thus knit, a kingdom ever stands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE V.  Pentapolis. A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SIMONIDES, reading a letter, at one door:
the Knights meet him</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Knight</speaker>
<line>Good morrow to the good Simonides.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Knights, from my daughter this I let you know,</line>
<line>That for this twelvemonth she'll not undertake</line>
<line>A married life.</line>
<line>Her reason to herself is only known,</line>
<line>Which yet from her by no means can I get.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Knight</speaker>
<line>May we not get access to her, my lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>'Faith, by no means; she has so strictly tied</line>
<line>Her to her chamber, that 'tis impossible.</line>
<line>One twelve moons more she'll wear Diana's livery;</line>
<line>This by the eye of Cynthia hath she vow'd</line>
<line>And on her virgin honour will not break it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Knight</speaker>
<line>Loath to bid farewell, we take our leaves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Knights</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>So,</line>
<line>They are well dispatch'd; now to my daughter's letter:</line>
<line>She tells me here, she'd wed the stranger knight,</line>
<line>Or never more to view nor day nor light.</line>
<line>'Tis well, mistress; your choice agrees with mine;</line>
<line>I like that well: nay, how absolute she's in't,</line>
<line>Not minding whether I dislike or no!</line>
<line>Well, I do commend her choice;</line>
<line>And will no longer have it be delay'd.</line>
<line>Soft! here he comes: I must dissemble it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>All fortune to the good Simonides!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>To you as much, sir! I am beholding to you</line>
<line>For your sweet music this last night: I do</line>
<line>Protest my ears were never better fed</line>
<line>With such delightful pleasing harmony.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>It is your grace's pleasure to commend;</line>
<line>Not my desert.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Sir, you are music's master.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>The worst of all her scholars, my good lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Let me ask you one thing:</line>
<line>What do you think of my daughter, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>A most virtuous princess.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>And she is fair too, is she not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>As a fair day in summer, wondrous fair.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Sir, my daughter thinks very well of you;</line>
<line>Ay, so well, that you must be her master,</line>
<line>And she will be your scholar: therefore look to it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I am unworthy for her schoolmaster.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>She thinks not so; peruse this writing else.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  What's here?</line>
<line>A letter, that she loves the knight of Tyre!</line>
<line>'Tis the king's subtlety to have my life.</line>
<line>O, seek not to entrap me, gracious lord,</line>
<line>A stranger and distressed gentleman,</line>
<line>That never aim'd so high to love your daughter,</line>
<line>But bent all offices to honour her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Thou hast bewitch'd my daughter, and thou art</line>
<line>A villain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>By the gods, I have not:</line>
<line>Never did thought of mine levy offence;</line>
<line>Nor never did my actions yet commence</line>
<line>A deed might gain her love or your displeasure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Traitor, thou liest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Traitor!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Ay, traitor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Even in his throat--unless it be the king--</line>
<line>That calls me traitor, I return the lie.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Now, by the gods, I do applaud his courage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>My actions are as noble as my thoughts,</line>
<line>That never relish'd of a base descent.</line>
<line>I came unto your court for honour's cause,</line>
<line>And not to be a rebel to her state;</line>
<line>And he that otherwise accounts of me,</line>
<line>This sword shall prove he's honour's enemy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>No?</line>
<line>Here comes my daughter, she can witness it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter THAISA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Then, as you are as virtuous as fair,</line>
<line>Resolve your angry father, if my tongue</line>
<line>Did ere solicit, or my hand subscribe</line>
<line>To any syllable that made love to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Why, sir, say if you had,</line>
<line>Who takes offence at that would make me glad?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>Yea, mistress, are you so peremptory?</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>I am glad on't with all my heart.--</line>
<line>I'll tame you; I'll bring you in subjection.</line>
<line>Will you, not having my consent,</line>
<line>Bestow your love and your affections</line>
<line>Upon a stranger?</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>who, for aught I know,</line>
<line>May be, nor can I think the contrary,</line>
<line>As great in blood as I myself.--</line>
<line>Therefore hear you, mistress; either frame</line>
<line>Your will to mine,--and you, sir, hear you,</line>
<line>Either be ruled by me, or I will make you--</line>
<line>Man and wife:</line>
<line>Nay, come, your hands and lips must seal it too:</line>
<line>And being join'd, I'll thus your hopes destroy;</line>
<line>And for a further grief,--God give you joy!--</line>
<line>What, are you both pleased?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Yes, if you love me, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Even as my life, or blood that fosters it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>What, are you both agreed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOTH</speaker>
<line>Yes, if it please your majesty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIMONIDES</speaker>
<line>It pleaseth me so well, that I will see you wed;</line>
<line>And then with what haste you can get you to bed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT III</title>

<section role="prologue"><title>[Prologue]</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>Now sleep y-slaked hath the rout;</line>
<line>No din but snores the house about,</line>
<line>Made louder by the o'er-fed breast</line>
<line>Of this most pompous marriage-feast.</line>
<line>The cat, with eyne of burning coal,</line>
<line>Now crouches fore the mouse's hole;</line>
<line>And crickets sing at the oven's mouth,</line>
<line>E'er the blither for their drouth.</line>
<line>Hymen hath brought the bride to bed.</line>
<line>Where, by the loss of maidenhead,</line>
<line>A babe is moulded. Be attent,</line>
<line>And time that is so briefly spent</line>
<line>With your fine fancies quaintly eche:</line>
<line>What's dumb in show I'll plain with speech.</line>
<bridgehead role="subhead">DUMB SHOW.</bridgehead>
<para role="stagedir">Enter, PERICLES and SIMONIDES at one door, with
Attendants; a Messenger meets them, kneels, and
gives PERICLES a letter: PERICLES shows it
SIMONIDES; the Lords kneel to him. Then enter
THAISA with child, with LYCHORIDA a nurse. The
KING shows her the letter; she rejoices: she and
PERICLES takes leave of her father, and depart with
LYCHORIDA and their Attendants. Then exeunt
SIMONIDES and the rest</para>
<line>By many a dern and painful perch</line>
<line>Of Pericles the careful search,</line>
<line>By the four opposing coigns</line>
<line>Which the world together joins,</line>
<line>Is made with all due diligence</line>
<line>That horse and sail and high expense</line>
<line>Can stead the quest. At last from Tyre,</line>
<line>Fame answering the most strange inquire,</line>
<line>To the court of King Simonides</line>
<line>Are letters brought, the tenor these:</line>
<line>Antiochus and his daughter dead;</line>
<line>The men of Tyrus on the head</line>
<line>Of Helicanus would set on</line>
<line>The crown of Tyre, but he will none:</line>
<line>The mutiny he there hastes t' oppress;</line>
<line>Says to 'em, if King Pericles</line>
<line>Come not home in twice six moons,</line>
<line>He, obedient to their dooms,</line>
<line>Will take the crown. The sum of this,</line>
<line>Brought hither to Pentapolis,</line>
<line>Y-ravished the regions round,</line>
<line>And every one with claps can sound,</line>
<line>'Our heir-apparent is a king!</line>
<line>Who dream'd, who thought of such a thing?'</line>
<line>Brief, he must hence depart to Tyre:</line>
<line>His queen with child makes her desire--</line>
<line>Which who shall cross?--along to go:</line>
<line>Omit we all their dole and woe:</line>
<line>Lychorida, her nurse, she takes,</line>
<line>And so to sea. Their vessel shakes</line>
<line>On Neptune's billow; half the flood</line>
<line>Hath their keel cut: but fortune's mood</line>
<line>Varies again; the grisly north</line>
<line>Disgorges such a tempest forth,</line>
<line>That, as a duck for life that dives,</line>
<line>So up and down the poor ship drives:</line>
<line>The lady shrieks, and well-a-near</line>
<line>Does fall in travail with her fear:</line>
<line>And what ensues in this fell storm</line>
<line>Shall for itself itself perform.</line>
<line>I nill relate, action may</line>
<line>Conveniently the rest convey;</line>
<line>Which might not what by me is told.</line>
<line>In your imagination hold</line>
<line>This stage the ship, upon whose deck</line>
<line>The sea-tost Pericles appears to speak.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES, on shipboard</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Thou god of this great vast, rebuke these surges,</line>
<line>Which wash both heaven and hell; and thou, that hast</line>
<line>Upon the winds command, bind them in brass,</line>
<line>Having call'd them from the deep! O, still</line>
<line>Thy deafening, dreadful thunders; gently quench</line>
<line>Thy nimble, sulphurous flashes! O, how, Lychorida,</line>
<line>How does my queen? Thou stormest venomously;</line>
<line>Wilt thou spit all thyself? The seaman's whistle</line>
<line>Is as a whisper in the ears of death,</line>
<line>Unheard. Lychorida!--Lucina, O</line>
<line>Divinest patroness, and midwife gentle</line>
<line>To those that cry by night, convey thy deity</line>
<line>Aboard our dancing boat; make swift the pangs</line>
<line>Of my queen's travails!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter LYCHORIDA, with an Infant</para>
<line>Now, Lychorida!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYCHORIDA</speaker>
<line>Here is a thing too young for such a place,</line>
<line>Who, if it had conceit, would die, as I</line>
<line>Am like to do: take in your arms this piece</line>
<line>Of your dead queen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>How, how, Lychorida!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYCHORIDA</speaker>
<line>Patience, good sir; do not assist the storm.</line>
<line>Here's all that is left living of your queen,</line>
<line>A little daughter: for the sake of it,</line>
<line>Be manly, and take comfort.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>O you gods!</line>
<line>Why do you make us love your goodly gifts,</line>
<line>And snatch them straight away? We here below</line>
<line>Recall not what we give, and therein may</line>
<line>Use honour with you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYCHORIDA</speaker>
<line>Patience, good sir,</line>
<line>Even for this charge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Now, mild may be thy life!</line>
<line>For a more blustrous birth had never babe:</line>
<line>Quiet and gentle thy conditions! for</line>
<line>Thou art the rudeliest welcome to this world</line>
<line>That ever was prince's child. Happy what follows!</line>
<line>Thou hast as chiding a nativity</line>
<line>As fire, air, water, earth, and heaven can make,</line>
<line>To herald thee from the womb: even at the first</line>
<line>Thy loss is more than can thy portage quit,</line>
<line>With all thou canst find here. Now, the good gods</line>
<line>Throw their best eyes upon't!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter two Sailors</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Sailor</speaker>
<line>What courage, sir? God save you!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Courage enough: I do not fear the flaw;</line>
<line>It hath done to me the worst. Yet, for the love</line>
<line>Of this poor infant, this fresh-new sea-farer,</line>
<line>I would it would be quiet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Sailor</speaker>
<line>Slack the bolins there! Thou wilt not, wilt thou?</line>
<line>Blow, and split thyself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Sailor</speaker>
<line>But sea-room, an the brine and cloudy billow kiss</line>
<line>the moon, I care not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Sailor</speaker>
<line>Sir, your queen must overboard: the sea works high,</line>
<line>the wind is loud, and will not lie till the ship be</line>
<line>cleared of the dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>That's your superstition.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Sailor</speaker>
<line>Pardon us, sir; with us at sea it hath been still</line>
<line>observed: and we are strong in custom. Therefore</line>
<line>briefly yield her; for she must overboard straight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>As you think meet. Most wretched queen!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYCHORIDA</speaker>
<line>Here she lies, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>A terrible childbed hast thou had, my dear;</line>
<line>No light, no fire: the unfriendly elements</line>
<line>Forgot thee utterly: nor have I time</line>
<line>To give thee hallow'd to thy grave, but straight</line>
<line>Must cast thee, scarcely coffin'd, in the ooze;</line>
<line>Where, for a monument upon thy bones,</line>
<line>And e'er-remaining lamps, the belching whale</line>
<line>And humming water must o'erwhelm thy corpse,</line>
<line>Lying with simple shells. O Lychorida,</line>
<line>Bid Nestor bring me spices, ink and paper,</line>
<line>My casket and my jewels; and bid Nicander</line>
<line>Bring me the satin coffer: lay the babe</line>
<line>Upon the pillow: hie thee, whiles I say</line>
<line>A priestly farewell to her: suddenly, woman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit LYCHORIDA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Sailor</speaker>
<line>Sir, we have a chest beneath the hatches, caulked</line>
<line>and bitumed ready.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I thank thee. Mariner, say what coast is this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Sailor</speaker>
<line>We are near Tarsus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Thither, gentle mariner.</line>
<line>Alter thy course for Tyre. When canst thou reach it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Sailor</speaker>
<line>By break of day, if the wind cease.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>O, make for Tarsus!</line>
<line>There will I visit Cleon, for the babe</line>
<line>Cannot hold out to Tyrus: there I'll leave it</line>
<line>At careful nursing. Go thy ways, good mariner:</line>
<line>I'll bring the body presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  Ephesus. A room in CERIMON's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CERIMON, with a Servant, and some Persons who
have been shipwrecked</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Philemon, ho!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter PHILEMON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PHILEMON</speaker>
<line>Doth my lord call?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Get fire and meat for these poor men:</line>
<line>'T has been a turbulent and stormy night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>I have been in many; but such a night as this,</line>
<line>Till now, I ne'er endured.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Your master will be dead ere you return;</line>
<line>There's nothing can be minister'd to nature</line>
<line>That can recover him.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To PHILEMON</para>
<line>Give this to the 'pothecary,</line>
<line>And tell me how it works.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all but CERIMON</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter two Gentlemen</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Good morrow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Good morrow to your lordship.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Gentlemen,</line>
<line>Why do you stir so early?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>Our lodgings, standing bleak upon the sea,</line>
<line>Shook as the earth did quake;</line>
<line>The very principals did seem to rend,</line>
<line>And all-to topple: pure surprise and fear</line>
<line>Made me to quit the house.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>That is the cause we trouble you so early;</line>
<line>'Tis not our husbandry.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>O, you say well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>But I much marvel that your lordship, having</line>
<line>Rich tire about you, should at these early hours</line>
<line>Shake off the golden slumber of repose.</line>
<line>'Tis most strange,</line>
<line>Nature should be so conversant with pain,</line>
<line>Being thereto not compell'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>I hold it ever,</line>
<line>Virtue and cunning were endowments greater</line>
<line>Than nobleness and riches: careless heirs</line>
<line>May the two latter darken and expend;</line>
<line>But immortality attends the former.</line>
<line>Making a man a god. 'Tis known, I ever</line>
<line>Have studied physic, through which secret art,</line>
<line>By turning o'er authorities, I have,</line>
<line>Together with my practise, made familiar</line>
<line>To me and to my aid the blest infusions</line>
<line>That dwell in vegetives, in metals, stones;</line>
<line>And I can speak of the disturbances</line>
<line>That nature works, and of her cures; which doth give me</line>
<line>A more content in course of true delight</line>
<line>Than to be thirsty after tottering honour,</line>
<line>Or tie my treasure up in silken bags,</line>
<line>To please the fool and death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Your honour has through Ephesus pour'd forth</line>
<line>Your charity, and hundreds call themselves</line>
<line>Your creatures, who by you have been restored:</line>
<line>And not your knowledge, your personal pain, but even</line>
<line>Your purse, still open, hath built Lord Cerimon</line>
<line>Such strong renown as time shall ne'er decay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter two or three Servants with a chest</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Servant</speaker>
<line>So; lift there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>What is that?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Servant</speaker>
<line>Sir, even now</line>
<line>Did the sea toss upon our shore this chest:</line>
<line>'Tis of some wreck.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Set 't down, let's look upon't.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>'Tis like a coffin, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Whate'er it be,</line>
<line>'Tis wondrous heavy. Wrench it open straight:</line>
<line>If the sea's stomach be o'ercharged with gold,</line>
<line>'Tis a good constraint of fortune it belches upon us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>'Tis so, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>How close 'tis caulk'd and bitumed!</line>
<line>Did the sea cast it up?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Servant</speaker>
<line>I never saw so huge a billow, sir,</line>
<line>As toss'd it upon shore.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Wrench it open;</line>
<line>Soft! it smells most sweetly in my sense.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>A delicate odour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>As ever hit my nostril. So, up with it.</line>
<line>O you most potent gods! what's here? a corse!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Most strange!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Shrouded in cloth of state; balm'd and entreasured</line>
<line>With full bags of spices! A passport too!</line>
<line>Apollo, perfect me in the characters!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Reads from a scroll</para>
<line>'Here I give to understand,</line>
<line>If e'er this coffin drive a-land,</line>
<line>I, King Pericles, have lost</line>
<line>This queen, worth all our mundane cost.</line>
<line>Who finds her, give her burying;</line>
<line>She was the daughter of a king:</line>
<line>Besides this treasure for a fee,</line>
<line>The gods requite his charity!'</line>
<line>If thou livest, Pericles, thou hast a heart</line>
<line>That even cracks for woe! This chanced tonight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Most likely, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Nay, certainly to-night;</line>
<line>For look how fresh she looks! They were too rough</line>
<line>That threw her in the sea. Make a fire within:</line>
<line>Fetch hither all my boxes in my closet.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit a Servant</para>
<line>Death may usurp on nature many hours,</line>
<line>And yet the fire of life kindle again</line>
<line>The o'erpress'd spirits. I heard of an Egyptian</line>
<line>That had nine hours lien dead,</line>
<line>Who was by good appliance recovered.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter a Servant, with boxes, napkins, and fire</para>
<line>Well said, well said; the fire and cloths.</line>
<line>The rough and woeful music that we have,</line>
<line>Cause it to sound, beseech you.</line>
<line>The viol once more: how thou stirr'st, thou block!</line>
<line>The music there!--I pray you, give her air.</line>
<line>Gentlemen.</line>
<line>This queen will live: nature awakes; a warmth</line>
<line>Breathes out of her: she hath not been entranced</line>
<line>Above five hours: see how she gins to blow</line>
<line>Into life's flower again!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>The heavens,</line>
<line>Through you, increase our wonder and set up</line>
<line>Your fame forever.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>She is alive; behold,</line>
<line>Her eyelids, cases to those heavenly jewels</line>
<line>Which Pericles hath lost,</line>
<line>Begin to part their fringes of bright gold;</line>
<line>The diamonds of a most praised water</line>
<line>Do appear, to make the world twice rich. Live,</line>
<line>And make us weep to hear your fate, fair creature,</line>
<line>Rare as you seem to be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">She moves</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>O dear Diana,</line>
<line>Where am I? Where's my lord? What world is this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Is not this strange?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Most rare.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Hush, my gentle neighbours!</line>
<line>Lend me your hands; to the next chamber bear her.</line>
<line>Get linen: now this matter must be look'd to,</line>
<line>For her relapse is mortal. Come, come;</line>
<line>And AEsculapius guide us!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt, carrying her away</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Tarsus. A room in CLEON's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES, CLEON, DIONYZA, and LYCHORIDA with
MARINA in her arms</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Most honour'd Cleon, I must needs be gone;</line>
<line>My twelve months are expired, and Tyrus stands</line>
<line>In a litigious peace. You, and your lady,</line>
<line>Take from my heart all thankfulness! The gods</line>
<line>Make up the rest upon you!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Your shafts of fortune, though they hurt you mortally,</line>
<line>Yet glance full wanderingly on us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>O your sweet queen!</line>
<line>That the strict fates had pleased you had brought her hither,</line>
<line>To have bless'd mine eyes with her!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>We cannot but obey</line>
<line>The powers above us. Could I rage and roar</line>
<line>As doth the sea she lies in, yet the end</line>
<line>Must be as 'tis. My gentle babe Marina, whom,</line>
<line>For she was born at sea, I have named so, here</line>
<line>I charge your charity withal, leaving her</line>
<line>The infant of your care; beseeching you</line>
<line>To give her princely training, that she may be</line>
<line>Manner'd as she is born.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Fear not, my lord, but think</line>
<line>Your grace, that fed my country with your corn,</line>
<line>For which the people's prayers still fall upon you,</line>
<line>Must in your child be thought on. If neglection</line>
<line>Should therein make me vile, the common body,</line>
<line>By you relieved, would force me to my duty:</line>
<line>But if to that my nature need a spur,</line>
<line>The gods revenge it upon me and mine,</line>
<line>To the end of generation!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I believe you;</line>
<line>Your honour and your goodness teach me to't,</line>
<line>Without your vows. Till she be married, madam,</line>
<line>By bright Diana, whom we honour, all</line>
<line>Unscissor'd shall this hair of mine remain,</line>
<line>Though I show ill in't. So I take my leave.</line>
<line>Good madam, make me blessed in your care</line>
<line>In bringing up my child.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>I have one myself,</line>
<line>Who shall not be more dear to my respect</line>
<line>Than yours, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Madam, my thanks and prayers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>We'll bring your grace e'en to the edge o' the shore,</line>
<line>Then give you up to the mask'd Neptune and</line>
<line>The gentlest winds of heaven.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I will embrace</line>
<line>Your offer. Come, dearest madam. O, no tears,</line>
<line>Lychorida, no tears:</line>
<line>Look to your little mistress, on whose grace</line>
<line>You may depend hereafter. Come, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  Ephesus. A room in CERIMON's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CERIMON and THAISA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Madam, this letter, and some certain jewels,</line>
<line>Lay with you in your coffer: which are now</line>
<line>At your command. Know you the character?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>It is my lord's.</line>
<line>That I was shipp'd at sea, I well remember,</line>
<line>Even on my eaning time; but whether there</line>
<line>Deliver'd, by the holy gods,</line>
<line>I cannot rightly say. But since King Pericles,</line>
<line>My wedded lord, I ne'er shall see again,</line>
<line>A vestal livery will I take me to,</line>
<line>And never more have joy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Madam, if this you purpose as ye speak,</line>
<line>Diana's temple is not distant far,</line>
<line>Where you may abide till your date expire.</line>
<line>Moreover, if you please, a niece of mine</line>
<line>Shall there attend you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>My recompense is thanks, that's all;</line>
<line>Yet my good will is great, though the gift small.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT IV</title>

<section role="prologue"><title>[Prologue]</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>Imagine Pericles arrived at Tyre,</line>
<line>Welcomed and settled to his own desire.</line>
<line>His woeful queen we leave at Ephesus,</line>
<line>Unto Diana there a votaress.</line>
<line>Now to Marina bend your mind,</line>
<line>Whom our fast-growing scene must find</line>
<line>At Tarsus, and by Cleon train'd</line>
<line>In music, letters; who hath gain'd</line>
<line>Of education all the grace,</line>
<line>Which makes her both the heart and place</line>
<line>Of general wonder. But, alack,</line>
<line>That monster envy, oft the wrack</line>
<line>Of earned praise, Marina's life</line>
<line>Seeks to take off by treason's knife.</line>
<line>And in this kind hath our Cleon</line>
<line>One daughter, and a wench full grown,</line>
<line>Even ripe for marriage-rite; this maid</line>
<line>Hight Philoten: and it is said</line>
<line>For certain in our story, she</line>
<line>Would ever with Marina be:</line>
<line>Be't when she weaved the sleided silk</line>
<line>With fingers long, small, white as milk;</line>
<line>Or when she would with sharp needle wound</line>
<line>The cambric, which she made more sound</line>
<line>By hurting it; or when to the lute</line>
<line>She sung, and made the night-bird mute,</line>
<line>That still records with moan; or when</line>
<line>She would with rich and constant pen</line>
<line>Vail to her mistress Dian; still</line>
<line>This Philoten contends in skill</line>
<line>With absolute Marina: so</line>
<line>With the dove of Paphos might the crow</line>
<line>Vie feathers white. Marina gets</line>
<line>All praises, which are paid as debts,</line>
<line>And not as given. This so darks</line>
<line>In Philoten all graceful marks,</line>
<line>That Cleon's wife, with envy rare,</line>
<line>A present murderer does prepare</line>
<line>For good Marina, that her daughter</line>
<line>Might stand peerless by this slaughter.</line>
<line>The sooner her vile thoughts to stead,</line>
<line>Lychorida, our nurse, is dead:</line>
<line>And cursed Dionyza hath</line>
<line>The pregnant instrument of wrath</line>
<line>Prest for this blow. The unborn event</line>
<line>I do commend to your content:</line>
<line>Only I carry winged time</line>
<line>Post on the lame feet of my rhyme;</line>
<line>Which never could I so convey,</line>
<line>Unless your thoughts went on my way.</line>
<line>Dionyza does appear,</line>
<line>With Leonine, a murderer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Tarsus. An open place near the sea-shore.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DIONYZA and LEONINE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Thy oath remember; thou hast sworn to do't:</line>
<line>'Tis but a blow, which never shall be known.</line>
<line>Thou canst not do a thing in the world so soon,</line>
<line>To yield thee so much profit. Let not conscience,</line>
<line>Which is but cold, inflaming love i' thy bosom,</line>
<line>Inflame too nicely; nor let pity, which</line>
<line>Even women have cast off, melt thee, but be</line>
<line>A soldier to thy purpose.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>I will do't; but yet she is a goodly creature.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>The fitter, then, the gods should have her. Here</line>
<line>she comes weeping for her only mistress' death.</line>
<line>Thou art resolved?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>I am resolved.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter MARINA, with a basket of flowers</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>No, I will rob Tellus of her weed,</line>
<line>To strew thy green with flowers: the yellows, blues,</line>
<line>The purple violets, and marigolds,</line>
<line>Shall as a carpet hang upon thy grave,</line>
<line>While summer-days do last. Ay me! poor maid,</line>
<line>Born in a tempest, when my mother died,</line>
<line>This world to me is like a lasting storm,</line>
<line>Whirring me from my friends.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>How now, Marina! why do you keep alone?</line>
<line>How chance my daughter is not with you? Do not</line>
<line>Consume your blood with sorrowing: you have</line>
<line>A nurse of me. Lord, how your favour's changed</line>
<line>With this unprofitable woe!</line>
<line>Come, give me your flowers, ere the sea mar it.</line>
<line>Walk with Leonine; the air is quick there,</line>
<line>And it pierces and sharpens the stomach. Come,</line>
<line>Leonine, take her by the arm, walk with her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>No, I pray you;</line>
<line>I'll not bereave you of your servant.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Come, come;</line>
<line>I love the king your father, and yourself,</line>
<line>With more than foreign heart. We every day</line>
<line>Expect him here: when he shall come and find</line>
<line>Our paragon to all reports thus blasted,</line>
<line>He will repent the breadth of his great voyage;</line>
<line>Blame both my lord and me, that we have taken</line>
<line>No care to your best courses. Go, I pray you,</line>
<line>Walk, and be cheerful once again; reserve</line>
<line>That excellent complexion, which did steal</line>
<line>The eyes of young and old. Care not for me</line>
<line>I can go home alone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Well, I will go;</line>
<line>But yet I have no desire to it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Come, come, I know 'tis good for you.</line>
<line>Walk half an hour, Leonine, at the least:</line>
<line>Remember what I have said.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>I warrant you, madam.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>I'll leave you, my sweet lady, for a while:</line>
<line>Pray, walk softly, do not heat your blood:</line>
<line>What! I must have a care of you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>My thanks, sweet madam.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit DIONYZA</para>
<line>Is this wind westerly that blows?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>South-west.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>When I was born, the wind was north.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>Was't so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>My father, as nurse said, did never fear,</line>
<line>But cried 'Good seaman!' to the sailors, galling</line>
<line>His kingly hands, haling ropes;</line>
<line>And, clasping to the mast, endured a sea</line>
<line>That almost burst the deck.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>When was this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>When I was born:</line>
<line>Never was waves nor wind more violent;</line>
<line>And from the ladder-tackle washes off</line>
<line>A canvas-climber. 'Ha!' says one, 'wilt out?'</line>
<line>And with a dropping industry they skip</line>
<line>From stem to stern: the boatswain whistles, and</line>
<line>The master calls, and trebles their confusion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>Come, say your prayers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>What mean you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>If you require a little space for prayer,</line>
<line>I grant it: pray; but be not tedious,</line>
<line>For the gods are quick of ear, and I am sworn</line>
<line>To do my work with haste.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Why will you kill me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>To satisfy my lady.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Why would she have me kill'd?</line>
<line>Now, as I can remember, by my troth,</line>
<line>I never did her hurt in all my life:</line>
<line>I never spake bad word, nor did ill turn</line>
<line>To any living creature: believe me, la,</line>
<line>I never kill'd a mouse, nor hurt a fly:</line>
<line>I trod upon a worm against my will,</line>
<line>But I wept for it. How have I offended,</line>
<line>Wherein my death might yield her any profit,</line>
<line>Or my life imply her any danger?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>My commission</line>
<line>Is not to reason of the deed, but do it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>You will not do't for all the world, I hope.</line>
<line>You are well favour'd, and your looks foreshow</line>
<line>You have a gentle heart. I saw you lately,</line>
<line>When you caught hurt in parting two that fought:</line>
<line>Good sooth, it show'd well in you: do so now:</line>
<line>Your lady seeks my life; come you between,</line>
<line>And save poor me, the weaker.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>I am sworn,</line>
<line>And will dispatch.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">He seizes her</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Pirates</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Pirate</speaker>
<line>Hold, villain!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">LEONINE runs away</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Pirate</speaker>
<line>A prize! a prize!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Pirate</speaker>
<line>Half-part, mates, half-part.</line>
<line>Come, let's have her aboard suddenly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Pirates with MARINA</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter LEONINE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LEONINE</speaker>
<line>These roguing thieves serve the great pirate Valdes;</line>
<line>And they have seized Marina. Let her go:</line>
<line>There's no hope she will return. I'll swear</line>
<line>she's dead,</line>
<line>And thrown into the sea. But I'll see further:</line>
<line>Perhaps they will but please themselves upon her,</line>
<line>Not carry her aboard. If she remain,</line>
<line>Whom they have ravish'd must by me be slain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  Mytilene. A room in a brothel.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Pandar, Bawd, and BOULT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Boult!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Search the market narrowly; Mytilene is full of</line>
<line>gallants. We lost too much money this mart by being</line>
<line>too wenchless.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>We were never so much out of creatures. We have but</line>
<line>poor three, and they can do no more than they can</line>
<line>do; and they with continual action are even as good as rotten.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Therefore let's have fresh ones, whate'er we pay for</line>
<line>them. If there be not a conscience to be used in</line>
<line>every trade, we shall never prosper.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Thou sayest true: 'tis not our bringing up of poor</line>
<line>bastards,--as, I think, I have brought up some eleven--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Ay, to eleven; and brought them down again. But</line>
<line>shall I search the market?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>What else, man? The stuff we have, a strong wind</line>
<line>will blow it to pieces, they are so pitifully sodden.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Thou sayest true; they're too unwholesome, o'</line>
<line>conscience. The poor Transylvanian is dead, that</line>
<line>lay with the little baggage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Ay, she quickly pooped him; she made him roast-meat</line>
<line>for worms. But I'll go search the market.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Three or four thousand chequins were as pretty a</line>
<line>proportion to live quietly, and so give over.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Why to give over, I pray you? is it a shame to get</line>
<line>when we are old?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>O, our credit comes not in like the commodity, nor</line>
<line>the commodity wages not with the danger: therefore,</line>
<line>if in our youths we could pick up some pretty</line>
<line>estate, 'twere not amiss to keep our door hatched.</line>
<line>Besides, the sore terms we stand upon with the gods</line>
<line>will be strong with us for giving over.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Come, other sorts offend as well as we.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>As well as we! ay, and better too; we offend worse.</line>
<line>Neither is our profession any trade; it's no</line>
<line>calling. But here comes Boult.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter BOULT, with the Pirates and MARINA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To MARINA</phrase>  Come your ways. My masters, you say</line>
<line>she's a virgin?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Pirate</speaker>
<line>O, sir, we doubt it not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Master, I have gone through for this piece, you see:</line>
<line>if you like her, so; if not, I have lost my earnest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Boult, has she any qualities?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>She has a good face, speaks well, and has excellent</line>
<line>good clothes: there's no further necessity of</line>
<line>qualities can make her be refused.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>What's her price, Boult?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I cannot be bated one doit of a thousand pieces.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Well, follow me, my masters, you shall have your</line>
<line>money presently. Wife, take her in; instruct her</line>
<line>what she has to do, that she may not be raw in her</line>
<line>entertainment.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Pandar and Pirates</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Boult, take you the marks of her, the colour of her</line>
<line>hair, complexion, height, age, with warrant of her</line>
<line>virginity; and cry 'He that will give most shall</line>
<line>have her first.' Such a maidenhead were no cheap</line>
<line>thing, if men were as they have been. Get this done</line>
<line>as I command you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Performance shall follow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Alack that Leonine was so slack, so slow!</line>
<line>He should have struck, not spoke; or that these pirates,</line>
<line>Not enough barbarous, had not o'erboard thrown me</line>
<line>For to seek my mother!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Why lament you, pretty one?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>That I am pretty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Come, the gods have done their part in you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>I accuse them not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>You are light into my hands, where you are like to live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>The more my fault</line>
<line>To scape his hands where I was like to die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Ay, and you shall live in pleasure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Yes, indeed shall you, and taste gentlemen of all</line>
<line>fashions: you shall fare well; you shall have the</line>
<line>difference of all complexions. What! do you stop your ears?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Are you a woman?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>What would you have me be, an I be not a woman?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>An honest woman, or not a woman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Marry, whip thee, gosling: I think I shall have</line>
<line>something to do with you. Come, you're a young</line>
<line>foolish sapling, and must be bowed as I would have</line>
<line>you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>The gods defend me!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>If it please the gods to defend you by men, then men</line>
<line>must comfort you, men must feed you, men must stir</line>
<line>you up. Boult's returned.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter BOULT</para>
<line>Now, sir, hast thou cried her through the market?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I have cried her almost to the number of her hairs;</line>
<line>I have drawn her picture with my voice.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>And I prithee tell me, how dost thou find the</line>
<line>inclination of the people, especially of the younger sort?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>'Faith, they listened to me as they would have</line>
<line>hearkened to their father's testament. There was a</line>
<line>Spaniard's mouth so watered, that he went to bed to</line>
<line>her very description.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>We shall have him here to-morrow with his best ruff on.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>To-night, to-night. But, mistress, do you know the</line>
<line>French knight that cowers i' the hams?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Who, Monsieur Veroles?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Ay, he: he offered to cut a caper at the</line>
<line>proclamation; but he made a groan at it, and swore</line>
<line>he would see her to-morrow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Well, well; as for him, he brought his disease</line>
<line>hither: here he does but repair it. I know he will</line>
<line>come in our shadow, to scatter his crowns in the</line>
<line>sun.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Well, if we had of every nation a traveller, we</line>
<line>should lodge them with this sign.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To MARINA</phrase>  Pray you, come hither awhile. You</line>
<line>have fortunes coming upon you. Mark me: you must</line>
<line>seem to do that fearfully which you commit</line>
<line>willingly, despise profit where you have most gain.</line>
<line>To weep that you live as ye do makes pity in your</line>
<line>lovers: seldom but that pity begets you a good</line>
<line>opinion, and that opinion a mere profit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>I understand you not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>O, take her home, mistress, take her home: these</line>
<line>blushes of hers must be quenched with some present practise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Thou sayest true, i' faith, so they must; for your</line>
<line>bride goes to that with shame which is her way to go</line>
<line>with warrant.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>'Faith, some do, and some do not. But, mistress, if</line>
<line>I have bargained for the joint,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Thou mayst cut a morsel off the spit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I may so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Who should deny it? Come, young one, I like the</line>
<line>manner of your garments well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Ay, by my faith, they shall not be changed yet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Boult, spend thou that in the town: report what a</line>
<line>sojourner we have; you'll lose nothing by custom.</line>
<line>When nature flamed this piece, she meant thee a good</line>
<line>turn; therefore say what a paragon she is, and thou</line>
<line>hast the harvest out of thine own report.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I warrant you, mistress, thunder shall not so awake</line>
<line>the beds of eels as my giving out her beauty stir up</line>
<line>the lewdly-inclined. I'll bring home some to-night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Come your ways; follow me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>If fires be hot, knives sharp, or waters deep,</line>
<line>Untied I still my virgin knot will keep.</line>
<line>Diana, aid my purpose!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>What have we to do with Diana? Pray you, will you go with us?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Tarsus. A room in CLEON's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter CLEON and DIONYZA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Why, are you foolish? Can it be undone?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>O Dionyza, such a piece of slaughter</line>
<line>The sun and moon ne'er look'd upon!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>I think</line>
<line>You'll turn a child again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Were I chief lord of all this spacious world,</line>
<line>I'ld give it to undo the deed. O lady,</line>
<line>Much less in blood than virtue, yet a princess</line>
<line>To equal any single crown o' the earth</line>
<line>I' the justice of compare! O villain Leonine!</line>
<line>Whom thou hast poison'd too:</line>
<line>If thou hadst drunk to him, 't had been a kindness</line>
<line>Becoming well thy fact: what canst thou say</line>
<line>When noble Pericles shall demand his child?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>That she is dead. Nurses are not the fates,</line>
<line>To foster it, nor ever to preserve.</line>
<line>She died at night; I'll say so. Who can cross it?</line>
<line>Unless you play the pious innocent,</line>
<line>And for an honest attribute cry out</line>
<line>'She died by foul play.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>O, go to. Well, well,</line>
<line>Of all the faults beneath the heavens, the gods</line>
<line>Do like this worst.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Be one of those that think</line>
<line>The petty wrens of Tarsus will fly hence,</line>
<line>And open this to Pericles. I do shame</line>
<line>To think of what a noble strain you are,</line>
<line>And of how coward a spirit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>To such proceeding</line>
<line>Who ever but his approbation added,</line>
<line>Though not his prime consent, he did not flow</line>
<line>From honourable sources.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>Be it so, then:</line>
<line>Yet none does know, but you, how she came dead,</line>
<line>Nor none can know, Leonine being gone.</line>
<line>She did disdain my child, and stood between</line>
<line>Her and her fortunes: none would look on her,</line>
<line>But cast their gazes on Marina's face;</line>
<line>Whilst ours was blurted at and held a malkin</line>
<line>Not worth the time of day. It pierced me through;</line>
<line>And though you call my course unnatural,</line>
<line>You not your child well loving, yet I find</line>
<line>It greets me as an enterprise of kindness</line>
<line>Perform'd to your sole daughter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Heavens forgive it!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>And as for Pericles,</line>
<line>What should he say? We wept after her hearse,</line>
<line>And yet we mourn: her monument</line>
<line>Is almost finish'd, and her epitaphs</line>
<line>In glittering golden characters express</line>
<line>A general praise to her, and care in us</line>
<line>At whose expense 'tis done.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CLEON</speaker>
<line>Thou art like the harpy,</line>
<line>Which, to betray, dost, with thine angel's face,</line>
<line>Seize with thine eagle's talons.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIONYZA</speaker>
<line>You are like one that superstitiously</line>
<line>Doth swear to the gods that winter kills the flies:</line>
<line>But yet I know you'll do as I advise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV</title>

<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER, before the monument of MARINA at Tarsus</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>Thus time we waste, and longest leagues make short;</line>
<line>Sail seas in cockles, have an wish but for't;</line>
<line>Making, to take your imagination,</line>
<line>From bourn to bourn, region to region.</line>
<line>By you being pardon'd, we commit no crime</line>
<line>To use one language in each several clime</line>
<line>Where our scenes seem to live. I do beseech you</line>
<line>To learn of me, who stand i' the gaps to teach you,</line>
<line>The stages of our story. Pericles</line>
<line>Is now again thwarting the wayward seas,</line>
<line>Attended on by many a lord and knight.</line>
<line>To see his daughter, all his life's delight.</line>
<line>Old Escanes, whom Helicanus late</line>
<line>Advanced in time to great and high estate,</line>
<line>Is left to govern. Bear you it in mind,</line>
<line>Old Helicanus goes along behind.</line>
<line>Well-sailing ships and bounteous winds have brought</line>
<line>This king to Tarsus,--think his pilot thought;</line>
<line>So with his steerage shall your thoughts grow on,--</line>
<line>To fetch his daughter home, who first is gone.</line>
<line>Like motes and shadows see them move awhile;</line>
<line>Your ears unto your eyes I'll reconcile.</line>
<bridgehead role="subhead">DUMB SHOW.</bridgehead>
<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES, at one door, with all his train;
CLEON and DIONYZA, at the other. CLEON shows
PERICLES the tomb; whereat PERICLES makes
lamentation, puts on sackcloth, and in a mighty
passion departs. Then exeunt CLEON and DIONYZA</para>
<line>See how belief may suffer by foul show!</line>
<line>This borrow'd passion stands for true old woe;</line>
<line>And Pericles, in sorrow all devour'd,</line>
<line>With sighs shot through, and biggest tears</line>
<line>o'ershower'd,</line>
<line>Leaves Tarsus and again embarks. He swears</line>
<line>Never to wash his face, nor cut his hairs:</line>
<line>He puts on sackcloth, and to sea. He bears</line>
<line>A tempest, which his mortal vessel tears,</line>
<line>And yet he rides it out. Now please you wit.</line>
<line>The epitaph is for Marina writ</line>
<line>By wicked Dionyza.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Reads the inscription on MARINA's monument</para>
<line>'The fairest, sweet'st, and best lies here,</line>
<line>Who wither'd in her spring of year.</line>
<line>She was of Tyrus the king's daughter,</line>
<line>On whom foul death hath made this slaughter;</line>
<line>Marina was she call'd; and at her birth,</line>
<line>Thetis, being proud, swallow'd some part o' the earth:</line>
<line>Therefore the earth, fearing to be o'erflow'd,</line>
<line>Hath Thetis' birth-child on the heavens bestow'd:</line>
<line>Wherefore she does, and swears she'll never stint,</line>
<line>Make raging battery upon shores of flint.'</line>
<line>No visor does become black villany</line>
<line>So well as soft and tender flattery.</line>
<line>Let Pericles believe his daughter's dead,</line>
<line>And bear his courses to be ordered</line>
<line>By Lady Fortune; while our scene must play</line>
<line>His daughter's woe and heavy well-a-day</line>
<line>In her unholy service. Patience, then,</line>
<line>And think you now are all in Mytilene.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE V.  Mytilene. A street before the brothel.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter, from the brothel, two Gentlemen</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Did you ever hear the like?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>No, nor never shall do in such a place as this, she</line>
<line>being once gone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>But to have divinity preached there! did you ever</line>
<line>dream of such a thing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Gentleman</speaker>
<line>No, no. Come, I am for no more bawdy-houses:</line>
<line>shall's go hear the vestals sing?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>I'll do any thing now that is virtuous; but I</line>
<line>am out of the road of rutting for ever.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE VI.  The same. A room in the brothel.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Pandar, Bawd, and BOULT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Well, I had rather than twice the worth of her she</line>
<line>had ne'er come here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Fie, fie upon her! she's able to freeze the god</line>
<line>Priapus, and undo a whole generation. We must</line>
<line>either get her ravished, or be rid of her. When she</line>
<line>should do for clients her fitment, and do me the</line>
<line>kindness of our profession, she has me her quirks,</line>
<line>her reasons, her master reasons, her prayers, her</line>
<line>knees; that she would make a puritan of the devil,</line>
<line>if he should cheapen a kiss of her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>'Faith, I must ravish her, or she'll disfurnish us</line>
<line>of all our cavaliers, and make our swearers priests.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Pandar</speaker>
<line>Now, the pox upon her green-sickness for me!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>'Faith, there's no way to be rid on't but by the</line>
<line>way to the pox. Here comes the Lord Lysimachus disguised.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>We should have both lord and lown, if the peevish</line>
<line>baggage would but give way to customers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter LYSIMACHUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>How now! How a dozen of virginities?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Now, the gods to-bless your honour!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I am glad to see your honour in good health.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>You may so; 'tis the better for you that your</line>
<line>resorters stand upon sound legs. How now!</line>
<line>wholesome iniquity have you that a man may deal</line>
<line>withal, and defy the surgeon?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>We have here one, sir, if she would--but there never</line>
<line>came her like in Mytilene.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>If she'ld do the deed of darkness, thou wouldst say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Your honour knows what 'tis to say well enough.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Well, call forth, call forth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>For flesh and blood, sir, white and red, you shall</line>
<line>see a rose; and she were a rose indeed, if she had but--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>What, prithee?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>O, sir, I can be modest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>That dignifies the renown of a bawd, no less than it</line>
<line>gives a good report to a number to be chaste.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit BOULT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Here comes that which grows to the stalk; never</line>
<line>plucked yet, I can assure you.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter BOULT with MARINA</para>
<line>Is she not a fair creature?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>'Faith, she would serve after a long voyage at sea.</line>
<line>Well, there's for you: leave us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>I beseech your honour, give me leave: a word, and</line>
<line>I'll have done presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>I beseech you, do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To MARINA</phrase>  First, I would have you note, this is</line>
<line>an honourable man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>I desire to find him so, that I may worthily note him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Next, he's the governor of this country, and a man</line>
<line>whom I am bound to.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>If he govern the country, you are bound to him</line>
<line>indeed; but how honourable he is in that, I know not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Pray you, without any more virginal fencing, will</line>
<line>you use him kindly? He will line your apron with gold.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>What he will do graciously, I will thankfully receive.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Ha' you done?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>My lord, she's not paced yet: you must take some</line>
<line>pains to work her to your manage. Come, we will</line>
<line>leave his honour and her together. Go thy ways.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Bawd, Pandar, and BOULT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Now, pretty one, how long have you been at this trade?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>What trade, sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Why, I cannot name't but I shall offend.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>I cannot be offended with my trade. Please you to name it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>How long have you been of this profession?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>E'er since I can remember.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Did you go to 't so young? Were you a gamester at</line>
<line>five or at seven?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Earlier too, sir, if now I be one.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Why, the house you dwell in proclaims you to be a</line>
<line>creature of sale.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Do you know this house to be a place of such resort,</line>
<line>and will come into 't? I hear say you are of</line>
<line>honourable parts, and are the governor of this place.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Why, hath your principal made known unto you who I am?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Who is my principal?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Why, your herb-woman; she that sets seeds and roots</line>
<line>of shame and iniquity. O, you have heard something</line>
<line>of my power, and so stand aloof for more serious</line>
<line>wooing. But I protest to thee, pretty one, my</line>
<line>authority shall not see thee, or else look friendly</line>
<line>upon thee. Come, bring me to some private place:</line>
<line>come, come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>If you were born to honour, show it now;</line>
<line>If put upon you, make the judgment good</line>
<line>That thought you worthy of it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>How's this? how's this? Some more; be sage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>For me,</line>
<line>That am a maid, though most ungentle fortune</line>
<line>Have placed me in this sty, where, since I came,</line>
<line>Diseases have been sold dearer than physic,</line>
<line>O, that the gods</line>
<line>Would set me free from this unhallow'd place,</line>
<line>Though they did change me to the meanest bird</line>
<line>That flies i' the purer air!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>I did not think</line>
<line>Thou couldst have spoke so well; ne'er dream'd thou couldst.</line>
<line>Had I brought hither a corrupted mind,</line>
<line>Thy speech had alter'd it. Hold, here's gold for thee:</line>
<line>Persever in that clear way thou goest,</line>
<line>And the gods strengthen thee!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>The good gods preserve you!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>For me, be you thoughten</line>
<line>That I came with no ill intent; for to me</line>
<line>The very doors and windows savour vilely.</line>
<line>Fare thee well. Thou art a piece of virtue, and</line>
<line>I doubt not but thy training hath been noble.</line>
<line>Hold, here's more gold for thee.</line>
<line>A curse upon him, die he like a thief,</line>
<line>That robs thee of thy goodness! If thou dost</line>
<line>Hear from me, it shall be for thy good.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter BOULT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I beseech your honour, one piece for me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Avaunt, thou damned door-keeper!</line>
<line>Your house, but for this virgin that doth prop it,</line>
<line>Would sink and overwhelm you. Away!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>How's this? We must take another course with you.</line>
<line>If your peevish chastity, which is not worth a</line>
<line>breakfast in the cheapest country under the cope,</line>
<line>shall undo a whole household, let me be gelded like</line>
<line>a spaniel. Come your ways.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Whither would you have me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>I must have your maidenhead taken off, or the common</line>
<line>hangman shall execute it. Come your ways. We'll</line>
<line>have no more gentlemen driven away. Come your ways, I say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter Bawd</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>How now! what's the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Worse and worse, mistress; she has here spoken holy</line>
<line>words to the Lord Lysimachus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>O abominable!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>She makes our profession as it were to stink afore</line>
<line>the face of the gods.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Marry, hang her up for ever!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>The nobleman would have dealt with her like a</line>
<line>nobleman, and she sent him away as cold as a</line>
<line>snowball; saying his prayers too.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>Boult, take her away; use her at thy pleasure:</line>
<line>crack the glass of her virginity, and make the rest malleable.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>An if she were a thornier piece of ground than she</line>
<line>is, she shall be ploughed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Hark, hark, you gods!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Bawd</speaker>
<line>She conjures: away with her! Would she had never</line>
<line>come within my doors! Marry, hang you! She's born</line>
<line>to undo us. Will you not go the way of women-kind?</line>
<line>Marry, come up, my dish of chastity with rosemary and bays!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Come, mistress; come your ways with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Whither wilt thou have me?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>To take from you the jewel you hold so dear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Prithee, tell me one thing first.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Come now, your one thing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>What canst thou wish thine enemy to be?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Why, I could wish him to be my master, or rather, my mistress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Neither of these are so bad as thou art,</line>
<line>Since they do better thee in their command.</line>
<line>Thou hold'st a place, for which the pained'st fiend</line>
<line>Of hell would not in reputation change:</line>
<line>Thou art the damned doorkeeper to every</line>
<line>Coistrel that comes inquiring for his Tib;</line>
<line>To the choleric fisting of every rogue</line>
<line>Thy ear is liable; thy food is such</line>
<line>As hath been belch'd on by infected lungs.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>What would you have me do? go to the wars, would</line>
<line>you? where a man may serve seven years for the loss</line>
<line>of a leg, and have not money enough in the end to</line>
<line>buy him a wooden one?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Do any thing but this thou doest. Empty</line>
<line>Old receptacles, or common shores, of filth;</line>
<line>Serve by indenture to the common hangman:</line>
<line>Any of these ways are yet better than this;</line>
<line>For what thou professest, a baboon, could he speak,</line>
<line>Would own a name too dear. O, that the gods</line>
<line>Would safely deliver me from this place!</line>
<line>Here, here's gold for thee.</line>
<line>If that thy master would gain by thee,</line>
<line>Proclaim that I can sing, weave, sew, and dance,</line>
<line>With other virtues, which I'll keep from boast:</line>
<line>And I will undertake all these to teach.</line>
<line>I doubt not but this populous city will</line>
<line>Yield many scholars.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>But can you teach all this you speak of?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Prove that I cannot, take me home again,</line>
<line>And prostitute me to the basest groom</line>
<line>That doth frequent your house.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>Well, I will see what I can do for thee: if I can</line>
<line>place thee, I will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>But amongst honest women.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BOULT</speaker>
<line>'Faith, my acquaintance lies little amongst them.</line>
<line>But since my master and mistress have bought you,</line>
<line>there's no going but by their consent: therefore I</line>
<line>will make them acquainted with your purpose, and I</line>
<line>doubt not but I shall find them tractable enough.</line>
<line>Come, I'll do for thee what I can; come your ways.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT V</title>

<section role="prologue"><title>[Prologue]</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>Marina thus the brothel 'scapes, and chances</line>
<line>Into an honest house, our story says.</line>
<line>She sings like one immortal, and she dances</line>
<line>As goddess-like to her admired lays;</line>
<line>Deep clerks she dumbs; and with her needle composes</line>
<line>Nature's own shape, of bud, bird, branch, or berry,</line>
<line>That even her art sisters the natural roses;</line>
<line>Her inkle, silk, twin with the rubied cherry:</line>
<line>That pupils lacks she none of noble race,</line>
<line>Who pour their bounty on her; and her gain</line>
<line>She gives the cursed bawd. Here we her place;</line>
<line>And to her father turn our thoughts again,</line>
<line>Where we left him, on the sea. We there him lost;</line>
<line>Whence, driven before the winds, he is arrived</line>
<line>Here where his daughter dwells; and on this coast</line>
<line>Suppose him now at anchor. The city strived</line>
<line>God Neptune's annual feast to keep: from whence</line>
<line>Lysimachus our Tyrian ship espies,</line>
<line>His banners sable, trimm'd with rich expense;</line>
<line>And to him in his barge with fervor hies.</line>
<line>In your supposing once more put your sight</line>
<line>Of heavy Pericles; think this his bark:</line>
<line>Where what is done in action, more, if might,</line>
<line>Shall be discover'd; please you, sit and hark.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>
<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  On board PERICLES' ship, off Mytilene. A close pavilion on deck, with a curtain before it; PERICLES within it, reclined on a couch. A barge lying beside the Tyrian vessel.</title>

<para role="stagedir">Enter two Sailors, one belonging to the Tyrian
vessel, the other to the barge; to them HELICANUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Tyrian Sailor</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To the Sailor of Mytilene</phrase>  Where is lord Helicanus?</line>
<line>he can resolve you.</line>
<line>O, here he is.</line>
<line>Sir, there's a barge put off from Mytilene,</line>
<line>And in it is Lysimachus the governor,</line>
<line>Who craves to come aboard. What is your will?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>That he have his. Call up some gentlemen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Tyrian Sailor</speaker>
<line>Ho, gentlemen! my lord calls.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter two or three Gentlemen</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Gentleman</speaker>
<line>Doth your lordship call?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Gentlemen, there's some of worth would come aboard;</line>
<line>I pray ye, greet them fairly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The Gentlemen and the two Sailors descend, and go
on board the barge</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter, from thence, LYSIMACHUS and Lords; with the
Gentlemen and the two Sailors</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Tyrian Sailor</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>This is the man that can, in aught you would,</line>
<line>Resolve you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Hail, reverend sir! the gods preserve you!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>And you, sir, to outlive the age I am,</line>
<line>And die as I would do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>You wish me well.</line>
<line>Being on shore, honouring of Neptune's triumphs,</line>
<line>Seeing this goodly vessel ride before us,</line>
<line>I made to it, to know of whence you are.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>First, what is your place?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>I am the governor of this place you lie before.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>Our vessel is of Tyre, in it the king;</line>
<line>A man who for this three months hath not spoken</line>
<line>To any one, nor taken sustenance</line>
<line>But to prorogue his grief.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Upon what ground is his distemperature?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>'Twould be too tedious to repeat;</line>
<line>But the main grief springs from the loss</line>
<line>Of a beloved daughter and a wife.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>May we not see him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>You may;</line>
<line>But bootless is your sight: he will not speak To any.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Yet let me obtain my wish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Behold him.</line>
<para role="stagedir">PERICLES discovered</para>
<line>This was a goodly person,</line>
<line>Till the disaster that, one mortal night,</line>
<line>Drove him to this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Sir king, all hail! the gods preserve you!</line>
<line>Hail, royal sir!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>It is in vain; he will not speak to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Lord</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>We have a maid in Mytilene, I durst wager,</line>
<line>Would win some words of him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>'Tis well bethought.</line>
<line>She questionless with her sweet harmony</line>
<line>And other chosen attractions, would allure,</line>
<line>And make a battery through his deafen'd parts,</line>
<line>Which now are midway stopp'd:</line>
<line>She is all happy as the fairest of all,</line>
<line>And, with her fellow maids is now upon</line>
<line>The leafy shelter that abuts against</line>
<line>The island's side.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Whispers a Lord, who goes off in the barge of
LYSIMACHUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Sure, all's effectless; yet nothing we'll omit</line>
<line>That bears recovery's name. But, since your kindness</line>
<line>We have stretch'd thus far, let us beseech you</line>
<line>That for our gold we may provision have,</line>
<line>Wherein we are not destitute for want,</line>
<line>But weary for the staleness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>O, sir, a courtesy</line>
<line>Which if we should deny, the most just gods</line>
<line>For every graff would send a caterpillar,</line>
<line>And so afflict our province. Yet once more</line>
<line>Let me entreat to know at large the cause</line>
<line>Of your king's sorrow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Sit, sir, I will recount it to you:</line>
<line>But, see, I am prevented.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter, from the barge, Lord, with MARINA, and a
young Lady</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>O, here is</line>
<line>The lady that I sent for. Welcome, fair one!</line>
<line>Is't not a goodly presence?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>She's a gallant lady.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>She's such a one, that, were I well assured</line>
<line>Came of a gentle kind and noble stock,</line>
<line>I'ld wish no better choice, and think me rarely wed.</line>
<line>Fair one, all goodness that consists in bounty</line>
<line>Expect even here, where is a kingly patient:</line>
<line>If that thy prosperous and artificial feat</line>
<line>Can draw him but to answer thee in aught,</line>
<line>Thy sacred physic shall receive such pay</line>
<line>As thy desires can wish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Sir, I will use</line>
<line>My utmost skill in his recovery, Provided</line>
<line>That none but I and my companion maid</line>
<line>Be suffer'd to come near him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Come, let us leave her;</line>
<line>And the gods make her prosperous!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">MARINA sings</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Mark'd he your music?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>No, nor look'd on us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>See, she will speak to him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Hail, sir! my lord, lend ear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Hum, ha!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>I am a maid,</line>
<line>My lord, that ne'er before invited eyes,</line>
<line>But have been gazed on like a comet: she speaks,</line>
<line>My lord, that, may be, hath endured a grief</line>
<line>Might equal yours, if both were justly weigh'd.</line>
<line>Though wayward fortune did malign my state,</line>
<line>My derivation was from ancestors</line>
<line>Who stood equivalent with mighty kings:</line>
<line>But time hath rooted out my parentage,</line>
<line>And to the world and awkward casualties</line>
<line>Bound me in servitude.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>I will desist;</line>
<line>But there is something glows upon my cheek,</line>
<line>And whispers in mine ear, 'Go not till he speak.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>My fortunes--parentage--good parentage--</line>
<line>To equal mine!--was it not thus? what say you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>I said, my lord, if you did know my parentage,</line>
<line>You would not do me violence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I do think so. Pray you, turn your eyes upon me.</line>
<line>You are like something that--What country-woman?</line>
<line>Here of these shores?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>No, nor of any shores:</line>
<line>Yet I was mortally brought forth, and am</line>
<line>No other than I appear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I am great with woe, and shall deliver weeping.</line>
<line>My dearest wife was like this maid, and such a one</line>
<line>My daughter might have been: my queen's square brows;</line>
<line>Her stature to an inch; as wand-like straight;</line>
<line>As silver-voiced; her eyes as jewel-like</line>
<line>And cased as richly; in pace another Juno;</line>
<line>Who starves the ears she feeds, and makes them hungry,</line>
<line>The more she gives them speech. Where do you live?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Where I am but a stranger: from the deck</line>
<line>You may discern the place.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Where were you bred?</line>
<line>And how achieved you these endowments, which</line>
<line>You make more rich to owe?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>If I should tell my history, it would seem</line>
<line>Like lies disdain'd in the reporting.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Prithee, speak:</line>
<line>Falseness cannot come from thee; for thou look'st</line>
<line>Modest as Justice, and thou seem'st a palace</line>
<line>For the crown'd Truth to dwell in: I will</line>
<line>believe thee,</line>
<line>And make my senses credit thy relation</line>
<line>To points that seem impossible; for thou look'st</line>
<line>Like one I loved indeed. What were thy friends?</line>
<line>Didst thou not say, when I did push thee back--</line>
<line>Which was when I perceived thee--that thou camest</line>
<line>From good descending?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>So indeed I did.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Report thy parentage. I think thou said'st</line>
<line>Thou hadst been toss'd from wrong to injury,</line>
<line>And that thou thought'st thy griefs might equal mine,</line>
<line>If both were open'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Some such thing</line>
<line>I said, and said no more but what my thoughts</line>
<line>Did warrant me was likely.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Tell thy story;</line>
<line>If thine consider'd prove the thousandth part</line>
<line>Of my endurance, thou art a man, and I</line>
<line>Have suffer'd like a girl: yet thou dost look</line>
<line>Like Patience gazing on kings' graves, and smiling</line>
<line>Extremity out of act. What were thy friends?</line>
<line>How lost thou them? Thy name, my most kind virgin?</line>
<line>Recount, I do beseech thee: come, sit by me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>My name is Marina.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>O, I am mock'd,</line>
<line>And thou by some incensed god sent hither</line>
<line>To make the world to laugh at me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Patience, good sir,</line>
<line>Or here I'll cease.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Nay, I'll be patient.</line>
<line>Thou little know'st how thou dost startle me,</line>
<line>To call thyself Marina.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>The name</line>
<line>Was given me by one that had some power,</line>
<line>My father, and a king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>How! a king's daughter?</line>
<line>And call'd Marina?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>You said you would believe me;</line>
<line>But, not to be a troubler of your peace,</line>
<line>I will end here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>But are you flesh and blood?</line>
<line>Have you a working pulse? and are no fairy?</line>
<line>Motion! Well; speak on. Where were you born?</line>
<line>And wherefore call'd Marina?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Call'd Marina</line>
<line>For I was born at sea.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>At sea! what mother?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>My mother was the daughter of a king;</line>
<line>Who died the minute I was born,</line>
<line>As my good nurse Lychorida hath oft</line>
<line>Deliver'd weeping.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>O, stop there a little!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>This is the rarest dream that e'er dull sleep</line>
<line>Did mock sad fools withal: this cannot be:</line>
<line>My daughter's buried. Well: where were you bred?</line>
<line>I'll hear you more, to the bottom of your story,</line>
<line>And never interrupt you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>You scorn: believe me, 'twere best I did give o'er.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I will believe you by the syllable</line>
<line>Of what you shall deliver. Yet, give me leave:</line>
<line>How came you in these parts? where were you bred?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>The king my father did in Tarsus leave me;</line>
<line>Till cruel Cleon, with his wicked wife,</line>
<line>Did seek to murder me: and having woo'd</line>
<line>A villain to attempt it, who having drawn to do't,</line>
<line>A crew of pirates came and rescued me;</line>
<line>Brought me to Mytilene. But, good sir,</line>
<line>Whither will you have me? Why do you weep?</line>
<line>It may be,</line>
<line>You think me an impostor: no, good faith;</line>
<line>I am the daughter to King Pericles,</line>
<line>If good King Pericles be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Ho, Helicanus!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Calls my lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Thou art a grave and noble counsellor,</line>
<line>Most wise in general: tell me, if thou canst,</line>
<line>What this maid is, or what is like to be,</line>
<line>That thus hath made me weep?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>I know not; but</line>
<line>Here is the regent, sir, of Mytilene</line>
<line>Speaks nobly of her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>She would never tell</line>
<line>Her parentage; being demanded that,</line>
<line>She would sit still and weep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>O Helicanus, strike me, honour'd sir;</line>
<line>Give me a gash, put me to present pain;</line>
<line>Lest this great sea of joys rushing upon me</line>
<line>O'erbear the shores of my mortality,</line>
<line>And drown me with their sweetness. O, come hither,</line>
<line>Thou that beget'st him that did thee beget;</line>
<line>Thou that wast born at sea, buried at Tarsus,</line>
<line>And found at sea again! O Helicanus,</line>
<line>Down on thy knees, thank the holy gods as loud</line>
<line>As thunder threatens us: this is Marina.</line>
<line>What was thy mother's name? tell me but that,</line>
<line>For truth can never be confirm'd enough,</line>
<line>Though doubts did ever sleep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>First, sir, I pray,</line>
<line>What is your title?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I am Pericles of Tyre: but tell me now</line>
<line>My drown'd queen's name, as in the rest you said</line>
<line>Thou hast been godlike perfect,</line>
<line>The heir of kingdoms and another like</line>
<line>To Pericles thy father.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>Is it no more to be your daughter than</line>
<line>To say my mother's name was Thaisa?</line>
<line>Thaisa was my mother, who did end</line>
<line>The minute I began.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Now, blessing on thee! rise; thou art my child.</line>
<line>Give me fresh garments. Mine own, Helicanus;</line>
<line>She is not dead at Tarsus, as she should have been,</line>
<line>By savage Cleon: she shall tell thee all;</line>
<line>When thou shalt kneel, and justify in knowledge</line>
<line>She is thy very princess. Who is this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Sir, 'tis the governor of Mytilene,</line>
<line>Who, hearing of your melancholy state,</line>
<line>Did come to see you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>I embrace you.</line>
<line>Give me my robes. I am wild in my beholding.</line>
<line>O heavens bless my girl! But, hark, what music?</line>
<line>Tell Helicanus, my Marina, tell him</line>
<line>O'er, point by point, for yet he seems to doubt,</line>
<line>How sure you are my daughter. But, what music?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, I hear none.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>None!</line>
<line>The music of the spheres! List, my Marina.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>It is not good to cross him; give him way.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Rarest sounds! Do ye not hear?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, I hear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Music</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Most heavenly music!</line>
<line>It nips me unto listening, and thick slumber</line>
<line>Hangs upon mine eyes: let me rest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Sleeps</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>A pillow for his head:</line>
<line>So, leave him all. Well, my companion friends,</line>
<line>If this but answer to my just belief,</line>
<line>I'll well remember you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all but PERICLES</para>
<para role="stagedir">DIANA appears to PERICLES as in a vision</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DIANA</speaker>
<line>My temple stands in Ephesus: hie thee thither,</line>
<line>And do upon mine altar sacrifice.</line>
<line>There, when my maiden priests are met together,</line>
<line>Before the people all,</line>
<line>Reveal how thou at sea didst lose thy wife:</line>
<line>To mourn thy crosses, with thy daughter's, call</line>
<line>And give them repetition to the life.</line>
<line>Or perform my bidding, or thou livest in woe;</line>
<line>Do it, and happy; by my silver bow!</line>
<line>Awake, and tell thy dream.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Disappears</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Celestial Dian, goddess argentine,</line>
<line>I will obey thee. Helicanus!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter HELICANUS, LYSIMACHUS, and MARINA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Sir?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>My purpose was for Tarsus, there to strike</line>
<line>The inhospitable Cleon; but I am</line>
<line>For other service first: toward Ephesus</line>
<line>Turn our blown sails; eftsoons I'll tell thee why.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To LYSIMACHUS</para>
<line>Shall we refresh us, sir, upon your shore,</line>
<line>And give you gold for such provision</line>
<line>As our intents will need?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Sir,</line>
<line>With all my heart; and, when you come ashore,</line>
<line>I have another suit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>You shall prevail,</line>
<line>Were it to woo my daughter; for it seems</line>
<line>You have been noble towards her.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LYSIMACHUS</speaker>
<line>Sir, lend me your arm.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Come, my Marina.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER, before the temple of DIANA at Ephesus</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>Now our sands are almost run;</line>
<line>More a little, and then dumb.</line>
<line>This, my last boon, give me,</line>
<line>For such kindness must relieve me,</line>
<line>That you aptly will suppose</line>
<line>What pageantry, what feats, what shows,</line>
<line>What minstrelsy, and pretty din,</line>
<line>The regent made in Mytilene</line>
<line>To greet the king. So he thrived,</line>
<line>That he is promised to be wived</line>
<line>To fair Marina; but in no wise</line>
<line>Till he had done his sacrifice,</line>
<line>As Dian bade: whereto being bound,</line>
<line>The interim, pray you, all confound.</line>
<line>In feather'd briefness sails are fill'd,</line>
<line>And wishes fall out as they're will'd.</line>
<line>At Ephesus, the temple see,</line>
<line>Our king and all his company.</line>
<line>That he can hither come so soon,</line>
<line>Is by your fancy's thankful doom.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The temple of Diana at Ephesus; THAISA standing near the altar, as high priestess; a number of Virgins on each side; CERIMON and other Inhabitants of Ephesus attending.</title>

<para role="stagedir">Enter PERICLES, with his train; LYSIMACHUS,
HELICANUS, MARINA, and a Lady</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Hail, Dian! to perform thy just command,</line>
<line>I here confess myself the king of Tyre;</line>
<line>Who, frighted from my country, did wed</line>
<line>At Pentapolis the fair Thaisa.</line>
<line>At sea in childbed died she, but brought forth</line>
<line>A maid-child call'd Marina; who, O goddess,</line>
<line>Wears yet thy silver livery. She at Tarsus</line>
<line>Was nursed with Cleon; who at fourteen years</line>
<line>He sought to murder: but her better stars</line>
<line>Brought her to Mytilene; 'gainst whose shore</line>
<line>Riding, her fortunes brought the maid aboard us,</line>
<line>Where, by her own most clear remembrance, she</line>
<line>Made known herself my daughter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Voice and favour!</line>
<line>You are, you are--O royal Pericles!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Faints</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>What means the nun? she dies! help, gentlemen!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Noble sir,</line>
<line>If you have told Diana's altar true,</line>
<line>This is your wife.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Reverend appearer, no;</line>
<line>I threw her overboard with these very arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Upon this coast, I warrant you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>'Tis most certain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Look to the lady; O, she's but o'erjoy'd.</line>
<line>Early in blustering morn this lady was</line>
<line>Thrown upon this shore. I oped the coffin,</line>
<line>Found there rich jewels; recover'd her, and placed her</line>
<line>Here in Diana's temple.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>May we see them?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>Great sir, they shall be brought you to my house,</line>
<line>Whither I invite you. Look, Thaisa is recovered.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>O, let me look!</line>
<line>If he be none of mine, my sanctity</line>
<line>Will to my sense bend no licentious ear,</line>
<line>But curb it, spite of seeing. O, my lord,</line>
<line>Are you not Pericles? Like him you spake,</line>
<line>Like him you are: did you not name a tempest,</line>
<line>A birth, and death?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>The voice of dead Thaisa!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>That Thaisa am I, supposed dead</line>
<line>And drown'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Immortal Dian!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Now I know you better.</line>
<line>When we with tears parted Pentapolis,</line>
<line>The king my father gave you such a ring.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Shows a ring</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>This, this: no more, you gods! your present kindness</line>
<line>Makes my past miseries sports: you shall do well,</line>
<line>That on the touching of her lips I may</line>
<line>Melt and no more be seen. O, come, be buried</line>
<line>A second time within these arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARINA</speaker>
<line>My heart</line>
<line>Leaps to be gone into my mother's bosom.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Kneels to THAISA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Look, who kneels here! Flesh of thy flesh, Thaisa;</line>
<line>Thy burden at the sea, and call'd Marina</line>
<line>For she was yielded there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Blest, and mine own!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HELICANUS</speaker>
<line>Hail, madam, and my queen!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>I know you not.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>You have heard me say, when I did fly from Tyre,</line>
<line>I left behind an ancient substitute:</line>
<line>Can you remember what I call'd the man?</line>
<line>I have named him oft.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>'Twas Helicanus then.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Still confirmation:</line>
<line>Embrace him, dear Thaisa; this is he.</line>
<line>Now do I long to hear how you were found;</line>
<line>How possibly preserved; and who to thank,</line>
<line>Besides the gods, for this great miracle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Lord Cerimon, my lord; this man,</line>
<line>Through whom the gods have shown their power; that can</line>
<line>From first to last resolve you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Reverend sir,</line>
<line>The gods can have no mortal officer</line>
<line>More like a god than you. Will you deliver</line>
<line>How this dead queen re-lives?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CERIMON</speaker>
<line>I will, my lord.</line>
<line>Beseech you, first go with me to my house,</line>
<line>Where shall be shown you all was found with her;</line>
<line>How she came placed here in the temple;</line>
<line>No needful thing omitted.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Pure Dian, bless thee for thy vision! I</line>
<line>Will offer night-oblations to thee. Thaisa,</line>
<line>This prince, the fair-betrothed of your daughter,</line>
<line>Shall marry her at Pentapolis. And now,</line>
<line>This ornament</line>
<line>Makes me look dismal will I clip to form;</line>
<line>And what this fourteen years no razor touch'd,</line>
<line>To grace thy marriage-day, I'll beautify.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THAISA</speaker>
<line>Lord Cerimon hath letters of good credit, sir,</line>
<line>My father's dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PERICLES</speaker>
<line>Heavens make a star of him! Yet there, my queen,</line>
<line>We'll celebrate their nuptials, and ourselves</line>
<line>Will in that kingdom spend our following days:</line>
<line>Our son and daughter shall in Tyrus reign.</line>
<line>Lord Cerimon, we do our longing stay</line>
<line>To hear the rest untold: sir, lead's the way.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>

<para role="stagedir">Enter GOWER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GOWER</speaker>
<line>In Antiochus and his daughter you have heard</line>
<line>Of monstrous lust the due and just reward:</line>
<line>In Pericles, his queen and daughter, seen,</line>
<line>Although assail'd with fortune fierce and keen,</line>
<line>Virtue preserved from fell destruction's blast,</line>
<line>Led on by heaven, and crown'd with joy at last:</line>
<line>In Helicanus may you well descry</line>
<line>A figure of truth, of faith, of loyalty:</line>
<line>In reverend Cerimon there well appears</line>
<line>The worth that learned charity aye wears:</line>
<line>For wicked Cleon and his wife, when fame</line>
<line>Had spread their cursed deed, and honour'd name</line>
<line>Of Pericles, to rage the city turn,</line>
<line>That him and his they in his palace burn;</line>
<line>The gods for murder seemed so content</line>
<line>To punish them; although not done, but meant.</line>
<line>So, on your patience evermore attending,</line>
<line>New joy wait on you! Here our play has ending.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>