<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="publishers.rnc" type="compact"?><book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" role="play">
<title>The Tragedy of King Richard the Second</title>

<info><author><personname><firstname>William</firstname><surname>Shakespeare</surname></personname></author><legalnotice>
<para>ASCII text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</para>
<para>SGML markup by Jon Bosak, 1992-1994.</para>
<para>XML version by Jon Bosak, 1996-1999.</para>
<para>The XML markup in this version is Copyright © 1999 Jon Bosak.
This work may freely be distributed on condition that it not be
modified or altered in any way.</para>
</legalnotice>     <copyright><year>2008</year><holder>Scott Hudson</holder></copyright></info>

<preface>
<title>Dramatis Personae</title>

<para><personname role="persona">KING RICHARD, the Second. </personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">JOHN OF GAUNT, Duke of Lancaster	</personname><personname role="persona">EDMUND OF LANGLEY, Duke of York  </personname></member><member>uncles to the King.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">HENRY, surnamed BOLINGBROKE, Duke of Hereford</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">son to John of Gaunt; afterwards King Henry IV.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DUKE OF AUMERLE, son to the Duke of York.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">THOMAS MOWBRAY, Duke of Norfolk.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DUKE OF SURREY</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">EARL OF SALISBURY</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LORD BERKELEY</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">BUSHY</personname><personname role="persona">BAGOT</personname><personname role="persona">GREEN</personname></member><member>servants to King Richard.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">EARL OF NORTHUMBERLAND</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">HENRY PERCY, surnamed HOTSPUR, his son. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LORD ROSS</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LORD WILLOUGHBY</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LORD FITZWATER</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Abbot Of Westminster</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LORD MARSHAL</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">SIR PIERCE OF EXTON</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Captain of a band of Welshmen. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">QUEEN to King Richard</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DUCHESS OF YORK</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">DUCHESS OF GLOUCESTER</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Lady attending on the Queen. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Lords, Heralds, Officers, Soldiers, two Gardeners, Keeper, Messenger, Groom, and other Attendants. </personname></para>
</preface>

<para role="scndescr">SCENE  England and Wales.</para>



<chapter role="act"><title>ACT I</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  London. KING RICHARD II's palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING RICHARD II, JOHN OF GAUNT, with other
Nobles and Attendants</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Old John of Gaunt, time-honour'd Lancaster,</line>
<line>Hast thou, according to thy oath and band,</line>
<line>Brought hither Henry Hereford thy bold son,</line>
<line>Here to make good the boisterous late appeal,</line>
<line>Which then our leisure would not let us hear,</line>
<line>Against the Duke of Norfolk, Thomas Mowbray?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>I have, my liege.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Tell me, moreover, hast thou sounded him,</line>
<line>If he appeal the duke on ancient malice;</line>
<line>Or worthily, as a good subject should,</line>
<line>On some known ground of treachery in him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>As near as I could sift him on that argument,</line>
<line>On some apparent danger seen in him</line>
<line>Aim'd at your highness, no inveterate malice.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Then call them to our presence; face to face,</line>
<line>And frowning brow to brow, ourselves will hear</line>
<line>The accuser and the accused freely speak:</line>
<line>High-stomach'd are they both, and full of ire,</line>
<line>In rage deaf as the sea, hasty as fire.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE and THOMAS MOWBRAY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Many years of happy days befal</line>
<line>My gracious sovereign, my most loving liege!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>Each day still better other's happiness;</line>
<line>Until the heavens, envying earth's good hap,</line>
<line>Add an immortal title to your crown!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We thank you both: yet one but flatters us,</line>
<line>As well appeareth by the cause you come;</line>
<line>Namely to appeal each other of high treason.</line>
<line>Cousin of Hereford, what dost thou object</line>
<line>Against the Duke of Norfolk, Thomas Mowbray?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>First, heaven be the record to my speech!</line>
<line>In the devotion of a subject's love,</line>
<line>Tendering the precious safety of my prince,</line>
<line>And free from other misbegotten hate,</line>
<line>Come I appellant to this princely presence.</line>
<line>Now, Thomas Mowbray, do I turn to thee,</line>
<line>And mark my greeting well; for what I speak</line>
<line>My body shall make good upon this earth,</line>
<line>Or my divine soul answer it in heaven.</line>
<line>Thou art a traitor and a miscreant,</line>
<line>Too good to be so and too bad to live,</line>
<line>Since the more fair and crystal is the sky,</line>
<line>The uglier seem the clouds that in it fly.</line>
<line>Once more, the more to aggravate the note,</line>
<line>With a foul traitor's name stuff I thy throat;</line>
<line>And wish, so please my sovereign, ere I move,</line>
<line>What my tongue speaks my right drawn sword may prove.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>Let not my cold words here accuse my zeal:</line>
<line>'Tis not the trial of a woman's war,</line>
<line>The bitter clamour of two eager tongues,</line>
<line>Can arbitrate this cause betwixt us twain;</line>
<line>The blood is hot that must be cool'd for this:</line>
<line>Yet can I not of such tame patience boast</line>
<line>As to be hush'd and nought at all to say:</line>
<line>First, the fair reverence of your highness curbs me</line>
<line>From giving reins and spurs to my free speech;</line>
<line>Which else would post until it had return'd</line>
<line>These terms of treason doubled down his throat.</line>
<line>Setting aside his high blood's royalty,</line>
<line>And let him be no kinsman to my liege,</line>
<line>I do defy him, and I spit at him;</line>
<line>Call him a slanderous coward and a villain:</line>
<line>Which to maintain I would allow him odds,</line>
<line>And meet him, were I tied to run afoot</line>
<line>Even to the frozen ridges of the Alps,</line>
<line>Or any other ground inhabitable,</line>
<line>Where ever Englishman durst set his foot.</line>
<line>Mean time let this defend my loyalty,</line>
<line>By all my hopes, most falsely doth he lie.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Pale trembling coward, there I throw my gage,</line>
<line>Disclaiming here the kindred of the king,</line>
<line>And lay aside my high blood's royalty,</line>
<line>Which fear, not reverence, makes thee to except.</line>
<line>If guilty dread have left thee so much strength</line>
<line>As to take up mine honour's pawn, then stoop:</line>
<line>By that and all the rites of knighthood else,</line>
<line>Will I make good against thee, arm to arm,</line>
<line>What I have spoke, or thou canst worse devise.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>I take it up; and by that sword I swear</line>
<line>Which gently laid my knighthood on my shoulder,</line>
<line>I'll answer thee in any fair degree,</line>
<line>Or chivalrous design of knightly trial:</line>
<line>And when I mount, alive may I not light,</line>
<line>If I be traitor or unjustly fight!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>What doth our cousin lay to Mowbray's charge?</line>
<line>It must be great that can inherit us</line>
<line>So much as of a thought of ill in him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Look, what I speak, my life shall prove it true;</line>
<line>That Mowbray hath received eight thousand nobles</line>
<line>In name of lendings for your highness' soldiers,</line>
<line>The which he hath detain'd for lewd employments,</line>
<line>Like a false traitor and injurious villain.</line>
<line>Besides I say and will in battle prove,</line>
<line>Or here or elsewhere to the furthest verge</line>
<line>That ever was survey'd by English eye,</line>
<line>That all the treasons for these eighteen years</line>
<line>Complotted and contrived in this land</line>
<line>Fetch from false Mowbray their first head and spring.</line>
<line>Further I say and further will maintain</line>
<line>Upon his bad life to make all this good,</line>
<line>That he did plot the Duke of Gloucester's death,</line>
<line>Suggest his soon-believing adversaries,</line>
<line>And consequently, like a traitor coward,</line>
<line>Sluiced out his innocent soul through streams of blood:</line>
<line>Which blood, like sacrificing Abel's, cries,</line>
<line>Even from the tongueless caverns of the earth,</line>
<line>To me for justice and rough chastisement;</line>
<line>And, by the glorious worth of my descent,</line>
<line>This arm shall do it, or this life be spent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>How high a pitch his resolution soars!</line>
<line>Thomas of Norfolk, what say'st thou to this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>O, let my sovereign turn away his face</line>
<line>And bid his ears a little while be deaf,</line>
<line>Till I have told this slander of his blood,</line>
<line>How God and good men hate so foul a liar.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Mowbray, impartial are our eyes and ears:</line>
<line>Were he my brother, nay, my kingdom's heir,</line>
<line>As he is but my father's brother's son,</line>
<line>Now, by my sceptre's awe, I make a vow,</line>
<line>Such neighbour nearness to our sacred blood</line>
<line>Should nothing privilege him, nor partialize</line>
<line>The unstooping firmness of my upright soul:</line>
<line>He is our subject, Mowbray; so art thou:</line>
<line>Free speech and fearless I to thee allow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>Then, Bolingbroke, as low as to thy heart,</line>
<line>Through the false passage of thy throat, thou liest.</line>
<line>Three parts of that receipt I had for Calais</line>
<line>Disbursed I duly to his highness' soldiers;</line>
<line>The other part reserved I by consent,</line>
<line>For that my sovereign liege was in my debt</line>
<line>Upon remainder of a dear account,</line>
<line>Since last I went to France to fetch his queen:</line>
<line>Now swallow down that lie. For Gloucester's death,</line>
<line>I slew him not; but to my own disgrace</line>
<line>Neglected my sworn duty in that case.</line>
<line>For you, my noble Lord of Lancaster,</line>
<line>The honourable father to my foe</line>
<line>Once did I lay an ambush for your life,</line>
<line>A trespass that doth vex my grieved soul</line>
<line>But ere I last received the sacrament</line>
<line>I did confess it, and exactly begg'd</line>
<line>Your grace's pardon, and I hope I had it.</line>
<line>This is my fault: as for the rest appeall'd,</line>
<line>It issues from the rancour of a villain,</line>
<line>A recreant and most degenerate traitor</line>
<line>Which in myself I boldly will defend;</line>
<line>And interchangeably hurl down my gage</line>
<line>Upon this overweening traitor's foot,</line>
<line>To prove myself a loyal gentleman</line>
<line>Even in the best blood chamber'd in his bosom.</line>
<line>In haste whereof, most heartily I pray</line>
<line>Your highness to assign our trial day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Wrath-kindled gentlemen, be ruled by me;</line>
<line>Let's purge this choler without letting blood:</line>
<line>This we prescribe, though no physician;</line>
<line>Deep malice makes too deep incision;</line>
<line>Forget, forgive; conclude and be agreed;</line>
<line>Our doctors say this is no month to bleed.</line>
<line>Good uncle, let this end where it begun;</line>
<line>We'll calm the Duke of Norfolk, you your son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>To be a make-peace shall become my age:</line>
<line>Throw down, my son, the Duke of Norfolk's gage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>And, Norfolk, throw down his.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>When, Harry, when?</line>
<line>Obedience bids I should not bid again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Norfolk, throw down, we bid; there is no boot.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>Myself I throw, dread sovereign, at thy foot.</line>
<line>My life thou shalt command, but not my shame:</line>
<line>The one my duty owes; but my fair name,</line>
<line>Despite of death that lives upon my grave,</line>
<line>To dark dishonour's use thou shalt not have.</line>
<line>I am disgraced, impeach'd and baffled here,</line>
<line>Pierced to the soul with slander's venom'd spear,</line>
<line>The which no balm can cure but his heart-blood</line>
<line>Which breathed this poison.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Rage must be withstood:</line>
<line>Give me his gage: lions make leopards tame.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>Yea, but not change his spots: take but my shame.</line>
<line>And I resign my gage. My dear dear lord,</line>
<line>The purest treasure mortal times afford</line>
<line>Is spotless reputation: that away,</line>
<line>Men are but gilded loam or painted clay.</line>
<line>A jewel in a ten-times-barr'd-up chest</line>
<line>Is a bold spirit in a loyal breast.</line>
<line>Mine honour is my life; both grow in one:</line>
<line>Take honour from me, and my life is done:</line>
<line>Then, dear my liege, mine honour let me try;</line>
<line>In that I live and for that will I die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Cousin, throw up your gage; do you begin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>O, God defend my soul from such deep sin!</line>
<line>Shall I seem crest-fall'n in my father's sight?</line>
<line>Or with pale beggar-fear impeach my height</line>
<line>Before this out-dared dastard? Ere my tongue</line>
<line>Shall wound my honour with such feeble wrong,</line>
<line>Or sound so base a parle, my teeth shall tear</line>
<line>The slavish motive of recanting fear,</line>
<line>And spit it bleeding in his high disgrace,</line>
<line>Where shame doth harbour, even in Mowbray's face.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit JOHN OF GAUNT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We were not born to sue, but to command;</line>
<line>Which since we cannot do to make you friends,</line>
<line>Be ready, as your lives shall answer it,</line>
<line>At Coventry, upon Saint Lambert's day:</line>
<line>There shall your swords and lances arbitrate</line>
<line>The swelling difference of your settled hate:</line>
<line>Since we can not atone you, we shall see</line>
<line>Justice design the victor's chivalry.</line>
<line>Lord marshal, command our officers at arms</line>
<line>Be ready to direct these home alarms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The DUKE OF LANCASTER'S palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter JOHN OF GAUNT with DUCHESS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Alas, the part I had in Woodstock's blood</line>
<line>Doth more solicit me than your exclaims,</line>
<line>To stir against the butchers of his life!</line>
<line>But since correction lieth in those hands</line>
<line>Which made the fault that we cannot correct,</line>
<line>Put we our quarrel to the will of heaven;</line>
<line>Who, when they see the hours ripe on earth,</line>
<line>Will rain hot vengeance on offenders' heads.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS</speaker>
<line>Finds brotherhood in thee no sharper spur?</line>
<line>Hath love in thy old blood no living fire?</line>
<line>Edward's seven sons, whereof thyself art one,</line>
<line>Were as seven vials of his sacred blood,</line>
<line>Or seven fair branches springing from one root:</line>
<line>Some of those seven are dried by nature's course,</line>
<line>Some of those branches by the Destinies cut;</line>
<line>But Thomas, my dear lord, my life, my Gloucester,</line>
<line>One vial full of Edward's sacred blood,</line>
<line>One flourishing branch of his most royal root,</line>
<line>Is crack'd, and all the precious liquor spilt,</line>
<line>Is hack'd down, and his summer leaves all faded,</line>
<line>By envy's hand and murder's bloody axe.</line>
<line>Ah, Gaunt, his blood was thine! that bed, that womb,</line>
<line>That metal, that self-mould, that fashion'd thee</line>
<line>Made him a man; and though thou livest and breathest,</line>
<line>Yet art thou slain in him: thou dost consent</line>
<line>In some large measure to thy father's death,</line>
<line>In that thou seest thy wretched brother die,</line>
<line>Who was the model of thy father's life.</line>
<line>Call it not patience, Gaunt; it is despair:</line>
<line>In suffering thus thy brother to be slaughter'd,</line>
<line>Thou showest the naked pathway to thy life,</line>
<line>Teaching stern murder how to butcher thee:</line>
<line>That which in mean men we intitle patience</line>
<line>Is pale cold cowardice in noble breasts.</line>
<line>What shall I say? to safeguard thine own life,</line>
<line>The best way is to venge my Gloucester's death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>God's is the quarrel; for God's substitute,</line>
<line>His deputy anointed in His sight,</line>
<line>Hath caused his death: the which if wrongfully,</line>
<line>Let heaven revenge; for I may never lift</line>
<line>An angry arm against His minister.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS</speaker>
<line>Where then, alas, may I complain myself?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>To God, the widow's champion and defence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS</speaker>
<line>Why, then, I will. Farewell, old Gaunt.</line>
<line>Thou goest to Coventry, there to behold</line>
<line>Our cousin Hereford and fell Mowbray fight:</line>
<line>O, sit my husband's wrongs on Hereford's spear,</line>
<line>That it may enter butcher Mowbray's breast!</line>
<line>Or, if misfortune miss the first career,</line>
<line>Be Mowbray's sins so heavy in his bosom,</line>
<line>They may break his foaming courser's back,</line>
<line>And throw the rider headlong in the lists,</line>
<line>A caitiff recreant to my cousin Hereford!</line>
<line>Farewell, old Gaunt: thy sometimes brother's wife</line>
<line>With her companion grief must end her life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Sister, farewell; I must to Coventry:</line>
<line>As much good stay with thee as go with me!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS</speaker>
<line>Yet one word more: grief boundeth where it falls,</line>
<line>Not with the empty hollowness, but weight:</line>
<line>I take my leave before I have begun,</line>
<line>For sorrow ends not when it seemeth done.</line>
<line>Commend me to thy brother, Edmund York.</line>
<line>Lo, this is all:--nay, yet depart not so;</line>
<line>Though this be all, do not so quickly go;</line>
<line>I shall remember more. Bid him--ah, what?--</line>
<line>With all good speed at Plashy visit me.</line>
<line>Alack, and what shall good old York there see</line>
<line>But empty lodgings and unfurnish'd walls,</line>
<line>Unpeopled offices, untrodden stones?</line>
<line>And what hear there for welcome but my groans?</line>
<line>Therefore commend me; let him not come there,</line>
<line>To seek out sorrow that dwells every where.</line>
<line>Desolate, desolate, will I hence and die:</line>
<line>The last leave of thee takes my weeping eye.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The lists at Coventry.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter the Lord Marshal and the DUKE OF AUMERLE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>My Lord Aumerle, is Harry Hereford arm'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Yea, at all points; and longs to enter in.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>The Duke of Norfolk, sprightfully and bold,</line>
<line>Stays but the summons of the appellant's trumpet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Why, then, the champions are prepared, and stay</line>
<line>For nothing but his majesty's approach.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The trumpets sound, and KING RICHARD enters with
his nobles, JOHN OF GAUNT, BUSHY, BAGOT, GREEN, and
others. When they are set, enter THOMAS MOWBRAY in
arms, defendant, with a Herald</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Marshal, demand of yonder champion</line>
<line>The cause of his arrival here in arms:</line>
<line>Ask him his name and orderly proceed</line>
<line>To swear him in the justice of his cause.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>In God's name and the king's, say who thou art</line>
<line>And why thou comest thus knightly clad in arms,</line>
<line>Against what man thou comest, and what thy quarrel:</line>
<line>Speak truly, on thy knighthood and thy oath;</line>
<line>As so defend thee heaven and thy valour!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>My name is Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk;</line>
<line>Who hither come engaged by my oath--</line>
<line>Which God defend a knight should violate!--</line>
<line>Both to defend my loyalty and truth</line>
<line>To God, my king and my succeeding issue,</line>
<line>Against the Duke of Hereford that appeals me</line>
<line>And, by the grace of God and this mine arm,</line>
<line>To prove him, in defending of myself,</line>
<line>A traitor to my God, my king, and me:</line>
<line>And as I truly fight, defend me heaven!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">The trumpets sound. Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE,
appellant, in armour, with a Herald</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Marshal, ask yonder knight in arms,</line>
<line>Both who he is and why he cometh hither</line>
<line>Thus plated in habiliments of war,</line>
<line>And formally, according to our law,</line>
<line>Depose him in the justice of his cause.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>What is thy name? and wherefore comest thou hither,</line>
<line>Before King Richard in his royal lists?</line>
<line>Against whom comest thou? and what's thy quarrel?</line>
<line>Speak like a true knight, so defend thee heaven!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Harry of Hereford, Lancaster and Derby</line>
<line>Am I; who ready here do stand in arms,</line>
<line>To prove, by God's grace and my body's valour,</line>
<line>In lists, on Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk,</line>
<line>That he is a traitor, foul and dangerous,</line>
<line>To God of heaven, King Richard and to me;</line>
<line>And as I truly fight, defend me heaven!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>On pain of death, no person be so bold</line>
<line>Or daring-hardy as to touch the lists,</line>
<line>Except the marshal and such officers</line>
<line>Appointed to direct these fair designs.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Lord marshal, let me kiss my sovereign's hand,</line>
<line>And bow my knee before his majesty:</line>
<line>For Mowbray and myself are like two men</line>
<line>That vow a long and weary pilgrimage;</line>
<line>Then let us take a ceremonious leave</line>
<line>And loving farewell of our several friends.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>The appellant in all duty greets your highness,</line>
<line>And craves to kiss your hand and take his leave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We will descend and fold him in our arms.</line>
<line>Cousin of Hereford, as thy cause is right,</line>
<line>So be thy fortune in this royal fight!</line>
<line>Farewell, my blood; which if to-day thou shed,</line>
<line>Lament we may, but not revenge thee dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>O let no noble eye profane a tear</line>
<line>For me, if I be gored with Mowbray's spear:</line>
<line>As confident as is the falcon's flight</line>
<line>Against a bird, do I with Mowbray fight.</line>
<line>My loving lord, I take my leave of you;</line>
<line>Of you, my noble cousin, Lord Aumerle;</line>
<line>Not sick, although I have to do with death,</line>
<line>But lusty, young, and cheerly drawing breath.</line>
<line>Lo, as at English feasts, so I regreet</line>
<line>The daintiest last, to make the end most sweet:</line>
<line>O thou, the earthly author of my blood,</line>
<line>Whose youthful spirit, in me regenerate,</line>
<line>Doth with a twofold vigour lift me up</line>
<line>To reach at victory above my head,</line>
<line>Add proof unto mine armour with thy prayers;</line>
<line>And with thy blessings steel my lance's point,</line>
<line>That it may enter Mowbray's waxen coat,</line>
<line>And furbish new the name of John a Gaunt,</line>
<line>Even in the lusty havior of his son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>God in thy good cause make thee prosperous!</line>
<line>Be swift like lightning in the execution;</line>
<line>And let thy blows, doubly redoubled,</line>
<line>Fall like amazing thunder on the casque</line>
<line>Of thy adverse pernicious enemy:</line>
<line>Rouse up thy youthful blood, be valiant and live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Mine innocency and Saint George to thrive!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>However God or fortune cast my lot,</line>
<line>There lives or dies, true to King Richard's throne,</line>
<line>A loyal, just and upright gentleman:</line>
<line>Never did captive with a freer heart</line>
<line>Cast off his chains of bondage and embrace</line>
<line>His golden uncontroll'd enfranchisement,</line>
<line>More than my dancing soul doth celebrate</line>
<line>This feast of battle with mine adversary.</line>
<line>Most mighty liege, and my companion peers,</line>
<line>Take from my mouth the wish of happy years:</line>
<line>As gentle and as jocund as to jest</line>
<line>Go I to fight: truth hath a quiet breast.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Farewell, my lord: securely I espy</line>
<line>Virtue with valour couched in thine eye.</line>
<line>Order the trial, marshal, and begin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>Harry of Hereford, Lancaster and Derby,</line>
<line>Receive thy lance; and God defend the right!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Strong as a tower in hope, I cry amen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>Go bear this lance to Thomas, Duke of Norfolk.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Herald</speaker>
<line>Harry of Hereford, Lancaster and Derby,</line>
<line>Stands here for God, his sovereign and himself,</line>
<line>On pain to be found false and recreant,</line>
<line>To prove the Duke of Norfolk, Thomas Mowbray,</line>
<line>A traitor to his God, his king and him;</line>
<line>And dares him to set forward to the fight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Herald</speaker>
<line>Here standeth Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk,</line>
<line>On pain to be found false and recreant,</line>
<line>Both to defend himself and to approve</line>
<line>Henry of Hereford, Lancaster, and Derby,</line>
<line>To God, his sovereign and to him disloyal;</line>
<line>Courageously and with a free desire</line>
<line>Attending but the signal to begin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>Sound, trumpets; and set forward, combatants.</line>
<para role="stagedir">A charge sounded</para>
<line>Stay, the king hath thrown his warder down.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Let them lay by their helmets and their spears,</line>
<line>And both return back to their chairs again:</line>
<line>Withdraw with us: and let the trumpets sound</line>
<line>While we return these dukes what we decree.</line>
<para role="stagedir">A long flourish</para>
<line>Draw near,</line>
<line>And list what with our council we have done.</line>
<line>For that our kingdom's earth should not be soil'd</line>
<line>With that dear blood which it hath fostered;</line>
<line>And for our eyes do hate the dire aspect</line>
<line>Of civil wounds plough'd up with neighbours' sword;</line>
<line>And for we think the eagle-winged pride</line>
<line>Of sky-aspiring and ambitious thoughts,</line>
<line>With rival-hating envy, set on you</line>
<line>To wake our peace, which in our country's cradle</line>
<line>Draws the sweet infant breath of gentle sleep;</line>
<line>Which so roused up with boisterous untuned drums,</line>
<line>With harsh resounding trumpets' dreadful bray,</line>
<line>And grating shock of wrathful iron arms,</line>
<line>Might from our quiet confines fright fair peace</line>
<line>And make us wade even in our kindred's blood,</line>
<line>Therefore, we banish you our territories:</line>
<line>You, cousin Hereford, upon pain of life,</line>
<line>Till twice five summers have enrich'd our fields</line>
<line>Shall not regreet our fair dominions,</line>
<line>But tread the stranger paths of banishment.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Your will be done: this must my comfort be,</line>
<line>Sun that warms you here shall shine on me;</line>
<line>And those his golden beams to you here lent</line>
<line>Shall point on me and gild my banishment.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Norfolk, for thee remains a heavier doom,</line>
<line>Which I with some unwillingness pronounce:</line>
<line>The sly slow hours shall not determinate</line>
<line>The dateless limit of thy dear exile;</line>
<line>The hopeless word of 'never to return'</line>
<line>Breathe I against thee, upon pain of life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>A heavy sentence, my most sovereign liege,</line>
<line>And all unlook'd for from your highness' mouth:</line>
<line>A dearer merit, not so deep a maim</line>
<line>As to be cast forth in the common air,</line>
<line>Have I deserved at your highness' hands.</line>
<line>The language I have learn'd these forty years,</line>
<line>My native English, now I must forego:</line>
<line>And now my tongue's use is to me no more</line>
<line>Than an unstringed viol or a harp,</line>
<line>Or like a cunning instrument cased up,</line>
<line>Or, being open, put into his hands</line>
<line>That knows no touch to tune the harmony:</line>
<line>Within my mouth you have engaol'd my tongue,</line>
<line>Doubly portcullis'd with my teeth and lips;</line>
<line>And dull unfeeling barren ignorance</line>
<line>Is made my gaoler to attend on me.</line>
<line>I am too old to fawn upon a nurse,</line>
<line>Too far in years to be a pupil now:</line>
<line>What is thy sentence then but speechless death,</line>
<line>Which robs my tongue from breathing native breath?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>It boots thee not to be compassionate:</line>
<line>After our sentence plaining comes too late.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>Then thus I turn me from my country's light,</line>
<line>To dwell in solemn shades of endless night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Return again, and take an oath with thee.</line>
<line>Lay on our royal sword your banish'd hands;</line>
<line>Swear by the duty that you owe to God--</line>
<line>Our part therein we banish with yourselves--</line>
<line>To keep the oath that we administer:</line>
<line>You never shall, so help you truth and God!</line>
<line>Embrace each other's love in banishment;</line>
<line>Nor never look upon each other's face;</line>
<line>Nor never write, regreet, nor reconcile</line>
<line>This louring tempest of your home-bred hate;</line>
<line>Nor never by advised purpose meet</line>
<line>To plot, contrive, or complot any ill</line>
<line>'Gainst us, our state, our subjects, or our land.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I swear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>And I, to keep all this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Norfolk, so far as to mine enemy:--</line>
<line>By this time, had the king permitted us,</line>
<line>One of our souls had wander'd in the air.</line>
<line>Banish'd this frail sepulchre of our flesh,</line>
<line>As now our flesh is banish'd from this land:</line>
<line>Confess thy treasons ere thou fly the realm;</line>
<line>Since thou hast far to go, bear not along</line>
<line>The clogging burthen of a guilty soul.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
<line>No, Bolingbroke: if ever I were traitor,</line>
<line>My name be blotted from the book of life,</line>
<line>And I from heaven banish'd as from hence!</line>
<line>But what thou art, God, thou, and I do know;</line>
<line>And all too soon, I fear, the king shall rue.</line>
<line>Farewell, my liege. Now no way can I stray;</line>
<line>Save back to England, all the world's my way.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Uncle, even in the glasses of thine eyes</line>
<line>I see thy grieved heart: thy sad aspect</line>
<line>Hath from the number of his banish'd years</line>
<line>Pluck'd four away.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To HENRY BOLINGBROKE</para>
<line>Six frozen winter spent,</line>
<line>Return with welcome home from banishment.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>How long a time lies in one little word!</line>
<line>Four lagging winters and four wanton springs</line>
<line>End in a word: such is the breath of kings.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>I thank my liege, that in regard of me</line>
<line>He shortens four years of my son's exile:</line>
<line>But little vantage shall I reap thereby;</line>
<line>For, ere the six years that he hath to spend</line>
<line>Can change their moons and bring their times about</line>
<line>My oil-dried lamp and time-bewasted light</line>
<line>Shall be extinct with age and endless night;</line>
<line>My inch of taper will be burnt and done,</line>
<line>And blindfold death not let me see my son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Why uncle, thou hast many years to live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>But not a minute, king, that thou canst give:</line>
<line>Shorten my days thou canst with sullen sorrow,</line>
<line>And pluck nights from me, but not lend a morrow;</line>
<line>Thou canst help time to furrow me with age,</line>
<line>But stop no wrinkle in his pilgrimage;</line>
<line>Thy word is current with him for my death,</line>
<line>But dead, thy kingdom cannot buy my breath.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Thy son is banish'd upon good advice,</line>
<line>Whereto thy tongue a party-verdict gave:</line>
<line>Why at our justice seem'st thou then to lour?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Things sweet to taste prove in digestion sour.</line>
<line>You urged me as a judge; but I had rather</line>
<line>You would have bid me argue like a father.</line>
<line>O, had it been a stranger, not my child,</line>
<line>To smooth his fault I should have been more mild:</line>
<line>A partial slander sought I to avoid,</line>
<line>And in the sentence my own life destroy'd.</line>
<line>Alas, I look'd when some of you should say,</line>
<line>I was too strict to make mine own away;</line>
<line>But you gave leave to my unwilling tongue</line>
<line>Against my will to do myself this wrong.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Cousin, farewell; and, uncle, bid him so:</line>
<line>Six years we banish him, and he shall go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Exeunt KING RICHARD II and train</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Cousin, farewell: what presence must not know,</line>
<line>From where you do remain let paper show.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord Marshal</speaker>
<line>My lord, no leave take I; for I will ride,</line>
<line>As far as land will let me, by your side.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>O, to what purpose dost thou hoard thy words,</line>
<line>That thou return'st no greeting to thy friends?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I have too few to take my leave of you,</line>
<line>When the tongue's office should be prodigal</line>
<line>To breathe the abundant dolour of the heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Thy grief is but thy absence for a time.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Joy absent, grief is present for that time.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>What is six winters? they are quickly gone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>To men in joy; but grief makes one hour ten.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Call it a travel that thou takest for pleasure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>My heart will sigh when I miscall it so,</line>
<line>Which finds it an inforced pilgrimage.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>The sullen passage of thy weary steps</line>
<line>Esteem as foil wherein thou art to set</line>
<line>The precious jewel of thy home return.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Nay, rather, every tedious stride I make</line>
<line>Will but remember me what a deal of world</line>
<line>I wander from the jewels that I love.</line>
<line>Must I not serve a long apprenticehood</line>
<line>To foreign passages, and in the end,</line>
<line>Having my freedom, boast of nothing else</line>
<line>But that I was a journeyman to grief?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>All places that the eye of heaven visits</line>
<line>Are to a wise man ports and happy havens.</line>
<line>Teach thy necessity to reason thus;</line>
<line>There is no virtue like necessity.</line>
<line>Think not the king did banish thee,</line>
<line>But thou the king. Woe doth the heavier sit,</line>
<line>Where it perceives it is but faintly borne.</line>
<line>Go, say I sent thee forth to purchase honour</line>
<line>And not the king exiled thee; or suppose</line>
<line>Devouring pestilence hangs in our air</line>
<line>And thou art flying to a fresher clime:</line>
<line>Look, what thy soul holds dear, imagine it</line>
<line>To lie that way thou go'st, not whence thou comest:</line>
<line>Suppose the singing birds musicians,</line>
<line>The grass whereon thou tread'st the presence strew'd,</line>
<line>The flowers fair ladies, and thy steps no more</line>
<line>Than a delightful measure or a dance;</line>
<line>For gnarling sorrow hath less power to bite</line>
<line>The man that mocks at it and sets it light.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>O, who can hold a fire in his hand</line>
<line>By thinking on the frosty Caucasus?</line>
<line>Or cloy the hungry edge of appetite</line>
<line>By bare imagination of a feast?</line>
<line>Or wallow naked in December snow</line>
<line>By thinking on fantastic summer's heat?</line>
<line>O, no! the apprehension of the good</line>
<line>Gives but the greater feeling to the worse:</line>
<line>Fell sorrow's tooth doth never rankle more</line>
<line>Than when he bites, but lanceth not the sore.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Come, come, my son, I'll bring thee on thy way:</line>
<line>Had I thy youth and cause, I would not stay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Then, England's ground, farewell; sweet soil, adieu;</line>
<line>My mother, and my nurse, that bears me yet!</line>
<line>Where'er I wander, boast of this I can,</line>
<line>Though banish'd, yet a trueborn Englishman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The court.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING RICHARD II, with BAGOT and GREEN at one
door; and the DUKE OF AUMERLE at another</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We did observe. Cousin Aumerle,</line>
<line>How far brought you high Hereford on his way?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>I brought high Hereford, if you call him so,</line>
<line>But to the next highway, and there I left him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>And say, what store of parting tears were shed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Faith, none for me; except the north-east wind,</line>
<line>Which then blew bitterly against our faces,</line>
<line>Awaked the sleeping rheum, and so by chance</line>
<line>Did grace our hollow parting with a tear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>What said our cousin when you parted with him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>'Farewell:'</line>
<line>And, for my heart disdained that my tongue</line>
<line>Should so profane the word, that taught me craft</line>
<line>To counterfeit oppression of such grief</line>
<line>That words seem'd buried in my sorrow's grave.</line>
<line>Marry, would the word 'farewell' have lengthen'd hours</line>
<line>And added years to his short banishment,</line>
<line>He should have had a volume of farewells;</line>
<line>But since it would not, he had none of me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>He is our cousin, cousin; but 'tis doubt,</line>
<line>When time shall call him home from banishment,</line>
<line>Whether our kinsman come to see his friends.</line>
<line>Ourself and Bushy, Bagot here and Green</line>
<line>Observed his courtship to the common people;</line>
<line>How he did seem to dive into their hearts</line>
<line>With humble and familiar courtesy,</line>
<line>What reverence he did throw away on slaves,</line>
<line>Wooing poor craftsmen with the craft of smiles</line>
<line>And patient underbearing of his fortune,</line>
<line>As 'twere to banish their affects with him.</line>
<line>Off goes his bonnet to an oyster-wench;</line>
<line>A brace of draymen bid God speed him well</line>
<line>And had the tribute of his supple knee,</line>
<line>With 'Thanks, my countrymen, my loving friends;'</line>
<line>As were our England in reversion his,</line>
<line>And he our subjects' next degree in hope.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>Well, he is gone; and with him go these thoughts.</line>
<line>Now for the rebels which stand out in Ireland,</line>
<line>Expedient manage must be made, my liege,</line>
<line>Ere further leisure yield them further means</line>
<line>For their advantage and your highness' loss.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We will ourself in person to this war:</line>
<line>And, for our coffers, with too great a court</line>
<line>And liberal largess, are grown somewhat light,</line>
<line>We are inforced to farm our royal realm;</line>
<line>The revenue whereof shall furnish us</line>
<line>For our affairs in hand: if that come short,</line>
<line>Our substitutes at home shall have blank charters;</line>
<line>Whereto, when they shall know what men are rich,</line>
<line>They shall subscribe them for large sums of gold</line>
<line>And send them after to supply our wants;</line>
<line>For we will make for Ireland presently.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter BUSHY</para>
<line>Bushy, what news?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Old John of Gaunt is grievous sick, my lord,</line>
<line>Suddenly taken; and hath sent post haste</line>
<line>To entreat your majesty to visit him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Where lies he?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>At Ely House.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Now put it, God, in the physician's mind</line>
<line>To help him to his grave immediately!</line>
<line>The lining of his coffers shall make coats</line>
<line>To deck our soldiers for these Irish wars.</line>
<line>Come, gentlemen, let's all go visit him:</line>
<line>Pray God we may make haste, and come too late!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All</speaker>
<line>Amen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT II</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Ely House.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter JOHN OF GAUNT sick, with the DUKE OF YORK,
&amp;c</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Will the king come, that I may breathe my last</line>
<line>In wholesome counsel to his unstaid youth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Vex not yourself, nor strive not with your breath;</line>
<line>For all in vain comes counsel to his ear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>O, but they say the tongues of dying men</line>
<line>Enforce attention like deep harmony:</line>
<line>Where words are scarce, they are seldom spent in vain,</line>
<line>For they breathe truth that breathe their words in pain.</line>
<line>He that no more must say is listen'd more</line>
<line>Than they whom youth and ease have taught to glose;</line>
<line>More are men's ends mark'd than their lives before:</line>
<line>The setting sun, and music at the close,</line>
<line>As the last taste of sweets, is sweetest last,</line>
<line>Writ in remembrance more than things long past:</line>
<line>Though Richard my life's counsel would not hear,</line>
<line>My death's sad tale may yet undeaf his ear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>No; it is stopp'd with other flattering sounds,</line>
<line>As praises, of whose taste the wise are fond,</line>
<line>Lascivious metres, to whose venom sound</line>
<line>The open ear of youth doth always listen;</line>
<line>Report of fashions in proud Italy,</line>
<line>Whose manners still our tardy apish nation</line>
<line>Limps after in base imitation.</line>
<line>Where doth the world thrust forth a vanity--</line>
<line>So it be new, there's no respect how vile--</line>
<line>That is not quickly buzzed into his ears?</line>
<line>Then all too late comes counsel to be heard,</line>
<line>Where will doth mutiny with wit's regard.</line>
<line>Direct not him whose way himself will choose:</line>
<line>'Tis breath thou lack'st, and that breath wilt thou lose.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Methinks I am a prophet new inspired</line>
<line>And thus expiring do foretell of him:</line>
<line>His rash fierce blaze of riot cannot last,</line>
<line>For violent fires soon burn out themselves;</line>
<line>Small showers last long, but sudden storms are short;</line>
<line>He tires betimes that spurs too fast betimes;</line>
<line>With eager feeding food doth choke the feeder:</line>
<line>Light vanity, insatiate cormorant,</line>
<line>Consuming means, soon preys upon itself.</line>
<line>This royal throne of kings, this scepter'd isle,</line>
<line>This earth of majesty, this seat of Mars,</line>
<line>This other Eden, demi-paradise,</line>
<line>This fortress built by Nature for herself</line>
<line>Against infection and the hand of war,</line>
<line>This happy breed of men, this little world,</line>
<line>This precious stone set in the silver sea,</line>
<line>Which serves it in the office of a wall,</line>
<line>Or as a moat defensive to a house,</line>
<line>Against the envy of less happier lands,</line>
<line>This blessed plot, this earth, this realm, this England,</line>
<line>This nurse, this teeming womb of royal kings,</line>
<line>Fear'd by their breed and famous by their birth,</line>
<line>Renowned for their deeds as far from home,</line>
<line>For Christian service and true chivalry,</line>
<line>As is the sepulchre in stubborn Jewry,</line>
<line>Of the world's ransom, blessed Mary's Son,</line>
<line>This land of such dear souls, this dear dear land,</line>
<line>Dear for her reputation through the world,</line>
<line>Is now leased out, I die pronouncing it,</line>
<line>Like to a tenement or pelting farm:</line>
<line>England, bound in with the triumphant sea</line>
<line>Whose rocky shore beats back the envious siege</line>
<line>Of watery Neptune, is now bound in with shame,</line>
<line>With inky blots and rotten parchment bonds:</line>
<line>That England, that was wont to conquer others,</line>
<line>Hath made a shameful conquest of itself.</line>
<line>Ah, would the scandal vanish with my life,</line>
<line>How happy then were my ensuing death!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter KING RICHARD II and QUEEN, DUKE OF AUMERLE,
BUSHY, GREEN, BAGOT, LORD ROSS, and LORD
WILLOUGHBY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>The king is come: deal mildly with his youth;</line>
<line>For young hot colts being raged do rage the more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>How fares our noble uncle, Lancaster?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>What comfort, man? how is't with aged Gaunt?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>O how that name befits my composition!</line>
<line>Old Gaunt indeed, and gaunt in being old:</line>
<line>Within me grief hath kept a tedious fast;</line>
<line>And who abstains from meat that is not gaunt?</line>
<line>For sleeping England long time have I watch'd;</line>
<line>Watching breeds leanness, leanness is all gaunt:</line>
<line>The pleasure that some fathers feed upon,</line>
<line>Is my strict fast; I mean, my children's looks;</line>
<line>And therein fasting, hast thou made me gaunt:</line>
<line>Gaunt am I for the grave, gaunt as a grave,</line>
<line>Whose hollow womb inherits nought but bones.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Can sick men play so nicely with their names?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>No, misery makes sport to mock itself:</line>
<line>Since thou dost seek to kill my name in me,</line>
<line>I mock my name, great king, to flatter thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Should dying men flatter with those that live?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>No, no, men living flatter those that die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Thou, now a-dying, say'st thou flatterest me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>O, no! thou diest, though I the sicker be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>I am in health, I breathe, and see thee ill.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>Now He that made me knows I see thee ill;</line>
<line>Ill in myself to see, and in thee seeing ill.</line>
<line>Thy death-bed is no lesser than thy land</line>
<line>Wherein thou liest in reputation sick;</line>
<line>And thou, too careless patient as thou art,</line>
<line>Commit'st thy anointed body to the cure</line>
<line>Of those physicians that first wounded thee:</line>
<line>A thousand flatterers sit within thy crown,</line>
<line>Whose compass is no bigger than thy head;</line>
<line>And yet, incaged in so small a verge,</line>
<line>The waste is no whit lesser than thy land.</line>
<line>O, had thy grandsire with a prophet's eye</line>
<line>Seen how his son's son should destroy his sons,</line>
<line>From forth thy reach he would have laid thy shame,</line>
<line>Deposing thee before thou wert possess'd,</line>
<line>Which art possess'd now to depose thyself.</line>
<line>Why, cousin, wert thou regent of the world,</line>
<line>It were a shame to let this land by lease;</line>
<line>But for thy world enjoying but this land,</line>
<line>Is it not more than shame to shame it so?</line>
<line>Landlord of England art thou now, not king:</line>
<line>Thy state of law is bondslave to the law; And thou--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>A lunatic lean-witted fool,</line>
<line>Presuming on an ague's privilege,</line>
<line>Darest with thy frozen admonition</line>
<line>Make pale our cheek, chasing the royal blood</line>
<line>With fury from his native residence.</line>
<line>Now, by my seat's right royal majesty,</line>
<line>Wert thou not brother to great Edward's son,</line>
<line>This tongue that runs so roundly in thy head</line>
<line>Should run thy head from thy unreverent shoulders.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
<line>O, spare me not, my brother Edward's son,</line>
<line>For that I was his father Edward's son;</line>
<line>That blood already, like the pelican,</line>
<line>Hast thou tapp'd out and drunkenly caroused:</line>
<line>My brother Gloucester, plain well-meaning soul,</line>
<line>Whom fair befal in heaven 'mongst happy souls!</line>
<line>May be a precedent and witness good</line>
<line>That thou respect'st not spilling Edward's blood:</line>
<line>Join with the present sickness that I have;</line>
<line>And thy unkindness be like crooked age,</line>
<line>To crop at once a too long wither'd flower.</line>
<line>Live in thy shame, but die not shame with thee!</line>
<line>These words hereafter thy tormentors be!</line>
<line>Convey me to my bed, then to my grave:</line>
<line>Love they to live that love and honour have.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit, borne off by his Attendants</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>And let them die that age and sullens have;</line>
<line>For both hast thou, and both become the grave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I do beseech your majesty, impute his words</line>
<line>To wayward sickliness and age in him:</line>
<line>He loves you, on my life, and holds you dear</line>
<line>As Harry Duke of Hereford, were he here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Right, you say true: as Hereford's love, so his;</line>
<line>As theirs, so mine; and all be as it is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter NORTHUMBERLAND</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My liege, old Gaunt commends him to your majesty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>What says he?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Nay, nothing; all is said</line>
<line>His tongue is now a stringless instrument;</line>
<line>Words, life and all, old Lancaster hath spent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Be York the next that must be bankrupt so!</line>
<line>Though death be poor, it ends a mortal woe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>The ripest fruit first falls, and so doth he;</line>
<line>His time is spent, our pilgrimage must be.</line>
<line>So much for that. Now for our Irish wars:</line>
<line>We must supplant those rough rug-headed kerns,</line>
<line>Which live like venom where no venom else</line>
<line>But only they have privilege to live.</line>
<line>And for these great affairs do ask some charge,</line>
<line>Towards our assistance we do seize to us</line>
<line>The plate, corn, revenues and moveables,</line>
<line>Whereof our uncle Gaunt did stand possess'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>How long shall I be patient? ah, how long</line>
<line>Shall tender duty make me suffer wrong?</line>
<line>Not Gloucester's death, nor Hereford's banishment</line>
<line>Not Gaunt's rebukes, nor England's private wrongs,</line>
<line>Nor the prevention of poor Bolingbroke</line>
<line>About his marriage, nor my own disgrace,</line>
<line>Have ever made me sour my patient cheek,</line>
<line>Or bend one wrinkle on my sovereign's face.</line>
<line>I am the last of noble Edward's sons,</line>
<line>Of whom thy father, Prince of Wales, was first:</line>
<line>In war was never lion raged more fierce,</line>
<line>In peace was never gentle lamb more mild,</line>
<line>Than was that young and princely gentleman.</line>
<line>His face thou hast, for even so look'd he,</line>
<line>Accomplish'd with the number of thy hours;</line>
<line>But when he frown'd, it was against the French</line>
<line>And not against his friends; his noble hand</line>
<line>Did will what he did spend and spent not that</line>
<line>Which his triumphant father's hand had won;</line>
<line>His hands were guilty of no kindred blood,</line>
<line>But bloody with the enemies of his kin.</line>
<line>O Richard! York is too far gone with grief,</line>
<line>Or else he never would compare between.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Why, uncle, what's the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>O my liege,</line>
<line>Pardon me, if you please; if not, I, pleased</line>
<line>Not to be pardon'd, am content withal.</line>
<line>Seek you to seize and gripe into your hands</line>
<line>The royalties and rights of banish'd Hereford?</line>
<line>Is not Gaunt dead, and doth not Hereford live?</line>
<line>Was not Gaunt just, and is not Harry true?</line>
<line>Did not the one deserve to have an heir?</line>
<line>Is not his heir a well-deserving son?</line>
<line>Take Hereford's rights away, and take from Time</line>
<line>His charters and his customary rights;</line>
<line>Let not to-morrow then ensue to-day;</line>
<line>Be not thyself; for how art thou a king</line>
<line>But by fair sequence and succession?</line>
<line>Now, afore God--God forbid I say true!--</line>
<line>If you do wrongfully seize Hereford's rights,</line>
<line>Call in the letters patent that he hath</line>
<line>By his attorneys-general to sue</line>
<line>His livery, and deny his offer'd homage,</line>
<line>You pluck a thousand dangers on your head,</line>
<line>You lose a thousand well-disposed hearts</line>
<line>And prick my tender patience, to those thoughts</line>
<line>Which honour and allegiance cannot think.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Think what you will, we seize into our hands</line>
<line>His plate, his goods, his money and his lands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I'll not be by the while: my liege, farewell:</line>
<line>What will ensue hereof, there's none can tell;</line>
<line>But by bad courses may be understood</line>
<line>That their events can never fall out good.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Go, Bushy, to the Earl of Wiltshire straight:</line>
<line>Bid him repair to us to Ely House</line>
<line>To see this business. To-morrow next</line>
<line>We will for Ireland; and 'tis time, I trow:</line>
<line>And we create, in absence of ourself,</line>
<line>Our uncle York lord governor of England;</line>
<line>For he is just and always loved us well.</line>
<line>Come on, our queen: to-morrow must we part;</line>
<line>Be merry, for our time of stay is short</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Exeunt KING RICHARD II, QUEEN, DUKE OF
AUMERLE, BUSHY, GREEN, and BAGOT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Well, lords, the Duke of Lancaster is dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>And living too; for now his son is duke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>Barely in title, not in revenue.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Richly in both, if justice had her right.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>My heart is great; but it must break with silence,</line>
<line>Ere't be disburden'd with a liberal tongue.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Nay, speak thy mind; and let him ne'er speak more</line>
<line>That speaks thy words again to do thee harm!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>Tends that thou wouldst speak to the Duke of Hereford?</line>
<line>If it be so, out with it boldly, man;</line>
<line>Quick is mine ear to hear of good towards him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>No good at all that I can do for him;</line>
<line>Unless you call it good to pity him,</line>
<line>Bereft and gelded of his patrimony.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Now, afore God, 'tis shame such wrongs are borne</line>
<line>In him, a royal prince, and many moe</line>
<line>Of noble blood in this declining land.</line>
<line>The king is not himself, but basely led</line>
<line>By flatterers; and what they will inform,</line>
<line>Merely in hate, 'gainst any of us all,</line>
<line>That will the king severely prosecute</line>
<line>'Gainst us, our lives, our children, and our heirs.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>The commons hath he pill'd with grievous taxes,</line>
<line>And quite lost their hearts: the nobles hath he fined</line>
<line>For ancient quarrels, and quite lost their hearts.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>And daily new exactions are devised,</line>
<line>As blanks, benevolences, and I wot not what:</line>
<line>But what, o' God's name, doth become of this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Wars have not wasted it, for warr'd he hath not,</line>
<line>But basely yielded upon compromise</line>
<line>That which his noble ancestors achieved with blows:</line>
<line>More hath he spent in peace than they in wars.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>The Earl of Wiltshire hath the realm in farm.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>The king's grown bankrupt, like a broken man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Reproach and dissolution hangeth over him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>He hath not money for these Irish wars,</line>
<line>His burthenous taxations notwithstanding,</line>
<line>But by the robbing of the banish'd duke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>His noble kinsman: most degenerate king!</line>
<line>But, lords, we hear this fearful tempest sing,</line>
<line>Yet see no shelter to avoid the storm;</line>
<line>We see the wind sit sore upon our sails,</line>
<line>And yet we strike not, but securely perish.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>We see the very wreck that we must suffer;</line>
<line>And unavoided is the danger now,</line>
<line>For suffering so the causes of our wreck.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Not so; even through the hollow eyes of death</line>
<line>I spy life peering; but I dare not say</line>
<line>How near the tidings of our comfort is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>Nay, let us share thy thoughts, as thou dost ours.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>Be confident to speak, Northumberland:</line>
<line>We three are but thyself; and, speaking so,</line>
<line>Thy words are but as thoughts; therefore, be bold.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Then thus: I have from Port le Blanc, a bay</line>
<line>In Brittany, received intelligence</line>
<line>That Harry Duke of Hereford, Rainold Lord Cobham,</line>
<line>That late broke from the Duke of Exeter,</line>
<line>His brother, Archbishop late of Canterbury,</line>
<line>Sir Thomas Erpingham, Sir John Ramston,</line>
<line>Sir John Norbery, Sir Robert Waterton and Francis Quoint,</line>
<line>All these well furnish'd by the Duke of Bretagne</line>
<line>With eight tall ships, three thousand men of war,</line>
<line>Are making hither with all due expedience</line>
<line>And shortly mean to touch our northern shore:</line>
<line>Perhaps they had ere this, but that they stay</line>
<line>The first departing of the king for Ireland.</line>
<line>If then we shall shake off our slavish yoke,</line>
<line>Imp out our drooping country's broken wing,</line>
<line>Redeem from broking pawn the blemish'd crown,</line>
<line>Wipe off the dust that hides our sceptre's gilt</line>
<line>And make high majesty look like itself,</line>
<line>Away with me in post to Ravenspurgh;</line>
<line>But if you faint, as fearing to do so,</line>
<line>Stay and be secret, and myself will go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>To horse, to horse! urge doubts to them that fear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>Hold out my horse, and I will first be there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter QUEEN, BUSHY, and BAGOT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Madam, your majesty is too much sad:</line>
<line>You promised, when you parted with the king,</line>
<line>To lay aside life-harming heaviness</line>
<line>And entertain a cheerful disposition.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>To please the king I did; to please myself</line>
<line>I cannot do it; yet I know no cause</line>
<line>Why I should welcome such a guest as grief,</line>
<line>Save bidding farewell to so sweet a guest</line>
<line>As my sweet Richard: yet again, methinks,</line>
<line>Some unborn sorrow, ripe in fortune's womb,</line>
<line>Is coming towards me, and my inward soul</line>
<line>With nothing trembles: at some thing it grieves,</line>
<line>More than with parting from my lord the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Each substance of a grief hath twenty shadows,</line>
<line>Which shows like grief itself, but is not so;</line>
<line>For sorrow's eye, glazed with blinding tears,</line>
<line>Divides one thing entire to many objects;</line>
<line>Like perspectives, which rightly gazed upon</line>
<line>Show nothing but confusion, eyed awry</line>
<line>Distinguish form: so your sweet majesty,</line>
<line>Looking awry upon your lord's departure,</line>
<line>Find shapes of grief, more than himself, to wail;</line>
<line>Which, look'd on as it is, is nought but shadows</line>
<line>Of what it is not. Then, thrice-gracious queen,</line>
<line>More than your lord's departure weep not: more's not seen;</line>
<line>Or if it be, 'tis with false sorrow's eye,</line>
<line>Which for things true weeps things imaginary.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>It may be so; but yet my inward soul</line>
<line>Persuades me it is otherwise: howe'er it be,</line>
<line>I cannot but be sad; so heavy sad</line>
<line>As, though on thinking on no thought I think,</line>
<line>Makes me with heavy nothing faint and shrink.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>'Tis nothing but conceit, my gracious lady.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>'Tis nothing less: conceit is still derived</line>
<line>From some forefather grief; mine is not so,</line>
<line>For nothing had begot my something grief;</line>
<line>Or something hath the nothing that I grieve:</line>
<line>'Tis in reversion that I do possess;</line>
<line>But what it is, that is not yet known; what</line>
<line>I cannot name; 'tis nameless woe, I wot.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter GREEN</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>God save your majesty! and well met, gentlemen:</line>
<line>I hope the king is not yet shipp'd for Ireland.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Why hopest thou so? 'tis better hope he is;</line>
<line>For his designs crave haste, his haste good hope:</line>
<line>Then wherefore dost thou hope he is not shipp'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>That he, our hope, might have retired his power,</line>
<line>And driven into despair an enemy's hope,</line>
<line>Who strongly hath set footing in this land:</line>
<line>The banish'd Bolingbroke repeals himself,</line>
<line>And with uplifted arms is safe arrived</line>
<line>At Ravenspurgh.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Now God in heaven forbid!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>Ah, madam, 'tis too true: and that is worse,</line>
<line>The Lord Northumberland, his son young Henry Percy,</line>
<line>The Lords of Ross, Beaumond, and Willoughby,</line>
<line>With all their powerful friends, are fled to him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Why have you not proclaim'd Northumberland</line>
<line>And all the rest revolted faction traitors?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>We have: whereupon the Earl of Worcester</line>
<line>Hath broke his staff, resign'd his stewardship,</line>
<line>And all the household servants fled with him</line>
<line>To Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>So, Green, thou art the midwife to my woe,</line>
<line>And Bolingbroke my sorrow's dismal heir:</line>
<line>Now hath my soul brought forth her prodigy,</line>
<line>And I, a gasping new-deliver'd mother,</line>
<line>Have woe to woe, sorrow to sorrow join'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Despair not, madam.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Who shall hinder me?</line>
<line>I will despair, and be at enmity</line>
<line>With cozening hope: he is a flatterer,</line>
<line>A parasite, a keeper back of death,</line>
<line>Who gently would dissolve the bands of life,</line>
<line>Which false hope lingers in extremity.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF YORK</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>Here comes the Duke of York.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>With signs of war about his aged neck:</line>
<line>O, full of careful business are his looks!</line>
<line>Uncle, for God's sake, speak comfortable words.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Should I do so, I should belie my thoughts:</line>
<line>Comfort's in heaven; and we are on the earth,</line>
<line>Where nothing lives but crosses, cares and grief.</line>
<line>Your husband, he is gone to save far off,</line>
<line>Whilst others come to make him lose at home:</line>
<line>Here am I left to underprop his land,</line>
<line>Who, weak with age, cannot support myself:</line>
<line>Now comes the sick hour that his surfeit made;</line>
<line>Now shall he try his friends that flatter'd him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Servant</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>My lord, your son was gone before I came.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>He was? Why, so! go all which way it will!</line>
<line>The nobles they are fled, the commons they are cold,</line>
<line>And will, I fear, revolt on Hereford's side.</line>
<line>Sirrah, get thee to Plashy, to my sister Gloucester;</line>
<line>Bid her send me presently a thousand pound:</line>
<line>Hold, take my ring.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>My lord, I had forgot to tell your lordship,</line>
<line>To-day, as I came by, I called there;</line>
<line>But I shall grieve you to report the rest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>What is't, knave?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>An hour before I came, the duchess died.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>God for his mercy! what a tide of woes</line>
<line>Comes rushing on this woeful land at once!</line>
<line>I know not what to do: I would to God,</line>
<line>So my untruth had not provoked him to it,</line>
<line>The king had cut off my head with my brother's.</line>
<line>What, are there no posts dispatch'd for Ireland?</line>
<line>How shall we do for money for these wars?</line>
<line>Come, sister,--cousin, I would say--pray, pardon me.</line>
<line>Go, fellow, get thee home, provide some carts</line>
<line>And bring away the armour that is there.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exit Servant</para>
<line>Gentlemen, will you go muster men?</line>
<line>If I know how or which way to order these affairs</line>
<line>Thus thrust disorderly into my hands,</line>
<line>Never believe me. Both are my kinsmen:</line>
<line>The one is my sovereign, whom both my oath</line>
<line>And duty bids defend; the other again</line>
<line>Is my kinsman, whom the king hath wrong'd,</line>
<line>Whom conscience and my kindred bids to right.</line>
<line>Well, somewhat we must do. Come, cousin, I'll</line>
<line>Dispose of you.</line>
<line>Gentlemen, go, muster up your men,</line>
<line>And meet me presently at Berkeley.</line>
<line>I should to Plashy too;</line>
<line>But time will not permit: all is uneven,</line>
<line>And every thing is left at six and seven.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt DUKE OF YORK and QUEEN</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>The wind sits fair for news to go to Ireland,</line>
<line>But none returns. For us to levy power</line>
<line>Proportionable to the enemy</line>
<line>Is all unpossible.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>Besides, our nearness to the king in love</line>
<line>Is near the hate of those love not the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BAGOT</speaker>
<line>And that's the wavering commons: for their love</line>
<line>Lies in their purses, and whoso empties them</line>
<line>By so much fills their hearts with deadly hate.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Wherein the king stands generally condemn'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BAGOT</speaker>
<line>If judgement lie in them, then so do we,</line>
<line>Because we ever have been near the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>Well, I will for refuge straight to Bristol castle:</line>
<line>The Earl of Wiltshire is already there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Thither will I with you; for little office</line>
<line>The hateful commons will perform for us,</line>
<line>Except like curs to tear us all to pieces.</line>
<line>Will you go along with us?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BAGOT</speaker>
<line>No; I will to Ireland to his majesty.</line>
<line>Farewell: if heart's presages be not vain,</line>
<line>We three here art that ne'er shall meet again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>That's as York thrives to beat back Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>Alas, poor duke! the task he undertakes</line>
<line>Is numbering sands and drinking oceans dry:</line>
<line>Where one on his side fights, thousands will fly.</line>
<line>Farewell at once, for once, for all, and ever.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>Well, we may meet again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BAGOT</speaker>
<line>I fear me, never.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Wilds in Gloucestershire.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE and NORTHUMBERLAND, with Forces</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>How far is it, my lord, to Berkeley now?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Believe me, noble lord,</line>
<line>I am a stranger here in Gloucestershire:</line>
<line>These high wild hills and rough uneven ways</line>
<line>Draws out our miles, and makes them wearisome,</line>
<line>And yet your fair discourse hath been as sugar,</line>
<line>Making the hard way sweet and delectable.</line>
<line>But I bethink me what a weary way</line>
<line>From Ravenspurgh to Cotswold will be found</line>
<line>In Ross and Willoughby, wanting your company,</line>
<line>Which, I protest, hath very much beguiled</line>
<line>The tediousness and process of my travel:</line>
<line>But theirs is sweetened with the hope to have</line>
<line>The present benefit which I possess;</line>
<line>And hope to joy is little less in joy</line>
<line>Than hope enjoy'd: by this the weary lords</line>
<line>Shall make their way seem short, as mine hath done</line>
<line>By sight of what I have, your noble company.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Of much less value is my company</line>
<line>Than your good words. But who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY PERCY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>It is my son, young Harry Percy,</line>
<line>Sent from my brother Worcester, whencesoever.</line>
<line>Harry, how fares your uncle?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>I had thought, my lord, to have learn'd his health of you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Why, is he not with the queen?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>No, my good Lord; he hath forsook the court,</line>
<line>Broken his staff of office and dispersed</line>
<line>The household of the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>What was his reason?</line>
<line>He was not so resolved when last we spake together.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Because your lordship was proclaimed traitor.</line>
<line>But he, my lord, is gone to Ravenspurgh,</line>
<line>To offer service to the Duke of Hereford,</line>
<line>And sent me over by Berkeley, to discover</line>
<line>What power the Duke of York had levied there;</line>
<line>Then with directions to repair to Ravenspurgh.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Have you forgot the Duke of Hereford, boy?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>No, my good lord, for that is not forgot</line>
<line>Which ne'er I did remember: to my knowledge,</line>
<line>I never in my life did look on him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Then learn to know him now; this is the duke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>My gracious lord, I tender you my service,</line>
<line>Such as it is, being tender, raw and young:</line>
<line>Which elder days shall ripen and confirm</line>
<line>To more approved service and desert.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I thank thee, gentle Percy; and be sure</line>
<line>I count myself in nothing else so happy</line>
<line>As in a soul remembering my good friends;</line>
<line>And, as my fortune ripens with thy love,</line>
<line>It shall be still thy true love's recompense:</line>
<line>My heart this covenant makes, my hand thus seals it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>How far is it to Berkeley? and what stir</line>
<line>Keeps good old York there with his men of war?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>There stands the castle, by yon tuft of trees,</line>
<line>Mann'd with three hundred men, as I have heard;</line>
<line>And in it are the Lords of York, Berkeley, and Seymour;</line>
<line>None else of name and noble estimate.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter LORD ROSS and LORD WILLOUGHBY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Here come the Lords of Ross and Willoughby,</line>
<line>Bloody with spurring, fiery-red with haste.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Welcome, my lords. I wot your love pursues</line>
<line>A banish'd traitor: all my treasury</line>
<line>Is yet but unfelt thanks, which more enrich'd</line>
<line>Shall be your love and labour's recompense.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>Your presence makes us rich, most noble lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>And far surmounts our labour to attain it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Evermore thanks, the exchequer of the poor;</line>
<line>Which, till my infant fortune comes to years,</line>
<line>Stands for my bounty. But who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter LORD BERKELEY</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>It is my Lord of Berkeley, as I guess.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD BERKELEY</speaker>
<line>My Lord of Hereford, my message is to you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>My lord, my answer is--to Lancaster;</line>
<line>And I am come to seek that name in England;</line>
<line>And I must find that title in your tongue,</line>
<line>Before I make reply to aught you say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD BERKELEY</speaker>
<line>Mistake me not, my lord; 'tis not my meaning</line>
<line>To raze one title of your honour out:</line>
<line>To you, my lord, I come, what lord you will,</line>
<line>From the most gracious regent of this land,</line>
<line>The Duke of York, to know what pricks you on</line>
<line>To take advantage of the absent time</line>
<line>And fright our native peace with self-born arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF YORK attended</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I shall not need transport my words by you;</line>
<line>Here comes his grace in person. My noble uncle!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Kneels</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Show me thy humble heart, and not thy knee,</line>
<line>Whose duty is deceiveable and false.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>My gracious uncle--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Tut, tut!</line>
<line>Grace me no grace, nor uncle me no uncle:</line>
<line>I am no traitor's uncle; and that word 'grace.'</line>
<line>In an ungracious mouth is but profane.</line>
<line>Why have those banish'd and forbidden legs</line>
<line>Dared once to touch a dust of England's ground?</line>
<line>But then more 'why?' why have they dared to march</line>
<line>So many miles upon her peaceful bosom,</line>
<line>Frighting her pale-faced villages with war</line>
<line>And ostentation of despised arms?</line>
<line>Comest thou because the anointed king is hence?</line>
<line>Why, foolish boy, the king is left behind,</line>
<line>And in my loyal bosom lies his power.</line>
<line>Were I but now the lord of such hot youth</line>
<line>As when brave Gaunt, thy father, and myself</line>
<line>Rescued the Black Prince, that young Mars of men,</line>
<line>From forth the ranks of many thousand French,</line>
<line>O, then how quickly should this arm of mine.</line>
<line>Now prisoner to the palsy, chastise thee</line>
<line>And minister correction to thy fault!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>My gracious uncle, let me know my fault:</line>
<line>On what condition stands it and wherein?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Even in condition of the worst degree,</line>
<line>In gross rebellion and detested treason:</line>
<line>Thou art a banish'd man, and here art come</line>
<line>Before the expiration of thy time,</line>
<line>In braving arms against thy sovereign.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>As I was banish'd, I was banish'd Hereford;</line>
<line>But as I come, I come for Lancaster.</line>
<line>And, noble uncle, I beseech your grace</line>
<line>Look on my wrongs with an indifferent eye:</line>
<line>You are my father, for methinks in you</line>
<line>I see old Gaunt alive; O, then, my father,</line>
<line>Will you permit that I shall stand condemn'd</line>
<line>A wandering vagabond; my rights and royalties</line>
<line>Pluck'd from my arms perforce and given away</line>
<line>To upstart unthrifts? Wherefore was I born?</line>
<line>If that my cousin king be King of England,</line>
<line>It must be granted I am Duke of Lancaster.</line>
<line>You have a son, Aumerle, my noble cousin;</line>
<line>Had you first died, and he been thus trod down,</line>
<line>He should have found his uncle Gaunt a father,</line>
<line>To rouse his wrongs and chase them to the bay.</line>
<line>I am denied to sue my livery here,</line>
<line>And yet my letters-patents give me leave:</line>
<line>My father's goods are all distrain'd and sold,</line>
<line>And these and all are all amiss employ'd.</line>
<line>What would you have me do? I am a subject,</line>
<line>And I challenge law: attorneys are denied me;</line>
<line>And therefore, personally I lay my claim</line>
<line>To my inheritance of free descent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>The noble duke hath been too much abused.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD ROSS</speaker>
<line>It stands your grace upon to do him right.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
<line>Base men by his endowments are made great.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>My lords of England, let me tell you this:</line>
<line>I have had feeling of my cousin's wrongs</line>
<line>And laboured all I could to do him right;</line>
<line>But in this kind to come, in braving arms,</line>
<line>Be his own carver and cut out his way,</line>
<line>To find out right with wrong, it may not be;</line>
<line>And you that do abet him in this kind</line>
<line>Cherish rebellion and are rebels all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>The noble duke hath sworn his coming is</line>
<line>But for his own; and for the right of that</line>
<line>We all have strongly sworn to give him aid;</line>
<line>And let him ne'er see joy that breaks that oath!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Well, well, I see the issue of these arms:</line>
<line>I cannot mend it, I must needs confess,</line>
<line>Because my power is weak and all ill left:</line>
<line>But if I could, by Him that gave me life,</line>
<line>I would attach you all and make you stoop</line>
<line>Unto the sovereign mercy of the king;</line>
<line>But since I cannot, be it known to you</line>
<line>I do remain as neuter. So, fare you well;</line>
<line>Unless you please to enter in the castle</line>
<line>And there repose you for this night.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>An offer, uncle, that we will accept:</line>
<line>But we must win your grace to go with us</line>
<line>To Bristol castle, which they say is held</line>
<line>By Bushy, Bagot and their complices,</line>
<line>The caterpillars of the commonwealth,</line>
<line>Which I have sworn to weed and pluck away.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>It may be I will go with you: but yet I'll pause;</line>
<line>For I am loath to break our country's laws.</line>
<line>Nor friends nor foes, to me welcome you are:</line>
<line>Things past redress are now with me past care.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  A camp in Wales.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter EARL OF SALISBURY and a Welsh Captain</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Captain</speaker>
<line>My lord of Salisbury, we have stay'd ten days,</line>
<line>And hardly kept our countrymen together,</line>
<line>And yet we hear no tidings from the king;</line>
<line>Therefore we will disperse ourselves: farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF SALISBURY</speaker>
<line>Stay yet another day, thou trusty Welshman:</line>
<line>The king reposeth all his confidence in thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Captain</speaker>
<line>'Tis thought the king is dead; we will not stay.</line>
<line>The bay-trees in our country are all wither'd</line>
<line>And meteors fright the fixed stars of heaven;</line>
<line>The pale-faced moon looks bloody on the earth</line>
<line>And lean-look'd prophets whisper fearful change;</line>
<line>Rich men look sad and ruffians dance and leap,</line>
<line>The one in fear to lose what they enjoy,</line>
<line>The other to enjoy by rage and war:</line>
<line>These signs forerun the death or fall of kings.</line>
<line>Farewell: our countrymen are gone and fled,</line>
<line>As well assured Richard their king is dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF SALISBURY</speaker>
<line>Ah, Richard, with the eyes of heavy mind</line>
<line>I see thy glory like a shooting star</line>
<line>Fall to the base earth from the firmament.</line>
<line>Thy sun sets weeping in the lowly west,</line>
<line>Witnessing storms to come, woe and unrest:</line>
<line>Thy friends are fled to wait upon thy foes,</line>
<line>And crossly to thy good all fortune goes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT III</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Bristol. Before the castle.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE, DUKE OF YORK,
NORTHUMBERLAND, LORD ROSS, HENRY PERCY, LORD
WILLOUGHBY, with BUSHY and GREEN, prisoners</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Bring forth these men.</line>
<line>Bushy and Green, I will not vex your souls--</line>
<line>Since presently your souls must part your bodies--</line>
<line>With too much urging your pernicious lives,</line>
<line>For 'twere no charity; yet, to wash your blood</line>
<line>From off my hands, here in the view of men</line>
<line>I will unfold some causes of your deaths.</line>
<line>You have misled a prince, a royal king,</line>
<line>A happy gentleman in blood and lineaments,</line>
<line>By you unhappied and disfigured clean:</line>
<line>You have in manner with your sinful hours</line>
<line>Made a divorce betwixt his queen and him,</line>
<line>Broke the possession of a royal bed</line>
<line>And stain'd the beauty of a fair queen's cheeks</line>
<line>With tears drawn from her eyes by your foul wrongs.</line>
<line>Myself, a prince by fortune of my birth,</line>
<line>Near to the king in blood, and near in love</line>
<line>Till you did make him misinterpret me,</line>
<line>Have stoop'd my neck under your injuries,</line>
<line>And sigh'd my English breath in foreign clouds,</line>
<line>Eating the bitter bread of banishment;</line>
<line>Whilst you have fed upon my signories,</line>
<line>Dispark'd my parks and fell'd my forest woods,</line>
<line>From my own windows torn my household coat,</line>
<line>Razed out my imprese, leaving me no sign,</line>
<line>Save men's opinions and my living blood,</line>
<line>To show the world I am a gentleman.</line>
<line>This and much more, much more than twice all this,</line>
<line>Condemns you to the death. See them deliver'd over</line>
<line>To execution and the hand of death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BUSHY</speaker>
<line>More welcome is the stroke of death to me</line>
<line>Than Bolingbroke to England. Lords, farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GREEN</speaker>
<line>My comfort is that heaven will take our souls</line>
<line>And plague injustice with the pains of hell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>My Lord Northumberland, see them dispatch'd.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt NORTHUMBERLAND and others, with the
prisoners</para>
<line>Uncle, you say the queen is at your house;</line>
<line>For God's sake, fairly let her be entreated:</line>
<line>Tell her I send to her my kind commends;</line>
<line>Take special care my greetings be deliver'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>A gentleman of mine I have dispatch'd</line>
<line>With letters of your love to her at large.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Thank, gentle uncle. Come, lords, away.</line>
<line>To fight with Glendower and his complices:</line>
<line>Awhile to work, and after holiday.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The coast of Wales. A castle in view.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Drums; flourish and colours. Enter KING RICHARD
II, the BISHOP OF CARLISLE, DUKE OF AUMERLE, and Soldiers</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Barkloughly castle call they this at hand?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Yea, my lord. How brooks your grace the air,</line>
<line>After your late tossing on the breaking seas?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Needs must I like it well: I weep for joy</line>
<line>To stand upon my kingdom once again.</line>
<line>Dear earth, I do salute thee with my hand,</line>
<line>Though rebels wound thee with their horses' hoofs:</line>
<line>As a long-parted mother with her child</line>
<line>Plays fondly with her tears and smiles in meeting,</line>
<line>So, weeping, smiling, greet I thee, my earth,</line>
<line>And do thee favours with my royal hands.</line>
<line>Feed not thy sovereign's foe, my gentle earth,</line>
<line>Nor with thy sweets comfort his ravenous sense;</line>
<line>But let thy spiders, that suck up thy venom,</line>
<line>And heavy-gaited toads lie in their way,</line>
<line>Doing annoyance to the treacherous feet</line>
<line>Which with usurping steps do trample thee:</line>
<line>Yield stinging nettles to mine enemies;</line>
<line>And when they from thy bosom pluck a flower,</line>
<line>Guard it, I pray thee, with a lurking adder</line>
<line>Whose double tongue may with a mortal touch</line>
<line>Throw death upon thy sovereign's enemies.</line>
<line>Mock not my senseless conjuration, lords:</line>
<line>This earth shall have a feeling and these stones</line>
<line>Prove armed soldiers, ere her native king</line>
<line>Shall falter under foul rebellion's arms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
<line>Fear not, my lord: that Power that made you king</line>
<line>Hath power to keep you king in spite of all.</line>
<line>The means that heaven yields must be embraced,</line>
<line>And not neglected; else, if heaven would,</line>
<line>And we will not, heaven's offer we refuse,</line>
<line>The proffer'd means of succor and redress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>He means, my lord, that we are too remiss;</line>
<line>Whilst Bolingbroke, through our security,</line>
<line>Grows strong and great in substance and in power.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Discomfortable cousin! know'st thou not</line>
<line>That when the searching eye of heaven is hid,</line>
<line>Behind the globe, that lights the lower world,</line>
<line>Then thieves and robbers range abroad unseen</line>
<line>In murders and in outrage, boldly here;</line>
<line>But when from under this terrestrial ball</line>
<line>He fires the proud tops of the eastern pines</line>
<line>And darts his light through every guilty hole,</line>
<line>Then murders, treasons and detested sins,</line>
<line>The cloak of night being pluck'd from off their backs,</line>
<line>Stand bare and naked, trembling at themselves?</line>
<line>So when this thief, this traitor, Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>Who all this while hath revell'd in the night</line>
<line>Whilst we were wandering with the antipodes,</line>
<line>Shall see us rising in our throne, the east,</line>
<line>His treasons will sit blushing in his face,</line>
<line>Not able to endure the sight of day,</line>
<line>But self-affrighted tremble at his sin.</line>
<line>Not all the water in the rough rude sea</line>
<line>Can wash the balm off from an anointed king;</line>
<line>The breath of worldly men cannot depose</line>
<line>The deputy elected by the Lord:</line>
<line>For every man that Bolingbroke hath press'd</line>
<line>To lift shrewd steel against our golden crown,</line>
<line>God for his Richard hath in heavenly pay</line>
<line>A glorious angel: then, if angels fight,</line>
<line>Weak men must fall, for heaven still guards the right.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter EARL OF SALISBURY</para>
<line>Welcome, my lord how far off lies your power?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EARL OF SALISBURY</speaker>
<line>Nor near nor farther off, my gracious lord,</line>
<line>Than this weak arm: discomfort guides my tongue</line>
<line>And bids me speak of nothing but despair.</line>
<line>One day too late, I fear me, noble lord,</line>
<line>Hath clouded all thy happy days on earth:</line>
<line>O, call back yesterday, bid time return,</line>
<line>And thou shalt have twelve thousand fighting men!</line>
<line>To-day, to-day, unhappy day, too late,</line>
<line>O'erthrows thy joys, friends, fortune and thy state:</line>
<line>For all the Welshmen, hearing thou wert dead.</line>
<line>Are gone to Bolingbroke, dispersed and fled.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Comfort, my liege; why looks your grace so pale?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>But now the blood of twenty thousand men</line>
<line>Did triumph in my face, and they are fled;</line>
<line>And, till so much blood thither come again,</line>
<line>Have I not reason to look pale and dead?</line>
<line>All souls that will be safe fly from my side,</line>
<line>For time hath set a blot upon my pride.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Comfort, my liege; remember who you are.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>I had forgot myself; am I not king?</line>
<line>Awake, thou coward majesty! thou sleepest.</line>
<line>Is not the king's name twenty thousand names?</line>
<line>Arm, arm, my name! a puny subject strikes</line>
<line>At thy great glory. Look not to the ground,</line>
<line>Ye favourites of a king: are we not high?</line>
<line>High be our thoughts: I know my uncle York</line>
<line>Hath power enough to serve our turn. But who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
<line>More health and happiness betide my liege</line>
<line>Than can my care-tuned tongue deliver him!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Mine ear is open and my heart prepared;</line>
<line>The worst is worldly loss thou canst unfold.</line>
<line>Say, is my kingdom lost? why, 'twas my care</line>
<line>And what loss is it to be rid of care?</line>
<line>Strives Bolingbroke to be as great as we?</line>
<line>Greater he shall not be; if he serve God,</line>
<line>We'll serve Him too and be his fellow so:</line>
<line>Revolt our subjects? that we cannot mend;</line>
<line>They break their faith to God as well as us:</line>
<line>Cry woe, destruction, ruin and decay:</line>
<line>The worst is death, and death will have his day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
<line>Glad am I that your highness is so arm'd</line>
<line>To bear the tidings of calamity.</line>
<line>Like an unseasonable stormy day,</line>
<line>Which makes the silver rivers drown their shores,</line>
<line>As if the world were all dissolved to tears,</line>
<line>So high above his limits swells the rage</line>
<line>Of Bolingbroke, covering your fearful land</line>
<line>With hard bright steel and hearts harder than steel.</line>
<line>White-beards have arm'd their thin and hairless scalps</line>
<line>Against thy majesty; boys, with women's voices,</line>
<line>Strive to speak big and clap their female joints</line>
<line>In stiff unwieldy arms against thy crown:</line>
<line>The very beadsmen learn to bend their bows</line>
<line>Of double-fatal yew against thy state;</line>
<line>Yea, distaff-women manage rusty bills</line>
<line>Against thy seat: both young and old rebel,</line>
<line>And all goes worse than I have power to tell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Too well, too well thou tell'st a tale so ill.</line>
<line>Where is the Earl of Wiltshire? where is Bagot?</line>
<line>What is become of Bushy? where is Green?</line>
<line>That they have let the dangerous enemy</line>
<line>Measure our confines with such peaceful steps?</line>
<line>If we prevail, their heads shall pay for it:</line>
<line>I warrant they have made peace with Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
<line>Peace have they made with him indeed, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>O villains, vipers, damn'd without redemption!</line>
<line>Dogs, easily won to fawn on any man!</line>
<line>Snakes, in my heart-blood warm'd, that sting my heart!</line>
<line>Three Judases, each one thrice worse than Judas!</line>
<line>Would they make peace? terrible hell make war</line>
<line>Upon their spotted souls for this offence!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
<line>Sweet love, I see, changing his property,</line>
<line>Turns to the sourest and most deadly hate:</line>
<line>Again uncurse their souls; their peace is made</line>
<line>With heads, and not with hands; those whom you curse</line>
<line>Have felt the worst of death's destroying wound</line>
<line>And lie full low, graved in the hollow ground.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Is Bushy, Green, and the Earl of Wiltshire dead?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
<line>Ay, all of them at Bristol lost their heads.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Where is the duke my father with his power?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>No matter where; of comfort no man speak:</line>
<line>Let's talk of graves, of worms, and epitaphs;</line>
<line>Make dust our paper and with rainy eyes</line>
<line>Write sorrow on the bosom of the earth,</line>
<line>Let's choose executors and talk of wills:</line>
<line>And yet not so, for what can we bequeath</line>
<line>Save our deposed bodies to the ground?</line>
<line>Our lands, our lives and all are Bolingbroke's,</line>
<line>And nothing can we call our own but death</line>
<line>And that small model of the barren earth</line>
<line>Which serves as paste and cover to our bones.</line>
<line>For God's sake, let us sit upon the ground</line>
<line>And tell sad stories of the death of kings;</line>
<line>How some have been deposed; some slain in war,</line>
<line>Some haunted by the ghosts they have deposed;</line>
<line>Some poison'd by their wives: some sleeping kill'd;</line>
<line>All murder'd: for within the hollow crown</line>
<line>That rounds the mortal temples of a king</line>
<line>Keeps Death his court and there the antic sits,</line>
<line>Scoffing his state and grinning at his pomp,</line>
<line>Allowing him a breath, a little scene,</line>
<line>To monarchize, be fear'd and kill with looks,</line>
<line>Infusing him with self and vain conceit,</line>
<line>As if this flesh which walls about our life,</line>
<line>Were brass impregnable, and humour'd thus</line>
<line>Comes at the last and with a little pin</line>
<line>Bores through his castle wall, and farewell king!</line>
<line>Cover your heads and mock not flesh and blood</line>
<line>With solemn reverence: throw away respect,</line>
<line>Tradition, form and ceremonious duty,</line>
<line>For you have but mistook me all this while:</line>
<line>I live with bread like you, feel want,</line>
<line>Taste grief, need friends: subjected thus,</line>
<line>How can you say to me, I am a king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
<line>My lord, wise men ne'er sit and wail their woes,</line>
<line>But presently prevent the ways to wail.</line>
<line>To fear the foe, since fear oppresseth strength,</line>
<line>Gives in your weakness strength unto your foe,</line>
<line>And so your follies fight against yourself.</line>
<line>Fear and be slain; no worse can come to fight:</line>
<line>And fight and die is death destroying death;</line>
<line>Where fearing dying pays death servile breath.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>My father hath a power; inquire of him</line>
<line>And learn to make a body of a limb.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Thou chidest me well: proud Bolingbroke, I come</line>
<line>To change blows with thee for our day of doom.</line>
<line>This ague fit of fear is over-blown;</line>
<line>An easy task it is to win our own.</line>
<line>Say, Scroop, where lies our uncle with his power?</line>
<line>Speak sweetly, man, although thy looks be sour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
<line>Men judge by the complexion of the sky</line>
<line>The state and inclination of the day:</line>
<line>So may you by my dull and heavy eye,</line>
<line>My tongue hath but a heavier tale to say.</line>
<line>I play the torturer, by small and small</line>
<line>To lengthen out the worst that must be spoken:</line>
<line>Your uncle York is join'd with Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>And all your northern castles yielded up,</line>
<line>And all your southern gentlemen in arms</line>
<line>Upon his party.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Thou hast said enough.</line>
<line>Beshrew thee, cousin, which didst lead me forth</line>
<para role="stagedir">To DUKE OF AUMERLE</para>
<line>Of that sweet way I was in to despair!</line>
<line>What say you now? what comfort have we now?</line>
<line>By heaven, I'll hate him everlastingly</line>
<line>That bids me be of comfort any more.</line>
<line>Go to Flint castle: there I'll pine away;</line>
<line>A king, woe's slave, shall kingly woe obey.</line>
<line>That power I have, discharge; and let them go</line>
<line>To ear the land that hath some hope to grow,</line>
<line>For I have none: let no man speak again</line>
<line>To alter this, for counsel is but vain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>My liege, one word.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>He does me double wrong</line>
<line>That wounds me with the flatteries of his tongue.</line>
<line>Discharge my followers: let them hence away,</line>
<line>From Richard's night to Bolingbroke's fair day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Wales. Before Flint castle.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter, with drum and colours, HENRY BOLINGBROKE,
DUKE OF YORK, NORTHUMBERLAND, Attendants, and forces</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>So that by this intelligence we learn</line>
<line>The Welshmen are dispersed, and Salisbury</line>
<line>Is gone to meet the king, who lately landed</line>
<line>With some few private friends upon this coast.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>The news is very fair and good, my lord:</line>
<line>Richard not far from hence hath hid his head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>It would beseem the Lord Northumberland</line>
<line>To say 'King Richard:' alack the heavy day</line>
<line>When such a sacred king should hide his head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Your grace mistakes; only to be brief</line>
<line>Left I his title out.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>The time hath been,</line>
<line>Would you have been so brief with him, he would</line>
<line>Have been so brief with you, to shorten you,</line>
<line>For taking so the head, your whole head's length.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Mistake not, uncle, further than you should.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Take not, good cousin, further than you should.</line>
<line>Lest you mistake the heavens are o'er our heads.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I know it, uncle, and oppose not myself</line>
<line>Against their will. But who comes here?</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY PERCY</para>
<line>Welcome, Harry: what, will not this castle yield?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>The castle royally is mann'd, my lord,</line>
<line>Against thy entrance.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Royally!</line>
<line>Why, it contains no king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Yes, my good lord,</line>
<line>It doth contain a king; King Richard lies</line>
<line>Within the limits of yon lime and stone:</line>
<line>And with him are the Lord Aumerle, Lord Salisbury,</line>
<line>Sir Stephen Scroop, besides a clergyman</line>
<line>Of holy reverence; who, I cannot learn.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>O, belike it is the Bishop of Carlisle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Noble lords,</line>
<line>Go to the rude ribs of that ancient castle;</line>
<line>Through brazen trumpet send the breath of parley</line>
<line>Into his ruin'd ears, and thus deliver:</line>
<line>Henry Bolingbroke</line>
<line>On both his knees doth kiss King Richard's hand</line>
<line>And sends allegiance and true faith of heart</line>
<line>To his most royal person, hither come</line>
<line>Even at his feet to lay my arms and power,</line>
<line>Provided that my banishment repeal'd</line>
<line>And lands restored again be freely granted:</line>
<line>If not, I'll use the advantage of my power</line>
<line>And lay the summer's dust with showers of blood</line>
<line>Rain'd from the wounds of slaughter'd Englishmen:</line>
<line>The which, how far off from the mind of Bolingbroke</line>
<line>It is, such crimson tempest should bedrench</line>
<line>The fresh green lap of fair King Richard's land,</line>
<line>My stooping duty tenderly shall show.</line>
<line>Go, signify as much, while here we march</line>
<line>Upon the grassy carpet of this plain.</line>
<line>Let's march without the noise of threatening drum,</line>
<line>That from this castle's tatter'd battlements</line>
<line>Our fair appointments may be well perused.</line>
<line>Methinks King Richard and myself should meet</line>
<line>With no less terror than the elements</line>
<line>Of fire and water, when their thundering shock</line>
<line>At meeting tears the cloudy cheeks of heaven.</line>
<line>Be he the fire, I'll be the yielding water:</line>
<line>The rage be his, whilst on the earth I rain</line>
<line>My waters; on the earth, and not on him.</line>
<line>March on, and mark King Richard how he looks.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Parle without, and answer within. Then a flourish.
Enter on the walls, KING RICHARD II, the BISHOP OF
CARLISLE, DUKE OF AUMERLE, SIR STEPHEN SCROOP, and
EARL OF SALISBURY</para>
<line>See, see, King Richard doth himself appear,</line>
<line>As doth the blushing discontented sun</line>
<line>From out the fiery portal of the east,</line>
<line>When he perceives the envious clouds are bent</line>
<line>To dim his glory and to stain the track</line>
<line>Of his bright passage to the occident.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Yet looks he like a king: behold, his eye,</line>
<line>As bright as is the eagle's, lightens forth</line>
<line>Controlling majesty: alack, alack, for woe,</line>
<line>That any harm should stain so fair a show!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We are amazed; and thus long have we stood</line>
<line>To watch the fearful bending of thy knee,</line>
<para role="stagedir">To NORTHUMBERLAND</para>
<line>Because we thought ourself thy lawful king:</line>
<line>And if we be, how dare thy joints forget</line>
<line>To pay their awful duty to our presence?</line>
<line>If we be not, show us the hand of God</line>
<line>That hath dismissed us from our stewardship;</line>
<line>For well we know, no hand of blood and bone</line>
<line>Can gripe the sacred handle of our sceptre,</line>
<line>Unless he do profane, steal, or usurp.</line>
<line>And though you think that all, as you have done,</line>
<line>Have torn their souls by turning them from us,</line>
<line>And we are barren and bereft of friends;</line>
<line>Yet know, my master, God omnipotent,</line>
<line>Is mustering in his clouds on our behalf</line>
<line>Armies of pestilence; and they shall strike</line>
<line>Your children yet unborn and unbegot,</line>
<line>That lift your vassal hands against my head</line>
<line>And threat the glory of my precious crown.</line>
<line>Tell Bolingbroke--for yond methinks he stands--</line>
<line>That every stride he makes upon my land</line>
<line>Is dangerous treason: he is come to open</line>
<line>The purple testament of bleeding war;</line>
<line>But ere the crown he looks for live in peace,</line>
<line>Ten thousand bloody crowns of mothers' sons</line>
<line>Shall ill become the flower of England's face,</line>
<line>Change the complexion of her maid-pale peace</line>
<line>To scarlet indignation and bedew</line>
<line>Her pastures' grass with faithful English blood.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>The king of heaven forbid our lord the king</line>
<line>Should so with civil and uncivil arms</line>
<line>Be rush'd upon! Thy thrice noble cousin</line>
<line>Harry Bolingbroke doth humbly kiss thy hand;</line>
<line>And by the honourable tomb he swears,</line>
<line>That stands upon your royal grandsire's bones,</line>
<line>And by the royalties of both your bloods,</line>
<line>Currents that spring from one most gracious head,</line>
<line>And by the buried hand of warlike Gaunt,</line>
<line>And by the worth and honour of himself,</line>
<line>Comprising all that may be sworn or said,</line>
<line>His coming hither hath no further scope</line>
<line>Than for his lineal royalties and to beg</line>
<line>Enfranchisement immediate on his knees:</line>
<line>Which on thy royal party granted once,</line>
<line>His glittering arms he will commend to rust,</line>
<line>His barbed steeds to stables, and his heart</line>
<line>To faithful service of your majesty.</line>
<line>This swears he, as he is a prince, is just;</line>
<line>And, as I am a gentleman, I credit him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Northumberland, say thus the king returns:</line>
<line>His noble cousin is right welcome hither;</line>
<line>And all the number of his fair demands</line>
<line>Shall be accomplish'd without contradiction:</line>
<line>With all the gracious utterance thou hast</line>
<line>Speak to his gentle hearing kind commends.</line>
<line>We do debase ourselves, cousin, do we not,</line>
<para role="stagedir">To DUKE OF AUMERLE</para>
<line>To look so poorly and to speak so fair?</line>
<line>Shall we call back Northumberland, and send</line>
<line>Defiance to the traitor, and so die?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>No, good my lord; let's fight with gentle words</line>
<line>Till time lend friends and friends their helpful swords.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>O God, O God! that e'er this tongue of mine,</line>
<line>That laid the sentence of dread banishment</line>
<line>On yon proud man, should take it off again</line>
<line>With words of sooth! O that I were as great</line>
<line>As is my grief, or lesser than my name!</line>
<line>Or that I could forget what I have been,</line>
<line>Or not remember what I must be now!</line>
<line>Swell'st thou, proud heart? I'll give thee scope to beat,</line>
<line>Since foes have scope to beat both thee and me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Northumberland comes back from Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>What must the king do now? must he submit?</line>
<line>The king shall do it: must he be deposed?</line>
<line>The king shall be contented: must he lose</line>
<line>The name of king? o' God's name, let it go:</line>
<line>I'll give my jewels for a set of beads,</line>
<line>My gorgeous palace for a hermitage,</line>
<line>My gay apparel for an almsman's gown,</line>
<line>My figured goblets for a dish of wood,</line>
<line>My sceptre for a palmer's walking staff,</line>
<line>My subjects for a pair of carved saints</line>
<line>And my large kingdom for a little grave,</line>
<line>A little little grave, an obscure grave;</line>
<line>Or I'll be buried in the king's highway,</line>
<line>Some way of common trade, where subjects' feet</line>
<line>May hourly trample on their sovereign's head;</line>
<line>For on my heart they tread now whilst I live;</line>
<line>And buried once, why not upon my head?</line>
<line>Aumerle, thou weep'st, my tender-hearted cousin!</line>
<line>We'll make foul weather with despised tears;</line>
<line>Our sighs and they shall lodge the summer corn,</line>
<line>And make a dearth in this revolting land.</line>
<line>Or shall we play the wantons with our woes,</line>
<line>And make some pretty match with shedding tears?</line>
<line>As thus, to drop them still upon one place,</line>
<line>Till they have fretted us a pair of graves</line>
<line>Within the earth; and, therein laid,--there lies</line>
<line>Two kinsmen digg'd their graves with weeping eyes.</line>
<line>Would not this ill do well? Well, well, I see</line>
<line>I talk but idly, and you laugh at me.</line>
<line>Most mighty prince, my Lord Northumberland,</line>
<line>What says King Bolingbroke? will his majesty</line>
<line>Give Richard leave to live till Richard die?</line>
<line>You make a leg, and Bolingbroke says ay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My lord, in the base court he doth attend</line>
<line>To speak with you; may it please you to come down.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Down, down I come; like glistering Phaethon,</line>
<line>Wanting the manage of unruly jades.</line>
<line>In the base court? Base court, where kings grow base,</line>
<line>To come at traitors' calls and do them grace.</line>
<line>In the base court? Come down? Down, court!</line>
<line>down, king!</line>
<line>For night-owls shriek where mounting larks</line>
<line>should sing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt from above</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>What says his majesty?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Sorrow and grief of heart</line>
<line>Makes him speak fondly, like a frantic man</line>
<line>Yet he is come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter KING RICHARD and his attendants below</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Stand all apart,</line>
<line>And show fair duty to his majesty.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He kneels down</para>
<line>My gracious lord,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Fair cousin, you debase your princely knee</line>
<line>To make the base earth proud with kissing it:</line>
<line>Me rather had my heart might feel your love</line>
<line>Than my unpleased eye see your courtesy.</line>
<line>Up, cousin, up; your heart is up, I know,</line>
<line>Thus high at least, although your knee be low.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>My gracious lord, I come but for mine own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Your own is yours, and I am yours, and all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>So far be mine, my most redoubted lord,</line>
<line>As my true service shall deserve your love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Well you deserve: they well deserve to have,</line>
<line>That know the strong'st and surest way to get.</line>
<line>Uncle, give me your hands: nay, dry your eyes;</line>
<line>Tears show their love, but want their remedies.</line>
<line>Cousin, I am too young to be your father,</line>
<line>Though you are old enough to be my heir.</line>
<line>What you will have, I'll give, and willing too;</line>
<line>For do we must what force will have us do.</line>
<line>Set on towards London, cousin, is it so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Yea, my good lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Then I must not say no.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  LANGLEY. The DUKE OF YORK's garden.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter the QUEEN and two Ladies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>What sport shall we devise here in this garden,</line>
<line>To drive away the heavy thought of care?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lady</speaker>
<line>Madam, we'll play at bowls.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>'Twill make me think the world is full of rubs,</line>
<line>And that my fortune rubs against the bias.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lady</speaker>
<line>Madam, we'll dance.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>My legs can keep no measure in delight,</line>
<line>When my poor heart no measure keeps in grief:</line>
<line>Therefore, no dancing, girl; some other sport.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lady</speaker>
<line>Madam, we'll tell tales.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Of sorrow or of joy?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lady</speaker>
<line>Of either, madam.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Of neither, girl:</line>
<line>For of joy, being altogether wanting,</line>
<line>It doth remember me the more of sorrow;</line>
<line>Or if of grief, being altogether had,</line>
<line>It adds more sorrow to my want of joy:</line>
<line>For what I have I need not to repeat;</line>
<line>And what I want it boots not to complain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lady</speaker>
<line>Madam, I'll sing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>'Tis well that thou hast cause</line>
<line>But thou shouldst please me better, wouldst thou weep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lady</speaker>
<line>I could weep, madam, would it do you good.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>And I could sing, would weeping do me good,</line>
<line>And never borrow any tear of thee.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Gardener, and two Servants</para>
<line>But stay, here come the gardeners:</line>
<line>Let's step into the shadow of these trees.</line>
<line>My wretchedness unto a row of pins,</line>
<line>They'll talk of state; for every one doth so</line>
<line>Against a change; woe is forerun with woe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">QUEEN and Ladies retire</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Gardener</speaker>
<line>Go, bind thou up yon dangling apricocks,</line>
<line>Which, like unruly children, make their sire</line>
<line>Stoop with oppression of their prodigal weight:</line>
<line>Give some supportance to the bending twigs.</line>
<line>Go thou, and like an executioner,</line>
<line>Cut off the heads of too fast growing sprays,</line>
<line>That look too lofty in our commonwealth:</line>
<line>All must be even in our government.</line>
<line>You thus employ'd, I will go root away</line>
<line>The noisome weeds, which without profit suck</line>
<line>The soil's fertility from wholesome flowers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>Why should we in the compass of a pale</line>
<line>Keep law and form and due proportion,</line>
<line>Showing, as in a model, our firm estate,</line>
<line>When our sea-walled garden, the whole land,</line>
<line>Is full of weeds, her fairest flowers choked up,</line>
<line>Her fruit-trees all upturned, her hedges ruin'd,</line>
<line>Her knots disorder'd and her wholesome herbs</line>
<line>Swarming with caterpillars?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Gardener</speaker>
<line>Hold thy peace:</line>
<line>He that hath suffer'd this disorder'd spring</line>
<line>Hath now himself met with the fall of leaf:</line>
<line>The weeds which his broad-spreading leaves did shelter,</line>
<line>That seem'd in eating him to hold him up,</line>
<line>Are pluck'd up root and all by Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>I mean the Earl of Wiltshire, Bushy, Green.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>What, are they dead?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Gardener</speaker>
<line>They are; and Bolingbroke</line>
<line>Hath seized the wasteful king. O, what pity is it</line>
<line>That he had not so trimm'd and dress'd his land</line>
<line>As we this garden! We at time of year</line>
<line>Do wound the bark, the skin of our fruit-trees,</line>
<line>Lest, being over-proud in sap and blood,</line>
<line>With too much riches it confound itself:</line>
<line>Had he done so to great and growing men,</line>
<line>They might have lived to bear and he to taste</line>
<line>Their fruits of duty: superfluous branches</line>
<line>We lop away, that bearing boughs may live:</line>
<line>Had he done so, himself had borne the crown,</line>
<line>Which waste of idle hours hath quite thrown down.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>What, think you then the king shall be deposed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Gardener</speaker>
<line>Depress'd he is already, and deposed</line>
<line>'Tis doubt he will be: letters came last night</line>
<line>To a dear friend of the good Duke of York's,</line>
<line>That tell black tidings.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>O, I am press'd to death through want of speaking!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Coming forward</para>
<line>Thou, old Adam's likeness, set to dress this garden,</line>
<line>How dares thy harsh rude tongue sound this unpleasing news?</line>
<line>What Eve, what serpent, hath suggested thee</line>
<line>To make a second fall of cursed man?</line>
<line>Why dost thou say King Richard is deposed?</line>
<line>Darest thou, thou little better thing than earth,</line>
<line>Divine his downfall? Say, where, when, and how,</line>
<line>Camest thou by this ill tidings? speak, thou wretch.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Gardener</speaker>
<line>Pardon me, madam: little joy have I</line>
<line>To breathe this news; yet what I say is true.</line>
<line>King Richard, he is in the mighty hold</line>
<line>Of Bolingbroke: their fortunes both are weigh'd:</line>
<line>In your lord's scale is nothing but himself,</line>
<line>And some few vanities that make him light;</line>
<line>But in the balance of great Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>Besides himself, are all the English peers,</line>
<line>And with that odds he weighs King Richard down.</line>
<line>Post you to London, and you will find it so;</line>
<line>I speak no more than every one doth know.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Nimble mischance, that art so light of foot,</line>
<line>Doth not thy embassage belong to me,</line>
<line>And am I last that knows it? O, thou think'st</line>
<line>To serve me last, that I may longest keep</line>
<line>Thy sorrow in my breast. Come, ladies, go,</line>
<line>To meet at London London's king in woe.</line>
<line>What, was I born to this, that my sad look</line>
<line>Should grace the triumph of great Bolingbroke?</line>
<line>Gardener, for telling me these news of woe,</line>
<line>Pray God the plants thou graft'st may never grow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt QUEEN and Ladies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">GARDENER</speaker>
<line>Poor queen! so that thy state might be no worse,</line>
<line>I would my skill were subject to thy curse.</line>
<line>Here did she fall a tear; here in this place</line>
<line>I'll set a bank of rue, sour herb of grace:</line>
<line>Rue, even for ruth, here shortly shall be seen,</line>
<line>In the remembrance of a weeping queen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT IV</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Westminster Hall.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter, as to the Parliament, HENRY BOLINGBROKE,
DUKE OF AUMERLE, NORTHUMBERLAND, HENRY PERCY, LORD
FITZWATER, DUKE OF SURREY, the BISHOP OF CARLISLE,
the Abbot Of Westminster, and another Lord, Herald,
Officers, and BAGOT</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Call forth Bagot.</line>
<line>Now, Bagot, freely speak thy mind;</line>
<line>What thou dost know of noble Gloucester's death,</line>
<line>Who wrought it with the king, and who perform'd</line>
<line>The bloody office of his timeless end.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BAGOT</speaker>
<line>Then set before my face the Lord Aumerle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Cousin, stand forth, and look upon that man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BAGOT</speaker>
<line>My Lord Aumerle, I know your daring tongue</line>
<line>Scorns to unsay what once it hath deliver'd.</line>
<line>In that dead time when Gloucester's death was plotted,</line>
<line>I heard you say, 'Is not my arm of length,</line>
<line>That reacheth from the restful English court</line>
<line>As far as Calais, to mine uncle's head?'</line>
<line>Amongst much other talk, that very time,</line>
<line>I heard you say that you had rather refuse</line>
<line>The offer of an hundred thousand crowns</line>
<line>Than Bolingbroke's return to England;</line>
<line>Adding withal how blest this land would be</line>
<line>In this your cousin's death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Princes and noble lords,</line>
<line>What answer shall I make to this base man?</line>
<line>Shall I so much dishonour my fair stars,</line>
<line>On equal terms to give him chastisement?</line>
<line>Either I must, or have mine honour soil'd</line>
<line>With the attainder of his slanderous lips.</line>
<line>There is my gage, the manual seal of death,</line>
<line>That marks thee out for hell: I say, thou liest,</line>
<line>And will maintain what thou hast said is false</line>
<line>In thy heart-blood, though being all too base</line>
<line>To stain the temper of my knightly sword.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Bagot, forbear; thou shalt not take it up.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Excepting one, I would he were the best</line>
<line>In all this presence that hath moved me so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
<line>If that thy valour stand on sympathy,</line>
<line>There is my gage, Aumerle, in gage to thine:</line>
<line>By that fair sun which shows me where thou stand'st,</line>
<line>I heard thee say, and vauntingly thou spakest it</line>
<line>That thou wert cause of noble Gloucester's death.</line>
<line>If thou deny'st it twenty times, thou liest;</line>
<line>And I will turn thy falsehood to thy heart,</line>
<line>Where it was forged, with my rapier's point.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Thou darest not, coward, live to see that day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
<line>Now by my soul, I would it were this hour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Fitzwater, thou art damn'd to hell for this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>Aumerle, thou liest; his honour is as true</line>
<line>In this appeal as thou art all unjust;</line>
<line>And that thou art so, there I throw my gage,</line>
<line>To prove it on thee to the extremest point</line>
<line>Of mortal breathing: seize it, if thou darest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>An if I do not, may my hands rot off</line>
<line>And never brandish more revengeful steel</line>
<line>Over the glittering helmet of my foe!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Lord</speaker>
<line>I task the earth to the like, forsworn Aumerle;</line>
<line>And spur thee on with full as many lies</line>
<line>As may be holloa'd in thy treacherous ear</line>
<line>From sun to sun: there is my honour's pawn;</line>
<line>Engage it to the trial, if thou darest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Who sets me else? by heaven, I'll throw at all:</line>
<line>I have a thousand spirits in one breast,</line>
<line>To answer twenty thousand such as you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF SURREY</speaker>
<line>My Lord Fitzwater, I do remember well</line>
<line>The very time Aumerle and you did talk.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
<line>'Tis very true: you were in presence then;</line>
<line>And you can witness with me this is true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF SURREY</speaker>
<line>As false, by heaven, as heaven itself is true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
<line>Surrey, thou liest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF SURREY</speaker>
<line>Dishonourable boy!</line>
<line>That lie shall lie so heavy on my sword,</line>
<line>That it shall render vengeance and revenge</line>
<line>Till thou the lie-giver and that lie do lie</line>
<line>In earth as quiet as thy father's skull:</line>
<line>In proof whereof, there is my honour's pawn;</line>
<line>Engage it to the trial, if thou darest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
<line>How fondly dost thou spur a forward horse!</line>
<line>If I dare eat, or drink, or breathe, or live,</line>
<line>I dare meet Surrey in a wilderness,</line>
<line>And spit upon him, whilst I say he lies,</line>
<line>And lies, and lies: there is my bond of faith,</line>
<line>To tie thee to my strong correction.</line>
<line>As I intend to thrive in this new world,</line>
<line>Aumerle is guilty of my true appeal:</line>
<line>Besides, I heard the banish'd Norfolk say</line>
<line>That thou, Aumerle, didst send two of thy men</line>
<line>To execute the noble duke at Calais.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Some honest Christian trust me with a gage</line>
<line>That Norfolk lies: here do I throw down this,</line>
<line>If he may be repeal'd, to try his honour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>These differences shall all rest under gage</line>
<line>Till Norfolk be repeal'd: repeal'd he shall be,</line>
<line>And, though mine enemy, restored again</line>
<line>To all his lands and signories: when he's return'd,</line>
<line>Against Aumerle we will enforce his trial.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
<line>That honourable day shall ne'er be seen.</line>
<line>Many a time hath banish'd Norfolk fought</line>
<line>For Jesu Christ in glorious Christian field,</line>
<line>Streaming the ensign of the Christian cross</line>
<line>Against black pagans, Turks, and Saracens:</line>
<line>And toil'd with works of war, retired himself</line>
<line>To Italy; and there at Venice gave</line>
<line>His body to that pleasant country's earth,</line>
<line>And his pure soul unto his captain Christ,</line>
<line>Under whose colours he had fought so long.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Why, bishop, is Norfolk dead?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
<line>As surely as I live, my lord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Sweet peace conduct his sweet soul to the bosom</line>
<line>Of good old Abraham! Lords appellants,</line>
<line>Your differences shall all rest under gage</line>
<line>Till we assign you to your days of trial.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF YORK, attended</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Great Duke of Lancaster, I come to thee</line>
<line>From plume-pluck'd Richard; who with willing soul</line>
<line>Adopts thee heir, and his high sceptre yields</line>
<line>To the possession of thy royal hand:</line>
<line>Ascend his throne, descending now from him;</line>
<line>And long live Henry, fourth of that name!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>In God's name, I'll ascend the regal throne.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
<line>Marry. God forbid!</line>
<line>Worst in this royal presence may I speak,</line>
<line>Yet best beseeming me to speak the truth.</line>
<line>Would God that any in this noble presence</line>
<line>Were enough noble to be upright judge</line>
<line>Of noble Richard! then true noblesse would</line>
<line>Learn him forbearance from so foul a wrong.</line>
<line>What subject can give sentence on his king?</line>
<line>And who sits here that is not Richard's subject?</line>
<line>Thieves are not judged but they are by to hear,</line>
<line>Although apparent guilt be seen in them;</line>
<line>And shall the figure of God's majesty,</line>
<line>His captain, steward, deputy-elect,</line>
<line>Anointed, crowned, planted many years,</line>
<line>Be judged by subject and inferior breath,</line>
<line>And he himself not present? O, forfend it, God,</line>
<line>That in a Christian climate souls refined</line>
<line>Should show so heinous, black, obscene a deed!</line>
<line>I speak to subjects, and a subject speaks,</line>
<line>Stirr'd up by God, thus boldly for his king:</line>
<line>My Lord of Hereford here, whom you call king,</line>
<line>Is a foul traitor to proud Hereford's king:</line>
<line>And if you crown him, let me prophesy:</line>
<line>The blood of English shall manure the ground,</line>
<line>And future ages groan for this foul act;</line>
<line>Peace shall go sleep with Turks and infidels,</line>
<line>And in this seat of peace tumultuous wars</line>
<line>Shall kin with kin and kind with kind confound;</line>
<line>Disorder, horror, fear and mutiny</line>
<line>Shall here inhabit, and this land be call'd</line>
<line>The field of Golgotha and dead men's skulls.</line>
<line>O, if you raise this house against this house,</line>
<line>It will the woefullest division prove</line>
<line>That ever fell upon this cursed earth.</line>
<line>Prevent it, resist it, let it not be so,</line>
<line>Lest child, child's children, cry against you woe!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Well have you argued, sir; and, for your pains,</line>
<line>Of capital treason we arrest you here.</line>
<line>My Lord of Westminster, be it your charge</line>
<line>To keep him safely till his day of trial.</line>
<line>May it please you, lords, to grant the commons' suit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Fetch hither Richard, that in common view</line>
<line>He may surrender; so we shall proceed</line>
<line>Without suspicion.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I will be his conduct.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Lords, you that here are under our arrest,</line>
<line>Procure your sureties for your days of answer.</line>
<line>Little are we beholding to your love,</line>
<line>And little look'd for at your helping hands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter DUKE OF YORK, with KING RICHARD II, and
Officers bearing the regalia</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Alack, why am I sent for to a king,</line>
<line>Before I have shook off the regal thoughts</line>
<line>Wherewith I reign'd? I hardly yet have learn'd</line>
<line>To insinuate, flatter, bow, and bend my limbs:</line>
<line>Give sorrow leave awhile to tutor me</line>
<line>To this submission. Yet I well remember</line>
<line>The favours of these men: were they not mine?</line>
<line>Did they not sometime cry, 'all hail!' to me?</line>
<line>So Judas did to Christ: but he, in twelve,</line>
<line>Found truth in all but one: I, in twelve thousand, none.</line>
<line>God save the king! Will no man say amen?</line>
<line>Am I both priest and clerk? well then, amen.</line>
<line>God save the king! although I be not he;</line>
<line>And yet, amen, if heaven do think him me.</line>
<line>To do what service am I sent for hither?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>To do that office of thine own good will</line>
<line>Which tired majesty did make thee offer,</line>
<line>The resignation of thy state and crown</line>
<line>To Henry Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Give me the crown. Here, cousin, seize the crown;</line>
<line>Here cousin:</line>
<line>On this side my hand, and on that side yours.</line>
<line>Now is this golden crown like a deep well</line>
<line>That owes two buckets, filling one another,</line>
<line>The emptier ever dancing in the air,</line>
<line>The other down, unseen and full of water:</line>
<line>That bucket down and full of tears am I,</line>
<line>Drinking my griefs, whilst you mount up on high.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I thought you had been willing to resign.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>My crown I am; but still my griefs are mine:</line>
<line>You may my glories and my state depose,</line>
<line>But not my griefs; still am I king of those.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Part of your cares you give me with your crown.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Your cares set up do not pluck my cares down.</line>
<line>My care is loss of care, by old care done;</line>
<line>Your care is gain of care, by new care won:</line>
<line>The cares I give I have, though given away;</line>
<line>They tend the crown, yet still with me they stay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Are you contented to resign the crown?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Ay, no; no, ay; for I must nothing be;</line>
<line>Therefore no no, for I resign to thee.</line>
<line>Now mark me, how I will undo myself;</line>
<line>I give this heavy weight from off my head</line>
<line>And this unwieldy sceptre from my hand,</line>
<line>The pride of kingly sway from out my heart;</line>
<line>With mine own tears I wash away my balm,</line>
<line>With mine own hands I give away my crown,</line>
<line>With mine own tongue deny my sacred state,</line>
<line>With mine own breath release all duty's rites:</line>
<line>All pomp and majesty I do forswear;</line>
<line>My manors, rents, revenues I forego;</line>
<line>My acts, decrees, and statutes I deny:</line>
<line>God pardon all oaths that are broke to me!</line>
<line>God keep all vows unbroke that swear to thee!</line>
<line>Make me, that nothing have, with nothing grieved,</line>
<line>And thou with all pleased, that hast all achieved!</line>
<line>Long mayst thou live in Richard's seat to sit,</line>
<line>And soon lie Richard in an earthly pit!</line>
<line>God save King Harry, unking'd Richard says,</line>
<line>And send him many years of sunshine days!</line>
<line>What more remains?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>No more, but that you read</line>
<line>These accusations and these grievous crimes</line>
<line>Committed by your person and your followers</line>
<line>Against the state and profit of this land;</line>
<line>That, by confessing them, the souls of men</line>
<line>May deem that you are worthily deposed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Must I do so? and must I ravel out</line>
<line>My weaved-up folly? Gentle Northumberland,</line>
<line>If thy offences were upon record,</line>
<line>Would it not shame thee in so fair a troop</line>
<line>To read a lecture of them? If thou wouldst,</line>
<line>There shouldst thou find one heinous article,</line>
<line>Containing the deposing of a king</line>
<line>And cracking the strong warrant of an oath,</line>
<line>Mark'd with a blot, damn'd in the book of heaven:</line>
<line>Nay, all of you that stand and look upon,</line>
<line>Whilst that my wretchedness doth bait myself,</line>
<line>Though some of you with Pilate wash your hands</line>
<line>Showing an outward pity; yet you Pilates</line>
<line>Have here deliver'd me to my sour cross,</line>
<line>And water cannot wash away your sin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My lord, dispatch; read o'er these articles.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Mine eyes are full of tears, I cannot see:</line>
<line>And yet salt water blinds them not so much</line>
<line>But they can see a sort of traitors here.</line>
<line>Nay, if I turn mine eyes upon myself,</line>
<line>I find myself a traitor with the rest;</line>
<line>For I have given here my soul's consent</line>
<line>To undeck the pompous body of a king;</line>
<line>Made glory base and sovereignty a slave,</line>
<line>Proud majesty a subject, state a peasant.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My lord,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>No lord of thine, thou haught insulting man,</line>
<line>Nor no man's lord; I have no name, no title,</line>
<line>No, not that name was given me at the font,</line>
<line>But 'tis usurp'd: alack the heavy day,</line>
<line>That I have worn so many winters out,</line>
<line>And know not now what name to call myself!</line>
<line>O that I were a mockery king of snow,</line>
<line>Standing before the sun of Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>To melt myself away in water-drops!</line>
<line>Good king, great king, and yet not greatly good,</line>
<line>An if my word be sterling yet in England,</line>
<line>Let it command a mirror hither straight,</line>
<line>That it may show me what a face I have,</line>
<line>Since it is bankrupt of his majesty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Go some of you and fetch a looking-glass.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit an attendant</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>Read o'er this paper while the glass doth come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Fiend, thou torment'st me ere I come to hell!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Urge it no more, my Lord Northumberland.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>The commons will not then be satisfied.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>They shall be satisfied: I'll read enough,</line>
<line>When I do see the very book indeed</line>
<line>Where all my sins are writ, and that's myself.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter Attendant, with a glass</para>
<line>Give me the glass, and therein will I read.</line>
<line>No deeper wrinkles yet? hath sorrow struck</line>
<line>So many blows upon this face of mine,</line>
<line>And made no deeper wounds? O flattering glass,</line>
<line>Like to my followers in prosperity,</line>
<line>Thou dost beguile me! Was this face the face</line>
<line>That every day under his household roof</line>
<line>Did keep ten thousand men? was this the face</line>
<line>That, like the sun, did make beholders wink?</line>
<line>Was this the face that faced so many follies,</line>
<line>And was at last out-faced by Bolingbroke?</line>
<line>A brittle glory shineth in this face:</line>
<line>As brittle as the glory is the face;</line>
<para role="stagedir">Dashes the glass against the ground</para>
<line>For there it is, crack'd in a hundred shivers.</line>
<line>Mark, silent king, the moral of this sport,</line>
<line>How soon my sorrow hath destroy'd my face.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>The shadow of your sorrow hath destroy'd</line>
<line>The shadow or your face.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Say that again.</line>
<line>The shadow of my sorrow! ha! let's see:</line>
<line>'Tis very true, my grief lies all within;</line>
<line>And these external manners of laments</line>
<line>Are merely shadows to the unseen grief</line>
<line>That swells with silence in the tortured soul;</line>
<line>There lies the substance: and I thank thee, king,</line>
<line>For thy great bounty, that not only givest</line>
<line>Me cause to wail but teachest me the way</line>
<line>How to lament the cause. I'll beg one boon,</line>
<line>And then be gone and trouble you no more.</line>
<line>Shall I obtain it?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Name it, fair cousin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>'Fair cousin'? I am greater than a king:</line>
<line>For when I was a king, my flatterers</line>
<line>Were then but subjects; being now a subject,</line>
<line>I have a king here to my flatterer.</line>
<line>Being so great, I have no need to beg.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Yet ask.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>And shall I have?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>You shall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Then give me leave to go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Whither?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Whither you will, so I were from your sights.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Go, some of you convey him to the Tower.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>O, good! convey? conveyers are you all,</line>
<line>That rise thus nimbly by a true king's fall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt KING RICHARD II, some Lords, and a Guard</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>On Wednesday next we solemnly set down</line>
<line>Our coronation: lords, prepare yourselves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all except the BISHOP OF CARLISLE, the Abbot
of Westminster, and DUKE OF AUMERLE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Abbot</speaker>
<line>A woeful pageant have we here beheld.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
<line>The woe's to come; the children yet unborn.</line>
<line>Shall feel this day as sharp to them as thorn.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>You holy clergymen, is there no plot</line>
<line>To rid the realm of this pernicious blot?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Abbot</speaker>
<line>My lord,</line>
<line>Before I freely speak my mind herein,</line>
<line>You shall not only take the sacrament</line>
<line>To bury mine intents, but also to effect</line>
<line>Whatever I shall happen to devise.</line>
<line>I see your brows are full of discontent,</line>
<line>Your hearts of sorrow and your eyes of tears:</line>
<line>Come home with me to supper; and I'll lay</line>
<line>A plot shall show us all a merry day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT V</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  London. A street leading to the Tower.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter QUEEN and Ladies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>This way the king will come; this is the way</line>
<line>To Julius Caesar's ill-erected tower,</line>
<line>To whose flint bosom my condemned lord</line>
<line>Is doom'd a prisoner by proud Bolingbroke:</line>
<line>Here let us rest, if this rebellious earth</line>
<line>Have any resting for her true king's queen.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING RICHARD II and Guard</para>
<line>But soft, but see, or rather do not see,</line>
<line>My fair rose wither: yet look up, behold,</line>
<line>That you in pity may dissolve to dew,</line>
<line>And wash him fresh again with true-love tears.</line>
<line>Ah, thou, the model where old Troy did stand,</line>
<line>Thou map of honour, thou King Richard's tomb,</line>
<line>And not King Richard; thou most beauteous inn,</line>
<line>Why should hard-favour'd grief be lodged in thee,</line>
<line>When triumph is become an alehouse guest?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Join not with grief, fair woman, do not so,</line>
<line>To make my end too sudden: learn, good soul,</line>
<line>To think our former state a happy dream;</line>
<line>From which awaked, the truth of what we are</line>
<line>Shows us but this: I am sworn brother, sweet,</line>
<line>To grim Necessity, and he and I</line>
<line>Will keep a league till death. Hie thee to France</line>
<line>And cloister thee in some religious house:</line>
<line>Our holy lives must win a new world's crown,</line>
<line>Which our profane hours here have stricken down.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>What, is my Richard both in shape and mind</line>
<line>Transform'd and weaken'd? hath Bolingbroke deposed</line>
<line>Thine intellect? hath he been in thy heart?</line>
<line>The lion dying thrusteth forth his paw,</line>
<line>And wounds the earth, if nothing else, with rage</line>
<line>To be o'erpower'd; and wilt thou, pupil-like,</line>
<line>Take thy correction mildly, kiss the rod,</line>
<line>And fawn on rage with base humility,</line>
<line>Which art a lion and a king of beasts?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>A king of beasts, indeed; if aught but beasts,</line>
<line>I had been still a happy king of men.</line>
<line>Good sometime queen, prepare thee hence for France:</line>
<line>Think I am dead and that even here thou takest,</line>
<line>As from my death-bed, thy last living leave.</line>
<line>In winter's tedious nights sit by the fire</line>
<line>With good old folks and let them tell thee tales</line>
<line>Of woeful ages long ago betid;</line>
<line>And ere thou bid good night, to quit their griefs,</line>
<line>Tell thou the lamentable tale of me</line>
<line>And send the hearers weeping to their beds:</line>
<line>For why, the senseless brands will sympathize</line>
<line>The heavy accent of thy moving tongue</line>
<line>And in compassion weep the fire out;</line>
<line>And some will mourn in ashes, some coal-black,</line>
<line>For the deposing of a rightful king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter NORTHUMBERLAND and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My lord, the mind of Bolingbroke is changed:</line>
<line>You must to Pomfret, not unto the Tower.</line>
<line>And, madam, there is order ta'en for you;</line>
<line>With all swift speed you must away to France.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Northumberland, thou ladder wherewithal</line>
<line>The mounting Bolingbroke ascends my throne,</line>
<line>The time shall not be many hours of age</line>
<line>More than it is ere foul sin gathering head</line>
<line>Shalt break into corruption: thou shalt think,</line>
<line>Though he divide the realm and give thee half,</line>
<line>It is too little, helping him to all;</line>
<line>And he shall think that thou, which know'st the way</line>
<line>To plant unrightful kings, wilt know again,</line>
<line>Being ne'er so little urged, another way</line>
<line>To pluck him headlong from the usurped throne.</line>
<line>The love of wicked men converts to fear;</line>
<line>That fear to hate, and hate turns one or both</line>
<line>To worthy danger and deserved death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>My guilt be on my head, and there an end.</line>
<line>Take leave and part; for you must part forthwith.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Doubly divorced! Bad men, you violate</line>
<line>A twofold marriage, 'twixt my crown and me,</line>
<line>And then betwixt me and my married wife.</line>
<line>Let me unkiss the oath 'twixt thee and me;</line>
<line>And yet not so, for with a kiss 'twas made.</line>
<line>Part us, Northumberland; I toward the north,</line>
<line>Where shivering cold and sickness pines the clime;</line>
<line>My wife to France: from whence, set forth in pomp,</line>
<line>She came adorned hither like sweet May,</line>
<line>Sent back like Hallowmas or short'st of day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>And must we be divided? must we part?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Ay, hand from hand, my love, and heart from heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Banish us both and send the king with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>That were some love but little policy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Then whither he goes, thither let me go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>So two, together weeping, make one woe.</line>
<line>Weep thou for me in France, I for thee here;</line>
<line>Better far off than near, be ne'er the near.</line>
<line>Go, count thy way with sighs; I mine with groans.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>So longest way shall have the longest moans.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Twice for one step I'll groan, the way being short,</line>
<line>And piece the way out with a heavy heart.</line>
<line>Come, come, in wooing sorrow let's be brief,</line>
<line>Since, wedding it, there is such length in grief;</line>
<line>One kiss shall stop our mouths, and dumbly part;</line>
<line>Thus give I mine, and thus take I thy heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUEEN</speaker>
<line>Give me mine own again; 'twere no good part</line>
<line>To take on me to keep and kill thy heart.</line>
<line>So, now I have mine own again, be gone,</line>
<line>That I might strive to kill it with a groan.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>We make woe wanton with this fond delay:</line>
<line>Once more, adieu; the rest let sorrow say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The DUKE OF YORK's palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF YORK and DUCHESS OF YORK</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>My lord, you told me you would tell the rest,</line>
<line>When weeping made you break the story off,</line>
<line>of our two cousins coming into London.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Where did I leave?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>At that sad stop, my lord,</line>
<line>Where rude misgovern'd hands from windows' tops</line>
<line>Threw dust and rubbish on King Richard's head.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Then, as I said, the duke, great Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>Mounted upon a hot and fiery steed</line>
<line>Which his aspiring rider seem'd to know,</line>
<line>With slow but stately pace kept on his course,</line>
<line>Whilst all tongues cried 'God save thee,</line>
<line>Bolingbroke!'</line>
<line>You would have thought the very windows spake,</line>
<line>So many greedy looks of young and old</line>
<line>Through casements darted their desiring eyes</line>
<line>Upon his visage, and that all the walls</line>
<line>With painted imagery had said at once</line>
<line>'Jesu preserve thee! welcome, Bolingbroke!'</line>
<line>Whilst he, from the one side to the other turning,</line>
<line>Bareheaded, lower than his proud steed's neck,</line>
<line>Bespake them thus: 'I thank you, countrymen:'</line>
<line>And thus still doing, thus he pass'd along.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Alack, poor Richard! where rode he the whilst?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>As in a theatre, the eyes of men,</line>
<line>After a well-graced actor leaves the stage,</line>
<line>Are idly bent on him that enters next,</line>
<line>Thinking his prattle to be tedious;</line>
<line>Even so, or with much more contempt, men's eyes</line>
<line>Did scowl on gentle Richard; no man cried 'God save him!'</line>
<line>No joyful tongue gave him his welcome home:</line>
<line>But dust was thrown upon his sacred head:</line>
<line>Which with such gentle sorrow he shook off,</line>
<line>His face still combating with tears and smiles,</line>
<line>The badges of his grief and patience,</line>
<line>That had not God, for some strong purpose, steel'd</line>
<line>The hearts of men, they must perforce have melted</line>
<line>And barbarism itself have pitied him.</line>
<line>But heaven hath a hand in these events,</line>
<line>To whose high will we bound our calm contents.</line>
<line>To Bolingbroke are we sworn subjects now,</line>
<line>Whose state and honour I for aye allow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Here comes my son Aumerle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Aumerle that was;</line>
<line>But that is lost for being Richard's friend,</line>
<line>And, madam, you must call him Rutland now:</line>
<line>I am in parliament pledge for his truth</line>
<line>And lasting fealty to the new-made king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF AUMERLE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Welcome, my son: who are the violets now</line>
<line>That strew the green lap of the new come spring?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Madam, I know not, nor I greatly care not:</line>
<line>God knows I had as lief be none as one.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Well, bear you well in this new spring of time,</line>
<line>Lest you be cropp'd before you come to prime.</line>
<line>What news from Oxford? hold those justs and triumphs?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>For aught I know, my lord, they do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>You will be there, I know.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>If God prevent not, I purpose so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>What seal is that, that hangs without thy bosom?</line>
<line>Yea, look'st thou pale? let me see the writing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>My lord, 'tis nothing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>No matter, then, who see it;</line>
<line>I will be satisfied; let me see the writing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>I do beseech your grace to pardon me:</line>
<line>It is a matter of small consequence,</line>
<line>Which for some reasons I would not have seen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Which for some reasons, sir, I mean to see.</line>
<line>I fear, I fear,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>What should you fear?</line>
<line>'Tis nothing but some bond, that he is enter'd into</line>
<line>For gay apparel 'gainst the triumph day.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Bound to himself! what doth he with a bond</line>
<line>That he is bound to? Wife, thou art a fool.</line>
<line>Boy, let me see the writing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>I do beseech you, pardon me; I may not show it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I will be satisfied; let me see it, I say.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He plucks it out of his bosom and reads it</para>
<line>Treason! foul treason! Villain! traitor! slave!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>What is the matter, my lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Ho! who is within there?</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Servant</para>
<line>Saddle my horse.</line>
<line>God for his mercy, what treachery is here!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Why, what is it, my lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Give me my boots, I say; saddle my horse.</line>
<line>Now, by mine honour, by my life, by my troth,</line>
<line>I will appeach the villain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>What is the matter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Peace, foolish woman.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I will not peace. What is the matter, Aumerle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Good mother, be content; it is no more</line>
<line>Than my poor life must answer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Thy life answer!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Bring me my boots: I will unto the king.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter Servant with boots</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Strike him, Aumerle. Poor boy, thou art amazed.</line>
<line>Hence, villain! never more come in my sight.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Give me my boots, I say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Why, York, what wilt thou do?</line>
<line>Wilt thou not hide the trespass of thine own?</line>
<line>Have we more sons? or are we like to have?</line>
<line>Is not my teeming date drunk up with time?</line>
<line>And wilt thou pluck my fair son from mine age,</line>
<line>And rob me of a happy mother's name?</line>
<line>Is he not like thee? is he not thine own?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Thou fond mad woman,</line>
<line>Wilt thou conceal this dark conspiracy?</line>
<line>A dozen of them here have ta'en the sacrament,</line>
<line>And interchangeably set down their hands,</line>
<line>To kill the king at Oxford.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>He shall be none;</line>
<line>We'll keep him here: then what is that to him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Away, fond woman! were he twenty times my son,</line>
<line>I would appeach him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Hadst thou groan'd for him</line>
<line>As I have done, thou wouldst be more pitiful.</line>
<line>But now I know thy mind; thou dost suspect</line>
<line>That I have been disloyal to thy bed,</line>
<line>And that he is a bastard, not thy son:</line>
<line>Sweet York, sweet husband, be not of that mind:</line>
<line>He is as like thee as a man may be,</line>
<line>Not like to me, or any of my kin,</line>
<line>And yet I love him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Make way, unruly woman!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>After, Aumerle! mount thee upon his horse;</line>
<line>Spur post, and get before him to the king,</line>
<line>And beg thy pardon ere he do accuse thee.</line>
<line>I'll not be long behind; though I be old,</line>
<line>I doubt not but to ride as fast as York:</line>
<line>And never will I rise up from the ground</line>
<line>Till Bolingbroke have pardon'd thee. Away, be gone!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  A royal palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE, HENRY PERCY, and other Lords</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Can no man tell me of my unthrifty son?</line>
<line>'Tis full three months since I did see him last;</line>
<line>If any plague hang over us, 'tis he.</line>
<line>I would to God, my lords, he might be found:</line>
<line>Inquire at London, 'mongst the taverns there,</line>
<line>For there, they say, he daily doth frequent,</line>
<line>With unrestrained loose companions,</line>
<line>Even such, they say, as stand in narrow lanes,</line>
<line>And beat our watch, and rob our passengers;</line>
<line>Which he, young wanton and effeminate boy,</line>
<line>Takes on the point of honour to support</line>
<line>So dissolute a crew.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>My lord, some two days since I saw the prince,</line>
<line>And told him of those triumphs held at Oxford.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>And what said the gallant?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>His answer was, he would unto the stews,</line>
<line>And from the common'st creature pluck a glove,</line>
<line>And wear it as a favour; and with that</line>
<line>He would unhorse the lustiest challenger.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>As dissolute as desperate; yet through both</line>
<line>I see some sparks of better hope, which elder years</line>
<line>May happily bring forth. But who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF AUMERLE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Where is the king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>What means our cousin, that he stares and looks</line>
<line>So wildly?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>God save your grace! I do beseech your majesty,</line>
<line>To have some conference with your grace alone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Withdraw yourselves, and leave us here alone.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt HENRY PERCY and Lords</para>
<line>What is the matter with our cousin now?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>For ever may my knees grow to the earth,</line>
<line>My tongue cleave to my roof within my mouth</line>
<line>Unless a pardon ere I rise or speak.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Intended or committed was this fault?</line>
<line>If on the first, how heinous e'er it be,</line>
<line>To win thy after-love I pardon thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Then give me leave that I may turn the key,</line>
<line>That no man enter till my tale be done.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Have thy desire.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  My liege, beware; look to thyself;</line>
<line>Thou hast a traitor in thy presence there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Villain, I'll make thee safe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Drawing</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Stay thy revengeful hand; thou hast no cause to fear.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  Open the door, secure, foolhardy king:</line>
<line>Shall I for love speak treason to thy face?</line>
<line>Open the door, or I will break it open.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUKE OF YORK</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>What is the matter, uncle? speak;</line>
<line>Recover breath; tell us how near is danger,</line>
<line>That we may arm us to encounter it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Peruse this writing here, and thou shalt know</line>
<line>The treason that my haste forbids me show.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Remember, as thou read'st, thy promise pass'd:</line>
<line>I do repent me; read not my name there</line>
<line>My heart is not confederate with my hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>It was, villain, ere thy hand did set it down.</line>
<line>I tore it from the traitor's bosom, king;</line>
<line>Fear, and not love, begets his penitence:</line>
<line>Forget to pity him, lest thy pity prove</line>
<line>A serpent that will sting thee to the heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>O heinous, strong and bold conspiracy!</line>
<line>O loyal father of a treacherous son!</line>
<line>Thou sheer, immaculate and silver fountain,</line>
<line>From when this stream through muddy passages</line>
<line>Hath held his current and defiled himself!</line>
<line>Thy overflow of good converts to bad,</line>
<line>And thy abundant goodness shall excuse</line>
<line>This deadly blot in thy digressing son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>So shall my virtue be his vice's bawd;</line>
<line>And he shall spend mine honour with his shame,</line>
<line>As thriftless sons their scraping fathers' gold.</line>
<line>Mine honour lives when his dishonour dies,</line>
<line>Or my shamed life in his dishonour lies:</line>
<line>Thou kill'st me in his life; giving him breath,</line>
<line>The traitor lives, the true man's put to death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Within</phrase>  What ho, my liege! for God's sake,</line>
<line>let me in.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>What shrill-voiced suppliant makes this eager cry?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>A woman, and thy aunt, great king; 'tis I.</line>
<line>Speak with me, pity me, open the door.</line>
<line>A beggar begs that never begg'd before.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Our scene is alter'd from a serious thing,</line>
<line>And now changed to 'The Beggar and the King.'</line>
<line>My dangerous cousin, let your mother in:</line>
<line>I know she is come to pray for your foul sin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>If thou do pardon, whosoever pray,</line>
<line>More sins for this forgiveness prosper may.</line>
<line>This fester'd joint cut off, the rest rest sound;</line>
<line>This let alone will all the rest confound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DUCHESS OF YORK</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>O king, believe not this hard-hearted man!</line>
<line>Love loving not itself none other can.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Thou frantic woman, what dost thou make here?</line>
<line>Shall thy old dugs once more a traitor rear?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Sweet York, be patient. Hear me, gentle liege.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Kneels</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Rise up, good aunt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Not yet, I thee beseech:</line>
<line>For ever will I walk upon my knees,</line>
<line>And never see day that the happy sees,</line>
<line>Till thou give joy; until thou bid me joy,</line>
<line>By pardoning Rutland, my transgressing boy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
<line>Unto my mother's prayers I bend my knee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Against them both my true joints bended be.</line>
<line>Ill mayst thou thrive, if thou grant any grace!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Pleads he in earnest? look upon his face;</line>
<line>His eyes do drop no tears, his prayers are in jest;</line>
<line>His words come from his mouth, ours from our breast:</line>
<line>He prays but faintly and would be denied;</line>
<line>We pray with heart and soul and all beside:</line>
<line>His weary joints would gladly rise, I know;</line>
<line>Our knees shall kneel till to the ground they grow:</line>
<line>His prayers are full of false hypocrisy;</line>
<line>Ours of true zeal and deep integrity.</line>
<line>Our prayers do out-pray his; then let them have</line>
<line>That mercy which true prayer ought to have.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Good aunt, stand up.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Nay, do not say, 'stand up;'</line>
<line>Say, 'pardon' first, and afterwards 'stand up.'</line>
<line>And if I were thy nurse, thy tongue to teach,</line>
<line>'Pardon' should be the first word of thy speech.</line>
<line>I never long'd to hear a word till now;</line>
<line>Say 'pardon,' king; let pity teach thee how:</line>
<line>The word is short, but not so short as sweet;</line>
<line>No word like 'pardon' for kings' mouths so meet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Speak it in French, king; say, 'pardonne moi.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Dost thou teach pardon pardon to destroy?</line>
<line>Ah, my sour husband, my hard-hearted lord,</line>
<line>That set'st the word itself against the word!</line>
<line>Speak 'pardon' as 'tis current in our land;</line>
<line>The chopping French we do not understand.</line>
<line>Thine eye begins to speak; set thy tongue there;</line>
<line>Or in thy piteous heart plant thou thine ear;</line>
<line>That hearing how our plaints and prayers do pierce,</line>
<line>Pity may move thee 'pardon' to rehearse.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Good aunt, stand up.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>I do not sue to stand;</line>
<line>Pardon is all the suit I have in hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>I pardon him, as God shall pardon me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>O happy vantage of a kneeling knee!</line>
<line>Yet am I sick for fear: speak it again;</line>
<line>Twice saying 'pardon' doth not pardon twain,</line>
<line>But makes one pardon strong.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>With all my heart</line>
<line>I pardon him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>A god on earth thou art.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>But for our trusty brother-in-law and the abbot,</line>
<line>With all the rest of that consorted crew,</line>
<line>Destruction straight shall dog them at the heels.</line>
<line>Good uncle, help to order several powers</line>
<line>To Oxford, or where'er these traitors are:</line>
<line>They shall not live within this world, I swear,</line>
<line>But I will have them, if I once know where.</line>
<line>Uncle, farewell: and, cousin too, adieu:</line>
<line>Your mother well hath pray'd, and prove you true.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
<line>Come, my old son: I pray God make thee new.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The same.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter EXTON and Servant</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EXTON</speaker>
<line>Didst thou not mark the king, what words he spake,</line>
<line>'Have I no friend will rid me of this living fear?'</line>
<line>Was it not so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>These were his very words.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EXTON</speaker>
<line>'Have I no friend?' quoth he: he spake it twice,</line>
<line>And urged it twice together, did he not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Servant</speaker>
<line>He did.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EXTON</speaker>
<line>And speaking it, he wistly look'd on me,</line>
<line>And who should say, 'I would thou wert the man'</line>
<line>That would divorce this terror from my heart;'</line>
<line>Meaning the king at Pomfret. Come, let's go:</line>
<line>I am the king's friend, and will rid his foe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE V.  Pomfret castle.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter KING RICHARD</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>I have been studying how I may compare</line>
<line>This prison where I live unto the world:</line>
<line>And for because the world is populous</line>
<line>And here is not a creature but myself,</line>
<line>I cannot do it; yet I'll hammer it out.</line>
<line>My brain I'll prove the female to my soul,</line>
<line>My soul the father; and these two beget</line>
<line>A generation of still-breeding thoughts,</line>
<line>And these same thoughts people this little world,</line>
<line>In humours like the people of this world,</line>
<line>For no thought is contented. The better sort,</line>
<line>As thoughts of things divine, are intermix'd</line>
<line>With scruples and do set the word itself</line>
<line>Against the word:</line>
<line>As thus, 'Come, little ones,' and then again,</line>
<line>'It is as hard to come as for a camel</line>
<line>To thread the postern of a small needle's eye.'</line>
<line>Thoughts tending to ambition, they do plot</line>
<line>Unlikely wonders; how these vain weak nails</line>
<line>May tear a passage through the flinty ribs</line>
<line>Of this hard world, my ragged prison walls,</line>
<line>And, for they cannot, die in their own pride.</line>
<line>Thoughts tending to content flatter themselves</line>
<line>That they are not the first of fortune's slaves,</line>
<line>Nor shall not be the last; like silly beggars</line>
<line>Who sitting in the stocks refuge their shame,</line>
<line>That many have and others must sit there;</line>
<line>And in this thought they find a kind of ease,</line>
<line>Bearing their own misfortunes on the back</line>
<line>Of such as have before endured the like.</line>
<line>Thus play I in one person many people,</line>
<line>And none contented: sometimes am I king;</line>
<line>Then treasons make me wish myself a beggar,</line>
<line>And so I am: then crushing penury</line>
<line>Persuades me I was better when a king;</line>
<line>Then am I king'd again: and by and by</line>
<line>Think that I am unking'd by Bolingbroke,</line>
<line>And straight am nothing: but whate'er I be,</line>
<line>Nor I nor any man that but man is</line>
<line>With nothing shall be pleased, till he be eased</line>
<line>With being nothing. Music do I hear?</line>
<para role="stagedir">Music</para>
<line>Ha, ha! keep time: how sour sweet music is,</line>
<line>When time is broke and no proportion kept!</line>
<line>So is it in the music of men's lives.</line>
<line>And here have I the daintiness of ear</line>
<line>To cheque time broke in a disorder'd string;</line>
<line>But for the concord of my state and time</line>
<line>Had not an ear to hear my true time broke.</line>
<line>I wasted time, and now doth time waste me;</line>
<line>For now hath time made me his numbering clock:</line>
<line>My thoughts are minutes; and with sighs they jar</line>
<line>Their watches on unto mine eyes, the outward watch,</line>
<line>Whereto my finger, like a dial's point,</line>
<line>Is pointing still, in cleansing them from tears.</line>
<line>Now sir, the sound that tells what hour it is</line>
<line>Are clamorous groans, which strike upon my heart,</line>
<line>Which is the bell: so sighs and tears and groans</line>
<line>Show minutes, times, and hours: but my time</line>
<line>Runs posting on in Bolingbroke's proud joy,</line>
<line>While I stand fooling here, his Jack o' the clock.</line>
<line>This music mads me; let it sound no more;</line>
<line>For though it have holp madmen to their wits,</line>
<line>In me it seems it will make wise men mad.</line>
<line>Yet blessing on his heart that gives it me!</line>
<line>For 'tis a sign of love; and love to Richard</line>
<line>Is a strange brooch in this all-hating world.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Groom of the Stable</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Groom</speaker>
<line>Hail, royal prince!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Thanks, noble peer;</line>
<line>The cheapest of us is ten groats too dear.</line>
<line>What art thou? and how comest thou hither,</line>
<line>Where no man never comes but that sad dog</line>
<line>That brings me food to make misfortune live?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Groom</speaker>
<line>I was a poor groom of thy stable, king,</line>
<line>When thou wert king; who, travelling towards York,</line>
<line>With much ado at length have gotten leave</line>
<line>To look upon my sometimes royal master's face.</line>
<line>O, how it yearn'd my heart when I beheld</line>
<line>In London streets, that coronation-day,</line>
<line>When Bolingbroke rode on roan Barbary,</line>
<line>That horse that thou so often hast bestrid,</line>
<line>That horse that I so carefully have dress'd!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Rode he on Barbary? Tell me, gentle friend,</line>
<line>How went he under him?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Groom</speaker>
<line>So proudly as if he disdain'd the ground.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>So proud that Bolingbroke was on his back!</line>
<line>That jade hath eat bread from my royal hand;</line>
<line>This hand hath made him proud with clapping him.</line>
<line>Would he not stumble? would he not fall down,</line>
<line>Since pride must have a fall, and break the neck</line>
<line>Of that proud man that did usurp his back?</line>
<line>Forgiveness, horse! why do I rail on thee,</line>
<line>Since thou, created to be awed by man,</line>
<line>Wast born to bear? I was not made a horse;</line>
<line>And yet I bear a burthen like an ass,</line>
<line>Spurr'd, gall'd and tired by jouncing Bolingbroke.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter Keeper, with a dish</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Keeper</speaker>
<line>Fellow, give place; here is no longer stay.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>If thou love me, 'tis time thou wert away.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Groom</speaker>
<line>What my tongue dares not, that my heart shall say.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Keeper</speaker>
<line>My lord, will't please you to fall to?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>Taste of it first, as thou art wont to do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Keeper</speaker>
<line>My lord, I dare not: Sir Pierce of Exton, who</line>
<line>lately came from the king, commands the contrary.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>The devil take Henry of Lancaster and thee!</line>
<line>Patience is stale, and I am weary of it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Beats the keeper</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Keeper</speaker>
<line>Help, help, help!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter EXTON and Servants, armed</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">KING RICHARD II</speaker>
<line>How now! what means death in this rude assault?</line>
<line>Villain, thy own hand yields thy death's instrument.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Snatching an axe from a Servant and killing him</para>
<line>Go thou, and fill another room in hell.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He kills another. Then Exton strikes him down</para>
<line>That hand shall burn in never-quenching fire</line>
<line>That staggers thus my person. Exton, thy fierce hand</line>
<line>Hath with the king's blood stain'd the king's own land.</line>
<line>Mount, mount, my soul! thy seat is up on high;</line>
<line>Whilst my gross flesh sinks downward, here to die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Dies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EXTON</speaker>
<line>As full of valour as of royal blood:</line>
<line>Both have I spill'd; O would the deed were good!</line>
<line>For now the devil, that told me I did well,</line>
<line>Says that this deed is chronicled in hell.</line>
<line>This dead king to the living king I'll bear</line>
<line>Take hence the rest, and give them burial here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE VI.  Windsor castle.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE, DUKE OF YORK,
with other Lords, and Attendants</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Kind uncle York, the latest news we hear</line>
<line>Is that the rebels have consumed with fire</line>
<line>Our town of Cicester in Gloucestershire;</line>
<line>But whether they be ta'en or slain we hear not.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter NORTHUMBERLAND</para>
<line>Welcome, my lord what is the news?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
<line>First, to thy sacred state wish I all happiness.</line>
<line>The next news is, I have to London sent</line>
<line>The heads of Oxford, Salisbury, Blunt, and Kent:</line>
<line>The manner of their taking may appear</line>
<line>At large discoursed in this paper here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>We thank thee, gentle Percy, for thy pains;</line>
<line>And to thy worth will add right worthy gains.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter LORD FITZWATER</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
<line>My lord, I have from Oxford sent to London</line>
<line>The heads of Brocas and Sir Bennet Seely,</line>
<line>Two of the dangerous consorted traitors</line>
<line>That sought at Oxford thy dire overthrow.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Thy pains, Fitzwater, shall not be forgot;</line>
<line>Right noble is thy merit, well I wot.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter HENRY PERCY, and the BISHOP OF CARLISLE</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY PERCY</speaker>
<line>The grand conspirator, Abbot of Westminster,</line>
<line>With clog of conscience and sour melancholy</line>
<line>Hath yielded up his body to the grave;</line>
<line>But here is Carlisle living, to abide</line>
<line>Thy kingly doom and sentence of his pride.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Carlisle, this is your doom:</line>
<line>Choose out some secret place, some reverend room,</line>
<line>More than thou hast, and with it joy thy life;</line>
<line>So as thou livest in peace, die free from strife:</line>
<line>For though mine enemy thou hast ever been,</line>
<line>High sparks of honour in thee have I seen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter EXTON, with persons bearing a coffin</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EXTON</speaker>
<line>Great king, within this coffin I present</line>
<line>Thy buried fear: herein all breathless lies</line>
<line>The mightiest of thy greatest enemies,</line>
<line>Richard of Bordeaux, by me hither brought.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>Exton, I thank thee not; for thou hast wrought</line>
<line>A deed of slander with thy fatal hand</line>
<line>Upon my head and all this famous land.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">EXTON</speaker>
<line>From your own mouth, my lord, did I this deed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
<line>They love not poison that do poison need,</line>
<line>Nor do I thee: though I did wish him dead,</line>
<line>I hate the murderer, love him murdered.</line>
<line>The guilt of conscience take thou for thy labour,</line>
<line>But neither my good word nor princely favour:</line>
<line>With Cain go wander through shades of night,</line>
<line>And never show thy head by day nor light.</line>
<line>Lords, I protest, my soul is full of woe,</line>
<line>That blood should sprinkle me to make me grow:</line>
<line>Come, mourn with me for that I do lament,</line>
<line>And put on sullen black incontinent:</line>
<line>I'll make a voyage to the Holy Land,</line>
<line>To wash this blood off from my guilty hand:</line>
<line>March sadly after; grace my mournings here;</line>
<line>In weeping after this untimely bier.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>