<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="publishers.rnc" type="compact"?><book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" role="play">
<title>The Tragedy of Titus Andronicus</title>

<info><author><personname><firstname>William</firstname><surname>Shakespeare</surname></personname></author><legalnotice>
<para>ASCII text placed in the public domain by Moby Lexical Tools, 1992.</para>
<para>SGML markup by Jon Bosak, 1992-1994.</para>
<para>XML version by Jon Bosak, 1996-1999.</para>
<para>The XML markup in this version is Copyright © 1999 Jon Bosak.
This work may freely be distributed on condition that it not be
modified or altered in any way.</para>
</legalnotice>     <copyright><year>2008</year><holder>Scott Hudson</holder></copyright></info>

<preface>
<title>Dramatis Personae</title>

<para><personname role="persona">SATURNINUS, son to the late Emperor of Rome, and afterwards declared Emperor.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">BASSIANUS, brother to Saturninus; in love with Lavinia.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">TITUS ANDRONICUS, a noble Roman, general against the Goths.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">MARCUS ANDRONICUS, tribune of the people, and brother to Titus.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">LUCIUS</personname><personname role="persona">QUINTUS</personname><personname role="persona">MARTIUS</personname><personname role="persona">MUTIUS</personname></member><member>sons to Titus Andronicus.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">Young LUCIUS, a boy, son to Lucius.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">PUBLIUS, son to Marcus the Tribune.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">SEMPRONIUS</personname><personname role="persona">CAIUS</personname><personname role="persona">VALENTINE</personname></member><member>kinsmen to Titus.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">AEMILIUS, a noble Roman.</personname></para>

<simplelist columns="2"><member><personname role="persona">ALARBUS</personname><personname role="persona">DEMETRIUS</personname><personname role="persona">CHIRON</personname></member><member>sons to Tamora.</member></simplelist>

<para><personname role="persona">AARON, a Moor, beloved by Tamora.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">A Captain, Tribune, Messenger, and Clown; Romans.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Goths and Romans.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">TAMORA, Queen of the Goths.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">LAVINIA, daughter of Titus Andronicus.</personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">A Nurse. </personname></para>
<para><personname role="persona">Senators, Tribunes, Officers, Soldiers, anAttendants.</personname></para>
    
    <para role="scndescr">SCENE  Rome, and the country near it.</para>
</preface>



<chapter role="act"><title>ACT I</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Rome. Before the Capitol.</title>
<para role="stagedir">The Tomb of the ANDRONICI appearing; the Tribunes
and Senators aloft. Enter, below, from one side,
SATURNINUS and his Followers; and, from the other
side, BASSIANUS and his Followers; with drum and colours</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Noble patricians, patrons of my right,</line>
<line>Defend the justice of my cause with arms,</line>
<line>And, countrymen, my loving followers,</line>
<line>Plead my successive title with your swords:</line>
<line>I am his first-born son, that was the last</line>
<line>That wore the imperial diadem of Rome;</line>
<line>Then let my father's honours live in me,</line>
<line>Nor wrong mine age with this indignity.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Romans, friends, followers, favorers of my right,</line>
<line>If ever Bassianus, Caesar's son,</line>
<line>Were gracious in the eyes of royal Rome,</line>
<line>Keep then this passage to the Capitol</line>
<line>And suffer not dishonour to approach</line>
<line>The imperial seat, to virtue consecrate,</line>
<line>To justice, continence and nobility;</line>
<line>But let desert in pure election shine,</line>
<line>And, Romans, fight for freedom in your choice.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter MARCUS ANDRONICUS, aloft, with the crown</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Princes, that strive by factions and by friends</line>
<line>Ambitiously for rule and empery,</line>
<line>Know that the people of Rome, for whom we stand</line>
<line>A special party, have, by common voice,</line>
<line>In election for the Roman empery,</line>
<line>Chosen Andronicus, surnamed Pius</line>
<line>For many good and great deserts to Rome:</line>
<line>A nobler man, a braver warrior,</line>
<line>Lives not this day within the city walls:</line>
<line>He by the senate is accit'd home</line>
<line>From weary wars against the barbarous Goths;</line>
<line>That, with his sons, a terror to our foes,</line>
<line>Hath yoked a nation strong, train'd up in arms.</line>
<line>Ten years are spent since first he undertook</line>
<line>This cause of Rome and chastised with arms</line>
<line>Our enemies' pride: five times he hath return'd</line>
<line>Bleeding to Rome, bearing his valiant sons</line>
<line>In coffins from the field;</line>
<line>And now at last, laden with horror's spoils,</line>
<line>Returns the good Andronicus to Rome,</line>
<line>Renowned Titus, flourishing in arms.</line>
<line>Let us entreat, by honour of his name,</line>
<line>Whom worthily you would have now succeed.</line>
<line>And in the Capitol and senate's right,</line>
<line>Whom you pretend to honour and adore,</line>
<line>That you withdraw you and abate your strength;</line>
<line>Dismiss your followers and, as suitors should,</line>
<line>Plead your deserts in peace and humbleness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>How fair the tribune speaks to calm my thoughts!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Marcus Andronicus, so I do ally</line>
<line>In thy uprightness and integrity,</line>
<line>And so I love and honour thee and thine,</line>
<line>Thy noble brother Titus and his sons,</line>
<line>And her to whom my thoughts are humbled all,</line>
<line>Gracious Lavinia, Rome's rich ornament,</line>
<line>That I will here dismiss my loving friends,</line>
<line>And to my fortunes and the people's favor</line>
<line>Commit my cause in balance to be weigh'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt the followers of BASSIANUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Friends, that have been thus forward in my right,</line>
<line>I thank you all and here dismiss you all,</line>
<line>And to the love and favor of my country</line>
<line>Commit myself, my person and the cause.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt the followers of SATURNINUS</para>
<line>Rome, be as just and gracious unto me</line>
<line>As I am confident and kind to thee.</line>
<line>Open the gates, and let me in.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Tribunes, and me, a poor competitor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. SATURNINUS and BASSIANUS go up into the Capitol</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Captain</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Captain</speaker>
<line>Romans, make way: the good Andronicus.</line>
<line>Patron of virtue, Rome's best champion,</line>
<line>Successful in the battles that he fights,</line>
<line>With honour and with fortune is return'd</line>
<line>From where he circumscribed with his sword,</line>
<line>And brought to yoke, the enemies of Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Drums and trumpets sounded. Enter MARTIUS and
MUTIUS; After them, two Men bearing a coffin
covered with black; then LUCIUS and QUINTUS. After
them, TITUS ANDRONICUS; and then TAMORA, with
ALARBUS, DEMETRIUS, CHIRON, AARON, and other Goths,
prisoners; Soldiers and people following. The
Bearers set down the coffin, and TITUS speaks</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Hail, Rome, victorious in thy mourning weeds!</line>
<line>Lo, as the bark, that hath discharged her fraught,</line>
<line>Returns with precious jading to the bay</line>
<line>From whence at first she weigh'd her anchorage,</line>
<line>Cometh Andronicus, bound with laurel boughs,</line>
<line>To re-salute his country with his tears,</line>
<line>Tears of true joy for his return to Rome.</line>
<line>Thou great defender of this Capitol,</line>
<line>Stand gracious to the rites that we intend!</line>
<line>Romans, of five and twenty valiant sons,</line>
<line>Half of the number that King Priam had,</line>
<line>Behold the poor remains, alive and dead!</line>
<line>These that survive let Rome reward with love;</line>
<line>These that I bring unto their latest home,</line>
<line>With burial amongst their ancestors:</line>
<line>Here Goths have given me leave to sheathe my sword.</line>
<line>Titus, unkind and careless of thine own,</line>
<line>Why suffer'st thou thy sons, unburied yet,</line>
<line>To hover on the dreadful shore of Styx?</line>
<line>Make way to lay them by their brethren.</line>
<para role="stagedir">The tomb is opened</para>
<line>There greet in silence, as the dead are wont,</line>
<line>And sleep in peace, slain in your country's wars!</line>
<line>O sacred receptacle of my joys,</line>
<line>Sweet cell of virtue and nobility,</line>
<line>How many sons of mine hast thou in store,</line>
<line>That thou wilt never render to me more!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Give us the proudest prisoner of the Goths,</line>
<line>That we may hew his limbs, and on a pile</line>
<line>Ad manes fratrum sacrifice his flesh,</line>
<line>Before this earthy prison of their bones;</line>
<line>That so the shadows be not unappeased,</line>
<line>Nor we disturb'd with prodigies on earth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I give him you, the noblest that survives,</line>
<line>The eldest son of this distressed queen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Stay, Roman brethren! Gracious conqueror,</line>
<line>Victorious Titus, rue the tears I shed,</line>
<line>A mother's tears in passion for her son:</line>
<line>And if thy sons were ever dear to thee,</line>
<line>O, think my son to be as dear to me!</line>
<line>Sufficeth not that we are brought to Rome,</line>
<line>To beautify thy triumphs and return,</line>
<line>Captive to thee and to thy Roman yoke,</line>
<line>But must my sons be slaughter'd in the streets,</line>
<line>For valiant doings in their country's cause?</line>
<line>O, if to fight for king and commonweal</line>
<line>Were piety in thine, it is in these.</line>
<line>Andronicus, stain not thy tomb with blood:</line>
<line>Wilt thou draw near the nature of the gods?</line>
<line>Draw near them then in being merciful:</line>
<line>Sweet mercy is nobility's true badge:</line>
<line>Thrice noble Titus, spare my first-born son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Patient yourself, madam, and pardon me.</line>
<line>These are their brethren, whom you Goths beheld</line>
<line>Alive and dead, and for their brethren slain</line>
<line>Religiously they ask a sacrifice:</line>
<line>To this your son is mark'd, and die he must,</line>
<line>To appease their groaning shadows that are gone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Away with him! and make a fire straight;</line>
<line>And with our swords, upon a pile of wood,</line>
<line>Let's hew his limbs till they be clean consumed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt LUCIUS, QUINTUS, MARTIUS, and MUTIUS, with ALARBUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>O cruel, irreligious piety!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Was ever Scythia half so barbarous?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Oppose not Scythia to ambitious Rome.</line>
<line>Alarbus goes to rest; and we survive</line>
<line>To tremble under Titus' threatening looks.</line>
<line>Then, madam, stand resolved, but hope withal</line>
<line>The self-same gods that arm'd the Queen of Troy</line>
<line>With opportunity of sharp revenge</line>
<line>Upon the Thracian tyrant in his tent,</line>
<line>May favor Tamora, the Queen of Goths--</line>
<line>When Goths were Goths and Tamora was queen--</line>
<line>To quit the bloody wrongs upon her foes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter LUCIUS, QUINTUS, MARTIUS and MUTIUS, with
their swords bloody</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>See, lord and father, how we have perform'd</line>
<line>Our Roman rites: Alarbus' limbs are lopp'd,</line>
<line>And entrails feed the sacrificing fire,</line>
<line>Whose smoke, like incense, doth perfume the sky.</line>
<line>Remaineth nought, but to inter our brethren,</line>
<line>And with loud 'larums welcome them to Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Let it be so; and let Andronicus</line>
<line>Make this his latest farewell to their souls.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Trumpets sounded, and the coffin laid in the tomb</para>
<line>In peace and honour rest you here, my sons;</line>
<line>Rome's readiest champions, repose you here in rest,</line>
<line>Secure from worldly chances and mishaps!</line>
<line>Here lurks no treason, here no envy swells,</line>
<line>Here grow no damned grudges; here are no storms,</line>
<line>No noise, but silence and eternal sleep:</line>
<line>In peace and honour rest you here, my sons!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>In peace and honour live Lord Titus long;</line>
<line>My noble lord and father, live in fame!</line>
<line>Lo, at this tomb my tributary tears</line>
<line>I render, for my brethren's obsequies;</line>
<line>And at thy feet I kneel, with tears of joy,</line>
<line>Shed on the earth, for thy return to Rome:</line>
<line>O, bless me here with thy victorious hand,</line>
<line>Whose fortunes Rome's best citizens applaud!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Kind Rome, that hast thus lovingly reserved</line>
<line>The cordial of mine age to glad my heart!</line>
<line>Lavinia, live; outlive thy father's days,</line>
<line>And fame's eternal date, for virtue's praise!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter, below, MARCUS ANDRONICUS and Tribunes;
re-enter SATURNINUS and BASSIANUS, attended</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Long live Lord Titus, my beloved brother,</line>
<line>Gracious triumpher in the eyes of Rome!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Thanks, gentle tribune, noble brother Marcus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>And welcome, nephews, from successful wars,</line>
<line>You that survive, and you that sleep in fame!</line>
<line>Fair lords, your fortunes are alike in all,</line>
<line>That in your country's service drew your swords:</line>
<line>But safer triumph is this funeral pomp,</line>
<line>That hath aspired to Solon's happiness</line>
<line>And triumphs over chance in honour's bed.</line>
<line>Titus Andronicus, the people of Rome,</line>
<line>Whose friend in justice thou hast ever been,</line>
<line>Send thee by me, their tribune and their trust,</line>
<line>This palliament of white and spotless hue;</line>
<line>And name thee in election for the empire,</line>
<line>With these our late-deceased emperor's sons:</line>
<line>Be candidatus then, and put it on,</line>
<line>And help to set a head on headless Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>A better head her glorious body fits</line>
<line>Than his that shakes for age and feebleness:</line>
<line>What should I don this robe, and trouble you?</line>
<line>Be chosen with proclamations to-day,</line>
<line>To-morrow yield up rule, resign my life,</line>
<line>And set abroad new business for you all?</line>
<line>Rome, I have been thy soldier forty years,</line>
<line>And led my country's strength successfully,</line>
<line>And buried one and twenty valiant sons,</line>
<line>Knighted in field, slain manfully in arms,</line>
<line>In right and service of their noble country</line>
<line>Give me a staff of honour for mine age,</line>
<line>But not a sceptre to control the world:</line>
<line>Upright he held it, lords, that held it last.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Titus, thou shalt obtain and ask the empery.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Proud and ambitious tribune, canst thou tell?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Patience, Prince Saturninus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Romans, do me right:</line>
<line>Patricians, draw your swords: and sheathe them not</line>
<line>Till Saturninus be Rome's emperor.</line>
<line>Andronicus, would thou wert shipp'd to hell,</line>
<line>Rather than rob me of the people's hearts!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Proud Saturnine, interrupter of the good</line>
<line>That noble-minded Titus means to thee!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Content thee, prince; I will restore to thee</line>
<line>The people's hearts, and wean them from themselves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Andronicus, I do not flatter thee,</line>
<line>But honour thee, and will do till I die:</line>
<line>My faction if thou strengthen with thy friends,</line>
<line>I will most thankful be; and thanks to men</line>
<line>Of noble minds is honourable meed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>People of Rome, and people's tribunes here,</line>
<line>I ask your voices and your suffrages:</line>
<line>Will you bestow them friendly on Andronicus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Tribunes</speaker>
<line>To gratify the good Andronicus,</line>
<line>And gratulate his safe return to Rome,</line>
<line>The people will accept whom he admits.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Tribunes, I thank you: and this suit I make,</line>
<line>That you create your emperor's eldest son,</line>
<line>Lord Saturnine; whose virtues will, I hope,</line>
<line>Reflect on Rome as Titan's rays on earth,</line>
<line>And ripen justice in this commonweal:</line>
<line>Then, if you will elect by my advice,</line>
<line>Crown him and say 'Long live our emperor!'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>With voices and applause of every sort,</line>
<line>Patricians and plebeians, we create</line>
<line>Lord Saturninus Rome's great emperor,</line>
<line>And say 'Long live our Emperor Saturnine!'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">A long flourish till they come down</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Titus Andronicus, for thy favors done</line>
<line>To us in our election this day,</line>
<line>I give thee thanks in part of thy deserts,</line>
<line>And will with deeds requite thy gentleness:</line>
<line>And, for an onset, Titus, to advance</line>
<line>Thy name and honourable family,</line>
<line>Lavinia will I make my empress,</line>
<line>Rome's royal mistress, mistress of my heart,</line>
<line>And in the sacred Pantheon her espouse:</line>
<line>Tell me, Andronicus, doth this motion please thee?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>It doth, my worthy lord; and in this match</line>
<line>I hold me highly honour'd of your grace:</line>
<line>And here in sight of Rome to Saturnine,</line>
<line>King and commander of our commonweal,</line>
<line>The wide world's emperor, do I consecrate</line>
<line>My sword, my chariot and my prisoners;</line>
<line>Presents well worthy Rome's imperial lord:</line>
<line>Receive them then, the tribute that I owe,</line>
<line>Mine honour's ensigns humbled at thy feet.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Thanks, noble Titus, father of my life!</line>
<line>How proud I am of thee and of thy gifts</line>
<line>Rome shall record, and when I do forget</line>
<line>The least of these unspeakable deserts,</line>
<line>Romans, forget your fealty to me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To TAMORA</phrase>  Now, madam, are you prisoner to</line>
<line>an emperor;</line>
<line>To him that, for your honour and your state,</line>
<line>Will use you nobly and your followers.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>A goodly lady, trust me; of the hue</line>
<line>That I would choose, were I to choose anew.</line>
<line>Clear up, fair queen, that cloudy countenance:</line>
<line>Though chance of war hath wrought this change of cheer,</line>
<line>Thou comest not to be made a scorn in Rome:</line>
<line>Princely shall be thy usage every way.</line>
<line>Rest on my word, and let not discontent</line>
<line>Daunt all your hopes: madam, he comforts you</line>
<line>Can make you greater than the Queen of Goths.</line>
<line>Lavinia, you are not displeased with this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>Not I, my lord; sith true nobility</line>
<line>Warrants these words in princely courtesy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Thanks, sweet Lavinia. Romans, let us go;</line>
<line>Ransomless here we set our prisoners free:</line>
<line>Proclaim our honours, lords, with trump and drum.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. SATURNINUS courts TAMORA in dumb show</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Lord Titus, by your leave, this maid is mine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Seizing LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>How, sir! are you in earnest then, my lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Ay, noble Titus; and resolved withal</line>
<line>To do myself this reason and this right.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>'Suum cuique' is our Roman justice:</line>
<line>This prince in justice seizeth but his own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>And that he will, and shall, if Lucius live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Traitors, avaunt! Where is the emperor's guard?</line>
<line>Treason, my lord! Lavinia is surprised!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Surprised! by whom?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>By him that justly may</line>
<line>Bear his betroth'd from all the world away.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt BASSIANUS and MARCUS with LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MUTIUS</speaker>
<line>Brothers, help to convey her hence away,</line>
<line>And with my sword I'll keep this door safe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt LUCIUS, QUINTUS, and MARTIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Follow, my lord, and I'll soon bring her back.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MUTIUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, you pass not here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>What, villain boy!</line>
<line>Barr'st me my way in Rome?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Stabbing MUTIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MUTIUS</speaker>
<line>Help, Lucius, help!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Dies</para>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">During the fray, SATURNINUS, TAMORA, DEMETRIUS,
CHIRON and AARON go out and re-enter, above</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter LUCIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, you are unjust, and, more than so,</line>
<line>In wrongful quarrel you have slain your son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Nor thou, nor he, are any sons of mine;</line>
<line>My sons would never so dishonour me:</line>
<line>Traitor, restore Lavinia to the emperor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Dead, if you will; but not to be his wife,</line>
<line>That is another's lawful promised love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>No, Titus, no; the emperor needs her not,</line>
<line>Nor her, nor thee, nor any of thy stock:</line>
<line>I'll trust, by leisure, him that mocks me once;</line>
<line>Thee never, nor thy traitorous haughty sons,</line>
<line>Confederates all thus to dishonour me.</line>
<line>Was there none else in Rome to make a stale,</line>
<line>But Saturnine? Full well, Andronicus,</line>
<line>Agree these deeds with that proud brag of thine,</line>
<line>That said'st I begg'd the empire at thy hands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O monstrous! what reproachful words are these?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>But go thy ways; go, give that changing piece</line>
<line>To him that flourish'd for her with his sword</line>
<line>A valiant son-in-law thou shalt enjoy;</line>
<line>One fit to bandy with thy lawless sons,</line>
<line>To ruffle in the commonwealth of Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>These words are razors to my wounded heart.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>And therefore, lovely Tamora, queen of Goths,</line>
<line>That like the stately Phoebe 'mongst her nymphs</line>
<line>Dost overshine the gallant'st dames of Rome,</line>
<line>If thou be pleased with this my sudden choice,</line>
<line>Behold, I choose thee, Tamora, for my bride,</line>
<line>And will create thee empress of Rome,</line>
<line>Speak, Queen of Goths, dost thou applaud my choice?</line>
<line>And here I swear by all the Roman gods,</line>
<line>Sith priest and holy water are so near</line>
<line>And tapers burn so bright and every thing</line>
<line>In readiness for Hymenaeus stand,</line>
<line>I will not re-salute the streets of Rome,</line>
<line>Or climb my palace, till from forth this place</line>
<line>I lead espoused my bride along with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>And here, in sight of heaven, to Rome I swear,</line>
<line>If Saturnine advance the Queen of Goths,</line>
<line>She will a handmaid be to his desires,</line>
<line>A loving nurse, a mother to his youth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Ascend, fair queen, Pantheon. Lords, accompany</line>
<line>Your noble emperor and his lovely bride,</line>
<line>Sent by the heavens for Prince Saturnine,</line>
<line>Whose wisdom hath her fortune conquered:</line>
<line>There shall we consummate our spousal rites.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt all but TITUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I am not bid to wait upon this bride.</line>
<line>Titus, when wert thou wont to walk alone,</line>
<line>Dishonour'd thus, and challenged of wrongs?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter MARCUS, LUCIUS, QUINTUS, and MARTIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O Titus, see, O, see what thou hast done!</line>
<line>In a bad quarrel slain a virtuous son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>No, foolish tribune, no; no son of mine,</line>
<line>Nor thou, nor these, confederates in the deed</line>
<line>That hath dishonour'd all our family;</line>
<line>Unworthy brother, and unworthy sons!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>But let us give him burial, as becomes;</line>
<line>Give Mutius burial with our brethren.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Traitors, away! he rests not in this tomb:</line>
<line>This monument five hundred years hath stood,</line>
<line>Which I have sumptuously re-edified:</line>
<line>Here none but soldiers and Rome's servitors</line>
<line>Repose in fame; none basely slain in brawls:</line>
<line>Bury him where you can; he comes not here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, this is impiety in you:</line>
<line>My nephew Mutius' deeds do plead for him</line>
<line>He must be buried with his brethren.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>And shall, or him we will accompany.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>'And shall!' what villain was it that spake</line>
<line>that word?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>He that would vouch it in any place but here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>What, would you bury him in my despite?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>No, noble Titus, but entreat of thee</line>
<line>To pardon Mutius and to bury him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Marcus, even thou hast struck upon my crest,</line>
<line>And, with these boys, mine honour thou hast wounded:</line>
<line>My foes I do repute you every one;</line>
<line>So, trouble me no more, but get you gone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>He is not with himself; let us withdraw.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>Not I, till Mutius' bones be buried.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">MARCUS and the Sons of TITUS kneel</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Brother, for in that name doth nature plead,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>Father, and in that name doth nature speak,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Speak thou no more, if all the rest will speed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Renowned Titus, more than half my soul,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Dear father, soul and substance of us all,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Suffer thy brother Marcus to inter</line>
<line>His noble nephew here in virtue's nest,</line>
<line>That died in honour and Lavinia's cause.</line>
<line>Thou art a Roman; be not barbarous:</line>
<line>The Greeks upon advice did bury Ajax</line>
<line>That slew himself; and wise Laertes' son</line>
<line>Did graciously plead for his funerals:</line>
<line>Let not young Mutius, then, that was thy joy</line>
<line>Be barr'd his entrance here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Rise, Marcus, rise.</line>
<line>The dismall'st day is this that e'er I saw,</line>
<line>To be dishonour'd by my sons in Rome!</line>
<line>Well, bury him, and bury me the next.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">MUTIUS is put into the tomb</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>There lie thy bones, sweet Mutius, with thy friends,</line>
<line>Till we with trophies do adorn thy tomb.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Kneeling</phrase>  No man shed tears for noble Mutius;</line>
<line>He lives in fame that died in virtue's cause.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, to step out of these dreary dumps,</line>
<line>How comes it that the subtle Queen of Goths</line>
<line>Is of a sudden thus advanced in Rome?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I know not, Marcus; but I know it is,</line>
<line>Whether by device or no, the heavens can tell:</line>
<line>Is she not then beholding to the man</line>
<line>That brought her for this high good turn so far?</line>
<line>Yes, and will nobly him remunerate.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Re-enter, from one side, SATURNINUS
attended, TAMORA, DEMETRIUS, CHIRON and AARON; from
the other, BASSIANUS, LAVINIA, and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>So, Bassianus, you have play'd your prize:</line>
<line>God give you joy, sir, of your gallant bride!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>And you of yours, my lord! I say no more,</line>
<line>Nor wish no less; and so, I take my leave.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Traitor, if Rome have law or we have power,</line>
<line>Thou and thy faction shall repent this rape.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Rape, call you it, my lord, to seize my own,</line>
<line>My truth-betrothed love and now my wife?</line>
<line>But let the laws of Rome determine all;</line>
<line>Meanwhile I am possess'd of that is mine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>'Tis good, sir: you are very short with us;</line>
<line>But, if we live, we'll be as sharp with you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, what I have done, as best I may,</line>
<line>Answer I must and shall do with my life.</line>
<line>Only thus much I give your grace to know:</line>
<line>By all the duties that I owe to Rome,</line>
<line>This noble gentleman, Lord Titus here,</line>
<line>Is in opinion and in honour wrong'd;</line>
<line>That in the rescue of Lavinia</line>
<line>With his own hand did slay his youngest son,</line>
<line>In zeal to you and highly moved to wrath</line>
<line>To be controll'd in that he frankly gave:</line>
<line>Receive him, then, to favor, Saturnine,</line>
<line>That hath express'd himself in all his deeds</line>
<line>A father and a friend to thee and Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Prince Bassianus, leave to plead my deeds:</line>
<line>'Tis thou and those that have dishonour'd me.</line>
<line>Rome and the righteous heavens be my judge,</line>
<line>How I have loved and honour'd Saturnine!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>My worthy lord, if ever Tamora</line>
<line>Were gracious in those princely eyes of thine,</line>
<line>Then hear me speak in indifferently for all;</line>
<line>And at my suit, sweet, pardon what is past.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>What, madam! be dishonour'd openly,</line>
<line>And basely put it up without revenge?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Not so, my lord; the gods of Rome forfend</line>
<line>I should be author to dishonour you!</line>
<line>But on mine honour dare I undertake</line>
<line>For good Lord Titus' innocence in all;</line>
<line>Whose fury not dissembled speaks his griefs:</line>
<line>Then, at my suit, look graciously on him;</line>
<line>Lose not so noble a friend on vain suppose,</line>
<line>Nor with sour looks afflict his gentle heart.</line>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside to SATURNINUS</phrase>  My lord, be ruled by me,</line>
<line>be won at last;</line>
<line>Dissemble all your griefs and discontents:</line>
<line>You are but newly planted in your throne;</line>
<line>Lest, then, the people, and patricians too,</line>
<line>Upon a just survey, take Titus' part,</line>
<line>And so supplant you for ingratitude,</line>
<line>Which Rome reputes to be a heinous sin,</line>
<line>Yield at entreats; and then let me alone:</line>
<line>I'll find a day to massacre them all</line>
<line>And raze their faction and their family,</line>
<line>The cruel father and his traitorous sons,</line>
<line>To whom I sued for my dear son's life,</line>
<line>And make them know what 'tis to let a queen</line>
<line>Kneel in the streets and beg for grace in vain.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aloud</para>
<line>Come, come, sweet emperor; come, Andronicus;</line>
<line>Take up this good old man, and cheer the heart</line>
<line>That dies in tempest of thy angry frown.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Rise, Titus, rise; my empress hath prevail'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I thank your majesty, and her, my lord:</line>
<line>These words, these looks, infuse new life in me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Titus, I am incorporate in Rome,</line>
<line>A Roman now adopted happily,</line>
<line>And must advise the emperor for his good.</line>
<line>This day all quarrels die, Andronicus;</line>
<line>And let it be mine honour, good my lord,</line>
<line>That I have reconciled your friends and you.</line>
<line>For you, Prince Bassianus, I have pass'd</line>
<line>My word and promise to the emperor,</line>
<line>That you will be more mild and tractable.</line>
<line>And fear not lords, and you, Lavinia;</line>
<line>By my advice, all humbled on your knees,</line>
<line>You shall ask pardon of his majesty.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>We do, and vow to heaven and to his highness,</line>
<line>That what we did was mildly as we might,</line>
<line>Tendering our sister's honour and our own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>That, on mine honour, here I do protest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Away, and talk not; trouble us no more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Nay, nay, sweet emperor, we must all be friends:</line>
<line>The tribune and his nephews kneel for grace;</line>
<line>I will not be denied: sweet heart, look back.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Marcus, for thy sake and thy brother's here,</line>
<line>And at my lovely Tamora's entreats,</line>
<line>I do remit these young men's heinous faults: Stand up.</line>
<line>Lavinia, though you left me like a churl,</line>
<line>I found a friend, and sure as death I swore</line>
<line>I would not part a bachelor from the priest.</line>
<line>Come, if the emperor's court can feast two brides,</line>
<line>You are my guest, Lavinia, and your friends.</line>
<line>This day shall be a love-day, Tamora.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>To-morrow, an it please your majesty</line>
<line>To hunt the panther and the hart with me,</line>
<line>With horn and hound we'll give your grace bonjour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Be it so, Titus, and gramercy too.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Flourish. Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT II</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Rome. Before the Palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter AARON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Now climbeth Tamora Olympus' top,</line>
<line>Safe out of fortune's shot; and sits aloft,</line>
<line>Secure of thunder's crack or lightning flash;</line>
<line>Advanced above pale envy's threatening reach.</line>
<line>As when the golden sun salutes the morn,</line>
<line>And, having gilt the ocean with his beams,</line>
<line>Gallops the zodiac in his glistering coach,</line>
<line>And overlooks the highest-peering hills;</line>
<line>So Tamora:</line>
<line>Upon her wit doth earthly honour wait,</line>
<line>And virtue stoops and trembles at her frown.</line>
<line>Then, Aaron, arm thy heart, and fit thy thoughts,</line>
<line>To mount aloft with thy imperial mistress,</line>
<line>And mount her pitch, whom thou in triumph long</line>
<line>Hast prisoner held, fetter'd in amorous chains</line>
<line>And faster bound to Aaron's charming eyes</line>
<line>Than is Prometheus tied to Caucasus.</line>
<line>Away with slavish weeds and servile thoughts!</line>
<line>I will be bright, and shine in pearl and gold,</line>
<line>To wait upon this new-made empress.</line>
<line>To wait, said I? to wanton with this queen,</line>
<line>This goddess, this Semiramis, this nymph,</line>
<line>This siren, that will charm Rome's Saturnine,</line>
<line>And see his shipwreck and his commonweal's.</line>
<line>Holloa! what storm is this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DEMETRIUS and CHIRON, braving</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Chiron, thy years want wit, thy wit wants edge,</line>
<line>And manners, to intrude where I am graced;</line>
<line>And may, for aught thou know'st, affected be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Demetrius, thou dost over-ween in all;</line>
<line>And so in this, to bear me down with braves.</line>
<line>'Tis not the difference of a year or two</line>
<line>Makes me less gracious or thee more fortunate:</line>
<line>I am as able and as fit as thou</line>
<line>To serve, and to deserve my mistress' grace;</line>
<line>And that my sword upon thee shall approve,</line>
<line>And plead my passions for Lavinia's love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Clubs, clubs! these lovers will not keep</line>
<line>the peace.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Why, boy, although our mother, unadvised,</line>
<line>Gave you a dancing-rapier by your side,</line>
<line>Are you so desperate grown, to threat your friends?</line>
<line>Go to; have your lath glued within your sheath</line>
<line>Till you know better how to handle it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Meanwhile, sir, with the little skill I have,</line>
<line>Full well shalt thou perceive how much I dare.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Ay, boy, grow ye so brave?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They draw</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Coming forward</phrase>  Why, how now, lords!</line>
<line>So near the emperor's palace dare you draw,</line>
<line>And maintain such a quarrel openly?</line>
<line>Full well I wot the ground of all this grudge:</line>
<line>I would not for a million of gold</line>
<line>The cause were known to them it most concerns;</line>
<line>Nor would your noble mother for much more</line>
<line>Be so dishonour'd in the court of Rome.</line>
<line>For shame, put up.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Not I, till I have sheathed</line>
<line>My rapier in his bosom and withal</line>
<line>Thrust these reproachful speeches down his throat</line>
<line>That he hath breathed in my dishonour here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>For that I am prepared and full resolved.</line>
<line>Foul-spoken coward, that thunder'st with thy tongue,</line>
<line>And with thy weapon nothing darest perform!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Away, I say!</line>
<line>Now, by the gods that warlike Goths adore,</line>
<line>This petty brabble will undo us all.</line>
<line>Why, lords, and think you not how dangerous</line>
<line>It is to jet upon a prince's right?</line>
<line>What, is Lavinia then become so loose,</line>
<line>Or Bassianus so degenerate,</line>
<line>That for her love such quarrels may be broach'd</line>
<line>Without controlment, justice, or revenge?</line>
<line>Young lords, beware! and should the empress know</line>
<line>This discord's ground, the music would not please.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>I care not, I, knew she and all the world:</line>
<line>I love Lavinia more than all the world.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Youngling, learn thou to make some meaner choice:</line>
<line>Lavinia is thine elder brother's hope.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, are ye mad? or know ye not, in Rome</line>
<line>How furious and impatient they be,</line>
<line>And cannot brook competitors in love?</line>
<line>I tell you, lords, you do but plot your deaths</line>
<line>By this device.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Aaron, a thousand deaths</line>
<line>Would I propose to achieve her whom I love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>To achieve her! how?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Why makest thou it so strange?</line>
<line>She is a woman, therefore may be woo'd;</line>
<line>She is a woman, therefore may be won;</line>
<line>She is Lavinia, therefore must be loved.</line>
<line>What, man! more water glideth by the mill</line>
<line>Than wots the miller of; and easy it is</line>
<line>Of a cut loaf to steal a shive, we know:</line>
<line>Though Bassianus be the emperor's brother.</line>
<line>Better than he have worn Vulcan's badge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Ay, and as good as Saturninus may.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Then why should he despair that knows to court it</line>
<line>With words, fair looks and liberality?</line>
<line>What, hast not thou full often struck a doe,</line>
<line>And borne her cleanly by the keeper's nose?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, then, it seems, some certain snatch or so</line>
<line>Would serve your turns.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Ay, so the turn were served.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Aaron, thou hast hit it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Would you had hit it too!</line>
<line>Then should not we be tired with this ado.</line>
<line>Why, hark ye, hark ye! and are you such fools</line>
<line>To square for this? would it offend you, then</line>
<line>That both should speed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Faith, not me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Nor me, so I were one.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>For shame, be friends, and join for that you jar:</line>
<line>'Tis policy and stratagem must do</line>
<line>That you affect; and so must you resolve,</line>
<line>That what you cannot as you would achieve,</line>
<line>You must perforce accomplish as you may.</line>
<line>Take this of me: Lucrece was not more chaste</line>
<line>Than this Lavinia, Bassianus' love.</line>
<line>A speedier course than lingering languishment</line>
<line>Must we pursue, and I have found the path.</line>
<line>My lords, a solemn hunting is in hand;</line>
<line>There will the lovely Roman ladies troop:</line>
<line>The forest walks are wide and spacious;</line>
<line>And many unfrequented plots there are</line>
<line>Fitted by kind for rape and villany:</line>
<line>Single you thither then this dainty doe,</line>
<line>And strike her home by force, if not by words:</line>
<line>This way, or not at all, stand you in hope.</line>
<line>Come, come, our empress, with her sacred wit</line>
<line>To villany and vengeance consecrate,</line>
<line>Will we acquaint with all that we intend;</line>
<line>And she shall file our engines with advice,</line>
<line>That will not suffer you to square yourselves,</line>
<line>But to your wishes' height advance you both.</line>
<line>The emperor's court is like the house of Fame,</line>
<line>The palace full of tongues, of eyes, and ears:</line>
<line>The woods are ruthless, dreadful, deaf, and dull;</line>
<line>There speak, and strike, brave boys, and take</line>
<line>your turns;</line>
<line>There serve your lusts, shadow'd from heaven's eye,</line>
<line>And revel in Lavinia's treasury.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Thy counsel, lad, smells of no cowardice,</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Sit fas aut nefas, till I find the stream</line>
<line>To cool this heat, a charm to calm these fits.</line>
<line>Per Styga, per manes vehor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  A forest near Rome. Horns and cry of hounds heard.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TITUS ANDRONICUS, with Hunters, &amp;c., MARCUS,
LUCIUS, QUINTUS, and MARTIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>The hunt is up, the morn is bright and grey,</line>
<line>The fields are fragrant and the woods are green:</line>
<line>Uncouple here and let us make a bay</line>
<line>And wake the emperor and his lovely bride</line>
<line>And rouse the prince and ring a hunter's peal,</line>
<line>That all the court may echo with the noise.</line>
<line>Sons, let it be your charge, as it is ours,</line>
<line>To attend the emperor's person carefully:</line>
<line>I have been troubled in my sleep this night,</line>
<line>But dawning day new comfort hath inspired.</line>
<para role="stagedir">A cry of hounds and horns, winded in a peal. Enter
SATURNINUS, TAMORA, BASSIANUS, LAVINIA, DEMETRIUS,
CHIRON, and Attendants</para>
<line>Many good morrows to your majesty;</line>
<line>Madam, to you as many and as good:</line>
<line>I promised your grace a hunter's peal.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>And you have rung it lustily, my lord;</line>
<line>Somewhat too early for new-married ladies.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Lavinia, how say you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>I say, no;</line>
<line>I have been broad awake two hours and more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Come on, then; horse and chariots let us have,</line>
<line>And to our sport.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To TAMORA</para>
<line>Madam, now shall ye see</line>
<line>Our Roman hunting.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I have dogs, my lord,</line>
<line>Will rouse the proudest panther in the chase,</line>
<line>And climb the highest promontory top.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>And I have horse will follow where the game</line>
<line>Makes way, and run like swallows o'er the plain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Chiron, we hunt not, we, with horse nor hound,</line>
<line>But hope to pluck a dainty doe to ground.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  A lonely part of the forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter AARON, with a bag of gold</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>He that had wit would think that I had none,</line>
<line>To bury so much gold under a tree,</line>
<line>And never after to inherit it.</line>
<line>Let him that thinks of me so abjectly</line>
<line>Know that this gold must coin a stratagem,</line>
<line>Which, cunningly effected, will beget</line>
<line>A very excellent piece of villany:</line>
<line>And so repose, sweet gold, for their unrest</line>
<para role="stagedir">Hides the gold</para>
<line>That have their alms out of the empress' chest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter TAMORA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>My lovely Aaron, wherefore look'st thou sad,</line>
<line>When every thing doth make a gleeful boast?</line>
<line>The birds chant melody on every bush,</line>
<line>The snake lies rolled in the cheerful sun,</line>
<line>The green leaves quiver with the cooling wind</line>
<line>And make a chequer'd shadow on the ground:</line>
<line>Under their sweet shade, Aaron, let us sit,</line>
<line>And, whilst the babbling echo mocks the hounds,</line>
<line>Replying shrilly to the well-tuned horns,</line>
<line>As if a double hunt were heard at once,</line>
<line>Let us sit down and mark their yelping noise;</line>
<line>And, after conflict such as was supposed</line>
<line>The wandering prince and Dido once enjoy'd,</line>
<line>When with a happy storm they were surprised</line>
<line>And curtain'd with a counsel-keeping cave,</line>
<line>We may, each wreathed in the other's arms,</line>
<line>Our pastimes done, possess a golden slumber;</line>
<line>Whiles hounds and horns and sweet melodious birds</line>
<line>Be unto us as is a nurse's song</line>
<line>Of lullaby to bring her babe asleep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Madam, though Venus govern your desires,</line>
<line>Saturn is dominator over mine:</line>
<line>What signifies my deadly-standing eye,</line>
<line>My silence and my cloudy melancholy,</line>
<line>My fleece of woolly hair that now uncurls</line>
<line>Even as an adder when she doth unroll</line>
<line>To do some fatal execution?</line>
<line>No, madam, these are no venereal signs:</line>
<line>Vengeance is in my heart, death in my hand,</line>
<line>Blood and revenge are hammering in my head.</line>
<line>Hark Tamora, the empress of my soul,</line>
<line>Which never hopes more heaven than rests in thee,</line>
<line>This is the day of doom for Bassianus:</line>
<line>His Philomel must lose her tongue to-day,</line>
<line>Thy sons make pillage of her chastity</line>
<line>And wash their hands in Bassianus' blood.</line>
<line>Seest thou this letter? take it up, I pray thee,</line>
<line>And give the king this fatal plotted scroll.</line>
<line>Now question me no more; we are espied;</line>
<line>Here comes a parcel of our hopeful booty,</line>
<line>Which dreads not yet their lives' destruction.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Ah, my sweet Moor, sweeter to me than life!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>No more, great empress; Bassianus comes:</line>
<line>Be cross with him; and I'll go fetch thy sons</line>
<line>To back thy quarrels, whatsoe'er they be.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter BASSIANUS and LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Who have we here? Rome's royal empress,</line>
<line>Unfurnish'd of her well-beseeming troop?</line>
<line>Or is it Dian, habited like her,</line>
<line>Who hath abandoned her holy groves</line>
<line>To see the general hunting in this forest?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Saucy controller of our private steps!</line>
<line>Had I the power that some say Dian had,</line>
<line>Thy temples should be planted presently</line>
<line>With horns, as was Actaeon's; and the hounds</line>
<line>Should drive upon thy new-transformed limbs,</line>
<line>Unmannerly intruder as thou art!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>Under your patience, gentle empress,</line>
<line>'Tis thought you have a goodly gift in horning;</line>
<line>And to be doubted that your Moor and you</line>
<line>Are singled forth to try experiments:</line>
<line>Jove shield your husband from his hounds to-day!</line>
<line>'Tis pity they should take him for a stag.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>Believe me, queen, your swarth Cimmerian</line>
<line>Doth make your honour of his body's hue,</line>
<line>Spotted, detested, and abominable.</line>
<line>Why are you sequester'd from all your train,</line>
<line>Dismounted from your snow-white goodly steed.</line>
<line>And wander'd hither to an obscure plot,</line>
<line>Accompanied but with a barbarous Moor,</line>
<line>If foul desire had not conducted you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>And, being intercepted in your sport,</line>
<line>Great reason that my noble lord be rated</line>
<line>For sauciness. I pray you, let us hence,</line>
<line>And let her joy her raven-colour'd love;</line>
<line>This valley fits the purpose passing well.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">BASSIANUS</speaker>
<line>The king my brother shall have note of this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>Ay, for these slips have made him noted long:</line>
<line>Good king, to be so mightily abused!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Why have I patience to endure all this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter DEMETRIUS and CHIRON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>How now, dear sovereign, and our gracious mother!</line>
<line>Why doth your highness look so pale and wan?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Have I not reason, think you, to look pale?</line>
<line>These two have 'ticed me hither to this place:</line>
<line>A barren detested vale, you see it is;</line>
<line>The trees, though summer, yet forlorn and lean,</line>
<line>O'ercome with moss and baleful mistletoe:</line>
<line>Here never shines the sun; here nothing breeds,</line>
<line>Unless the nightly owl or fatal raven:</line>
<line>And when they show'd me this abhorred pit,</line>
<line>They told me, here, at dead time of the night,</line>
<line>A thousand fiends, a thousand hissing snakes,</line>
<line>Ten thousand swelling toads, as many urchins,</line>
<line>Would make such fearful and confused cries</line>
<line>As any mortal body hearing it</line>
<line>Should straight fall mad, or else die suddenly.</line>
<line>No sooner had they told this hellish tale,</line>
<line>But straight they told me they would bind me here</line>
<line>Unto the body of a dismal yew,</line>
<line>And leave me to this miserable death:</line>
<line>And then they call'd me foul adulteress,</line>
<line>Lascivious Goth, and all the bitterest terms</line>
<line>That ever ear did hear to such effect:</line>
<line>And, had you not by wondrous fortune come,</line>
<line>This vengeance on me had they executed.</line>
<line>Revenge it, as you love your mother's life,</line>
<line>Or be ye not henceforth call'd my children.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>This is a witness that I am thy son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Stabs BASSIANUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>And this for me, struck home to show my strength.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Also stabs BASSIANUS, who dies</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>Ay, come, Semiramis, nay, barbarous Tamora,</line>
<line>For no name fits thy nature but thy own!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Give me thy poniard; you shall know, my boys</line>
<line>Your mother's hand shall right your mother's wrong.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Stay, madam; here is more belongs to her;</line>
<line>First thrash the corn, then after burn the straw:</line>
<line>This minion stood upon her chastity,</line>
<line>Upon her nuptial vow, her loyalty,</line>
<line>And with that painted hope braves your mightiness:</line>
<line>And shall she carry this unto her grave?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>An if she do, I would I were an eunuch.</line>
<line>Drag hence her husband to some secret hole,</line>
<line>And make his dead trunk pillow to our lust.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>But when ye have the honey ye desire,</line>
<line>Let not this wasp outlive, us both to sting.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>I warrant you, madam, we will make that sure.</line>
<line>Come, mistress, now perforce we will enjoy</line>
<line>That nice-preserved honesty of yours.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>O Tamora! thou bear'st a woman's face,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>I will not hear her speak; away with her!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>Sweet lords, entreat her hear me but a word.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Listen, fair madam: let it be your glory</line>
<line>To see her tears; but be your heart to them</line>
<line>As unrelenting flint to drops of rain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>When did the tiger's young ones teach the dam?</line>
<line>O, do not learn her wrath; she taught it thee;</line>
<line>The milk thou suck'dst from her did turn to marble;</line>
<line>Even at thy teat thou hadst thy tyranny.</line>
<line>Yet every mother breeds not sons alike:</line>
<para role="stagedir">To CHIRON</para>
<line>Do thou entreat her show a woman pity.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>What, wouldst thou have me prove myself a bastard?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>'Tis true; the raven doth not hatch a lark:</line>
<line>Yet have I heard,--O, could I find it now!--</line>
<line>The lion moved with pity did endure</line>
<line>To have his princely paws pared all away:</line>
<line>Some say that ravens foster forlorn children,</line>
<line>The whilst their own birds famish in their nests:</line>
<line>O, be to me, though thy hard heart say no,</line>
<line>Nothing so kind, but something pitiful!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>I know not what it means; away with her!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>O, let me teach thee! for my father's sake,</line>
<line>That gave thee life, when well he might have</line>
<line>slain thee,</line>
<line>Be not obdurate, open thy deaf ears.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Hadst thou in person ne'er offended me,</line>
<line>Even for his sake am I pitiless.</line>
<line>Remember, boys, I pour'd forth tears in vain,</line>
<line>To save your brother from the sacrifice;</line>
<line>But fierce Andronicus would not relent;</line>
<line>Therefore, away with her, and use her as you will,</line>
<line>The worse to her, the better loved of me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>O Tamora, be call'd a gentle queen,</line>
<line>And with thine own hands kill me in this place!</line>
<line>For 'tis not life that I have begg'd so long;</line>
<line>Poor I was slain when Bassianus died.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>What begg'st thou, then? fond woman, let me go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>'Tis present death I beg; and one thing more</line>
<line>That womanhood denies my tongue to tell:</line>
<line>O, keep me from their worse than killing lust,</line>
<line>And tumble me into some loathsome pit,</line>
<line>Where never man's eye may behold my body:</line>
<line>Do this, and be a charitable murderer.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>So should I rob my sweet sons of their fee:</line>
<line>No, let them satisfy their lust on thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Away! for thou hast stay'd us here too long.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LAVINIA</speaker>
<line>No grace? no womanhood? Ah, beastly creature!</line>
<line>The blot and enemy to our general name!</line>
<line>Confusion fall--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Nay, then I'll stop your mouth. Bring thou her husband:</line>
<line>This is the hole where Aaron bid us hide him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">DEMETRIUS throws the body of BASSIANUS into the
pit; then exeunt DEMETRIUS and CHIRON, dragging
off LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Farewell, my sons: see that you make her sure.</line>
<line>Ne'er let my heart know merry cheer indeed,</line>
<line>Till all the Andronici be made away.</line>
<line>Now will I hence to seek my lovely Moor,</line>
<line>And let my spleenful sons this trull deflow'r.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter AARON, with QUINTUS and MARTIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Come on, my lords, the better foot before:</line>
<line>Straight will I bring you to the loathsome pit</line>
<line>Where I espied the panther fast asleep.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>My sight is very dull, whate'er it bodes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>And mine, I promise you; were't not for shame,</line>
<line>Well could I leave our sport to sleep awhile.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Falls into the pit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>What art thou fall'n? What subtle hole is this,</line>
<line>Whose mouth is cover'd with rude-growing briers,</line>
<line>Upon whose leaves are drops of new-shed blood</line>
<line>As fresh as morning dew distill'd on flowers?</line>
<line>A very fatal place it seems to me.</line>
<line>Speak, brother, hast thou hurt thee with the fall?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>O brother, with the dismall'st object hurt</line>
<line>That ever eye with sight made heart lament!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Now will I fetch the king to find them here,</line>
<line>That he thereby may give a likely guess</line>
<line>How these were they that made away his brother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>Why dost not comfort me, and help me out</line>
<line>From this unhallowed and blood-stained hole?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>I am surprised with an uncouth fear;</line>
<line>A chilling sweat o'er-runs my trembling joints:</line>
<line>My heart suspects more than mine eye can see.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>To prove thou hast a true-divining heart,</line>
<line>Aaron and thou look down into this den,</line>
<line>And see a fearful sight of blood and death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>Aaron is gone; and my compassionate heart</line>
<line>Will not permit mine eyes once to behold</line>
<line>The thing whereat it trembles by surmise;</line>
<line>O, tell me how it is; for ne'er till now</line>
<line>Was I a child to fear I know not what.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>Lord Bassianus lies embrewed here,</line>
<line>All on a heap, like to a slaughter'd lamb,</line>
<line>In this detested, dark, blood-drinking pit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>If it be dark, how dost thou know 'tis he?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>Upon his bloody finger he doth wear</line>
<line>A precious ring, that lightens all the hole,</line>
<line>Which, like a taper in some monument,</line>
<line>Doth shine upon the dead man's earthy cheeks,</line>
<line>And shows the ragged entrails of the pit:</line>
<line>So pale did shine the moon on Pyramus</line>
<line>When he by night lay bathed in maiden blood.</line>
<line>O brother, help me with thy fainting hand--</line>
<line>If fear hath made thee faint, as me it hath--</line>
<line>Out of this fell devouring receptacle,</line>
<line>As hateful as Cocytus' misty mouth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>Reach me thy hand, that I may help thee out;</line>
<line>Or, wanting strength to do thee so much good,</line>
<line>I may be pluck'd into the swallowing womb</line>
<line>Of this deep pit, poor Bassianus' grave.</line>
<line>I have no strength to pluck thee to the brink.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>Nor I no strength to climb without thy help.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">QUINTUS</speaker>
<line>Thy hand once more; I will not loose again,</line>
<line>Till thou art here aloft, or I below:</line>
<line>Thou canst not come to me: I come to thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Falls in</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SATURNINUS with AARON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Along with me: I'll see what hole is here,</line>
<line>And what he is that now is leap'd into it.</line>
<line>Say who art thou that lately didst descend</line>
<line>Into this gaping hollow of the earth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>The unhappy son of old Andronicus:</line>
<line>Brought hither in a most unlucky hour,</line>
<line>To find thy brother Bassianus dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>My brother dead! I know thou dost but jest:</line>
<line>He and his lady both are at the lodge</line>
<line>Upon the north side of this pleasant chase;</line>
<line>'Tis not an hour since I left him there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARTIUS</speaker>
<line>We know not where you left him all alive;</line>
<line>But, out, alas! here have we found him dead.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter TAMORA, with Attendants; TITUS
ANDRONICUS, and Lucius</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Where is my lord the king?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Here, Tamora, though grieved with killing grief.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Where is thy brother Bassianus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Now to the bottom dost thou search my wound:</line>
<line>Poor Bassianus here lies murdered.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Then all too late I bring this fatal writ,</line>
<line>The complot of this timeless tragedy;</line>
<line>And wonder greatly that man's face can fold</line>
<line>In pleasing smiles such murderous tyranny.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">She giveth SATURNINUS a letter</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Reads</phrase>  'An if we miss to meet him handsomely--</line>
<line>Sweet huntsman, Bassianus 'tis we mean--</line>
<line>Do thou so much as dig the grave for him:</line>
<line>Thou know'st our meaning. Look for thy reward</line>
<line>Among the nettles at the elder-tree</line>
<line>Which overshades the mouth of that same pit</line>
<line>Where we decreed to bury Bassianus.</line>
<line>Do this, and purchase us thy lasting friends.'</line>
<line>O Tamora! was ever heard the like?</line>
<line>This is the pit, and this the elder-tree.</line>
<line>Look, sirs, if you can find the huntsman out</line>
<line>That should have murdered Bassianus here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>My gracious lord, here is the bag of gold.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">To TITUS</phrase>  Two of thy whelps, fell curs of</line>
<line>bloody kind,</line>
<line>Have here bereft my brother of his life.</line>
<line>Sirs, drag them from the pit unto the prison:</line>
<line>There let them bide until we have devised</line>
<line>Some never-heard-of torturing pain for them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>What, are they in this pit? O wondrous thing!</line>
<line>How easily murder is discovered!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>High emperor, upon my feeble knee</line>
<line>I beg this boon, with tears not lightly shed,</line>
<line>That this fell fault of my accursed sons,</line>
<line>Accursed if the fault be proved in them,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>If it be proved! you see it is apparent.</line>
<line>Who found this letter? Tamora, was it you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Andronicus himself did take it up.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I did, my lord: yet let me be their bail;</line>
<line>For, by my father's reverend tomb, I vow</line>
<line>They shall be ready at your highness' will</line>
<line>To answer their suspicion with their lives.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Thou shalt not bail them: see thou follow me.</line>
<line>Some bring the murder'd body, some the murderers:</line>
<line>Let them not speak a word; the guilt is plain;</line>
<line>For, by my soul, were there worse end than death,</line>
<line>That end upon them should be executed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Andronicus, I will entreat the king;</line>
<line>Fear not thy sons; they shall do well enough.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come, Lucius, come; stay not to talk with them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the forest.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter DEMETRIUS and CHIRON with LAVINIA, ravished;
her hands cut off, and her tongue cut out</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>So, now go tell, an if thy tongue can speak,</line>
<line>Who 'twas that cut thy tongue and ravish'd thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Write down thy mind, bewray thy meaning so,</line>
<line>An if thy stumps will let thee play the scribe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>See, how with signs and tokens she can scrowl.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Go home, call for sweet water, wash thy hands.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>She hath no tongue to call, nor hands to wash;</line>
<line>And so let's leave her to her silent walks.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>An 'twere my case, I should go hang myself.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>If thou hadst hands to help thee knit the cord.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt DEMETRIUS and CHIRON</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter MARCUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS</speaker>
<line>Who is this? my niece, that flies away so fast!</line>
<line>Cousin, a word; where is your husband?</line>
<line>If I do dream, would all my wealth would wake me!</line>
<line>If I do wake, some planet strike me down,</line>
<line>That I may slumber in eternal sleep!</line>
<line>Speak, gentle niece, what stern ungentle hands</line>
<line>Have lopp'd and hew'd and made thy body bare</line>
<line>Of her two branches, those sweet ornaments,</line>
<line>Whose circling shadows kings have sought to sleep in,</line>
<line>And might not gain so great a happiness</line>
<line>As have thy love? Why dost not speak to me?</line>
<line>Alas, a crimson river of warm blood,</line>
<line>Like to a bubbling fountain stirr'd with wind,</line>
<line>Doth rise and fall between thy rosed lips,</line>
<line>Coming and going with thy honey breath.</line>
<line>But, sure, some Tereus hath deflowered thee,</line>
<line>And, lest thou shouldst detect him, cut thy tongue.</line>
<line>Ah, now thou turn'st away thy face for shame!</line>
<line>And, notwithstanding all this loss of blood,</line>
<line>As from a conduit with three issuing spouts,</line>
<line>Yet do thy cheeks look red as Titan's face</line>
<line>Blushing to be encountered with a cloud.</line>
<line>Shall I speak for thee? shall I say 'tis so?</line>
<line>O, that I knew thy heart; and knew the beast,</line>
<line>That I might rail at him, to ease my mind!</line>
<line>Sorrow concealed, like an oven stopp'd,</line>
<line>Doth burn the heart to cinders where it is.</line>
<line>Fair Philomela, she but lost her tongue,</line>
<line>And in a tedious sampler sew'd her mind:</line>
<line>But, lovely niece, that mean is cut from thee;</line>
<line>A craftier Tereus, cousin, hast thou met,</line>
<line>And he hath cut those pretty fingers off,</line>
<line>That could have better sew'd than Philomel.</line>
<line>O, had the monster seen those lily hands</line>
<line>Tremble, like aspen-leaves, upon a lute,</line>
<line>And make the silken strings delight to kiss them,</line>
<line>He would not then have touch'd them for his life!</line>
<line>Or, had he heard the heavenly harmony</line>
<line>Which that sweet tongue hath made,</line>
<line>He would have dropp'd his knife, and fell asleep</line>
<line>As Cerberus at the Thracian poet's feet.</line>
<line>Come, let us go, and make thy father blind;</line>
<line>For such a sight will blind a father's eye:</line>
<line>One hour's storm will drown the fragrant meads;</line>
<line>What will whole months of tears thy father's eyes?</line>
<line>Do not draw back, for we will mourn with thee</line>
<line>O, could our mourning ease thy misery!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT III</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Judges, Senators and Tribunes, with MARTIUS
and QUINTUS, bound, passing on to the place of
execution; TITUS going before, pleading</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Hear me, grave fathers! noble tribunes, stay!</line>
<line>For pity of mine age, whose youth was spent</line>
<line>In dangerous wars, whilst you securely slept;</line>
<line>For all my blood in Rome's great quarrel shed;</line>
<line>For all the frosty nights that I have watch'd;</line>
<line>And for these bitter tears, which now you see</line>
<line>Filling the aged wrinkles in my cheeks;</line>
<line>Be pitiful to my condemned sons,</line>
<line>Whose souls are not corrupted as 'tis thought.</line>
<line>For two and twenty sons I never wept,</line>
<line>Because they died in honour's lofty bed.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Lieth down; the Judges, &amp;c., pass by him, and Exeunt</para>
<line>For these, these, tribunes, in the dust I write</line>
<line>My heart's deep languor and my soul's sad tears:</line>
<line>Let my tears stanch the earth's dry appetite;</line>
<line>My sons' sweet blood will make it shame and blush.</line>
<line>O earth, I will befriend thee more with rain,</line>
<line>That shall distil from these two ancient urns,</line>
<line>Than youthful April shall with all his showers:</line>
<line>In summer's drought I'll drop upon thee still;</line>
<line>In winter with warm tears I'll melt the snow</line>
<line>And keep eternal spring-time on thy face,</line>
<line>So thou refuse to drink my dear sons' blood.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter LUCIUS, with his sword drawn</para>
<line>O reverend tribunes! O gentle, aged men!</line>
<line>Unbind my sons, reverse the doom of death;</line>
<line>And let me say, that never wept before,</line>
<line>My tears are now prevailing orators.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O noble father, you lament in vain:</line>
<line>The tribunes hear you not; no man is by;</line>
<line>And you recount your sorrows to a stone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Ah, Lucius, for thy brothers let me plead.</line>
<line>Grave tribunes, once more I entreat of you,--</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>My gracious lord, no tribune hears you speak.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, tis no matter, man; if they did hear,</line>
<line>They would not mark me, or if they did mark,</line>
<line>They would not pity me, yet plead I must;</line>
<line>And bootless unto them.</line>
<line>Therefore I tell my sorrows to the stones;</line>
<line>Who, though they cannot answer my distress,</line>
<line>Yet in some sort they are better than the tribunes,</line>
<line>For that they will not intercept my tale:</line>
<line>When I do weep, they humbly at my feet</line>
<line>Receive my tears and seem to weep with me;</line>
<line>And, were they but attired in grave weeds,</line>
<line>Rome could afford no tribune like to these.</line>
<line>A stone is soft as wax,--tribunes more hard than stones;</line>
<line>A stone is silent, and offendeth not,</line>
<line>And tribunes with their tongues doom men to death.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Rises</para>
<line>But wherefore stand'st thou with thy weapon drawn?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>To rescue my two brothers from their death:</line>
<line>For which attempt the judges have pronounced</line>
<line>My everlasting doom of banishment.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O happy man! they have befriended thee.</line>
<line>Why, foolish Lucius, dost thou not perceive</line>
<line>That Rome is but a wilderness of tigers?</line>
<line>Tigers must prey, and Rome affords no prey</line>
<line>But me and mine: how happy art thou, then,</line>
<line>From these devourers to be banished!</line>
<line>But who comes with our brother Marcus here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter MARCUS and LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Titus, prepare thy aged eyes to weep;</line>
<line>Or, if not so, thy noble heart to break:</line>
<line>I bring consuming sorrow to thine age.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Will it consume me? let me see it, then.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>This was thy daughter.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, Marcus, so she is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Ay me, this object kills me!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Faint-hearted boy, arise, and look upon her.</line>
<line>Speak, Lavinia, what accursed hand</line>
<line>Hath made thee handless in thy father's sight?</line>
<line>What fool hath added water to the sea,</line>
<line>Or brought a faggot to bright-burning Troy?</line>
<line>My grief was at the height before thou camest,</line>
<line>And now like Nilus, it disdaineth bounds.</line>
<line>Give me a sword, I'll chop off my hands too;</line>
<line>For they have fought for Rome, and all in vain;</line>
<line>And they have nursed this woe, in feeding life;</line>
<line>In bootless prayer have they been held up,</line>
<line>And they have served me to effectless use:</line>
<line>Now all the service I require of them</line>
<line>Is that the one will help to cut the other.</line>
<line>'Tis well, Lavinia, that thou hast no hands;</line>
<line>For hands, to do Rome service, are but vain.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Speak, gentle sister, who hath martyr'd thee?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, that delightful engine of her thoughts</line>
<line>That blabb'd them with such pleasing eloquence,</line>
<line>Is torn from forth that pretty hollow cage,</line>
<line>Where, like a sweet melodious bird, it sung</line>
<line>Sweet varied notes, enchanting every ear!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O, say thou for her, who hath done this deed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, thus I found her, straying in the park,</line>
<line>Seeking to hide herself, as doth the deer</line>
<line>That hath received some unrecuring wound.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>It was my deer; and he that wounded her</line>
<line>Hath hurt me more than had he killed me dead:</line>
<line>For now I stand as one upon a rock</line>
<line>Environed with a wilderness of sea,</line>
<line>Who marks the waxing tide grow wave by wave,</line>
<line>Expecting ever when some envious surge</line>
<line>Will in his brinish bowels swallow him.</line>
<line>This way to death my wretched sons are gone;</line>
<line>Here stands my other son, a banished man,</line>
<line>And here my brother, weeping at my woes.</line>
<line>But that which gives my soul the greatest spurn,</line>
<line>Is dear Lavinia, dearer than my soul.</line>
<line>Had I but seen thy picture in this plight,</line>
<line>It would have madded me: what shall I do</line>
<line>Now I behold thy lively body so?</line>
<line>Thou hast no hands, to wipe away thy tears:</line>
<line>Nor tongue, to tell me who hath martyr'd thee:</line>
<line>Thy husband he is dead: and for his death</line>
<line>Thy brothers are condemn'd, and dead by this.</line>
<line>Look, Marcus! ah, son Lucius, look on her!</line>
<line>When I did name her brothers, then fresh tears</line>
<line>Stood on her cheeks, as doth the honey-dew</line>
<line>Upon a gather'd lily almost wither'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Perchance she weeps because they kill'd her husband;</line>
<line>Perchance because she knows them innocent.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>If they did kill thy husband, then be joyful</line>
<line>Because the law hath ta'en revenge on them.</line>
<line>No, no, they would not do so foul a deed;</line>
<line>Witness the sorrow that their sister makes.</line>
<line>Gentle Lavinia, let me kiss thy lips.</line>
<line>Or make some sign how I may do thee ease:</line>
<line>Shall thy good uncle, and thy brother Lucius,</line>
<line>And thou, and I, sit round about some fountain,</line>
<line>Looking all downwards to behold our cheeks</line>
<line>How they are stain'd, as meadows, yet not dry,</line>
<line>With miry slime left on them by a flood?</line>
<line>And in the fountain shall we gaze so long</line>
<line>Till the fresh taste be taken from that clearness,</line>
<line>And made a brine-pit with our bitter tears?</line>
<line>Or shall we cut away our hands, like thine?</line>
<line>Or shall we bite our tongues, and in dumb shows</line>
<line>Pass the remainder of our hateful days?</line>
<line>What shall we do? let us, that have our tongues,</line>
<line>Plot some deuce of further misery,</line>
<line>To make us wonder'd at in time to come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Sweet father, cease your tears; for, at your grief,</line>
<line>See how my wretched sister sobs and weeps.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Patience, dear niece. Good Titus, dry thine eyes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Ah, Marcus, Marcus! brother, well I wot</line>
<line>Thy napkin cannot drink a tear of mine,</line>
<line>For thou, poor man, hast drown'd it with thine own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Ah, my Lavinia, I will wipe thy cheeks.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Mark, Marcus, mark! I understand her signs:</line>
<line>Had she a tongue to speak, now would she say</line>
<line>That to her brother which I said to thee:</line>
<line>His napkin, with his true tears all bewet,</line>
<line>Can do no service on her sorrowful cheeks.</line>
<line>O, what a sympathy of woe is this,</line>
<line>As far from help as Limbo is from bliss!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter AARON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Titus Andronicus, my lord the emperor</line>
<line>Sends thee this word,--that, if thou love thy sons,</line>
<line>Let Marcus, Lucius, or thyself, old Titus,</line>
<line>Or any one of you, chop off your hand,</line>
<line>And send it to the king: he for the same</line>
<line>Will send thee hither both thy sons alive;</line>
<line>And that shall be the ransom for their fault.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O gracious emperor! O gentle Aaron!</line>
<line>Did ever raven sing so like a lark,</line>
<line>That gives sweet tidings of the sun's uprise?</line>
<line>With all my heart, I'll send the emperor My hand:</line>
<line>Good Aaron, wilt thou help to chop it off?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Stay, father! for that noble hand of thine,</line>
<line>That hath thrown down so many enemies,</line>
<line>Shall not be sent: my hand will serve the turn:</line>
<line>My youth can better spare my blood than you;</line>
<line>And therefore mine shall save my brothers' lives.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Which of your hands hath not defended Rome,</line>
<line>And rear'd aloft the bloody battle-axe,</line>
<line>Writing destruction on the enemy's castle?</line>
<line>O, none of both but are of high desert:</line>
<line>My hand hath been but idle; let it serve</line>
<line>To ransom my two nephews from their death;</line>
<line>Then have I kept it to a worthy end.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Nay, come, agree whose hand shall go along,</line>
<line>For fear they die before their pardon come.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>My hand shall go.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>By heaven, it shall not go!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Sirs, strive no more: such wither'd herbs as these</line>
<line>Are meet for plucking up, and therefore mine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Sweet father, if I shall be thought thy son,</line>
<line>Let me redeem my brothers both from death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>And, for our father's sake and mother's care,</line>
<line>Now let me show a brother's love to thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Agree between you; I will spare my hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Then I'll go fetch an axe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>But I will use the axe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt LUCIUS and MARCUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come hither, Aaron; I'll deceive them both:</line>
<line>Lend me thy hand, and I will give thee mine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  If that be call'd deceit, I will be honest,</line>
<line>And never, whilst I live, deceive men so:</line>
<line>But I'll deceive you in another sort,</line>
<line>And that you'll say, ere half an hour pass.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Cuts off TITUS's hand</para>
<para role="stagedir">Re-enter LUCIUS and MARCUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Now stay your strife: what shall be is dispatch'd.</line>
<line>Good Aaron, give his majesty my hand:</line>
<line>Tell him it was a hand that warded him</line>
<line>From thousand dangers; bid him bury it</line>
<line>More hath it merited; that let it have.</line>
<line>As for my sons, say I account of them</line>
<line>As jewels purchased at an easy price;</line>
<line>And yet dear too, because I bought mine own.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>I go, Andronicus: and for thy hand</line>
<line>Look by and by to have thy sons with thee.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>Their heads, I mean. O, how this villany</line>
<line>Doth fat me with the very thoughts of it!</line>
<line>Let fools do good, and fair men call for grace.</line>
<line>Aaron will have his soul black like his face.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, here I lift this one hand up to heaven,</line>
<line>And bow this feeble ruin to the earth:</line>
<line>If any power pities wretched tears,</line>
<line>To that I call!</line>
<para role="stagedir">To LAVINIA</para>
<line>What, wilt thou kneel with me?</line>
<line>Do, then, dear heart; for heaven shall hear our prayers;</line>
<line>Or with our sighs we'll breathe the welkin dim,</line>
<line>And stain the sun with fog, as sometime clouds</line>
<line>When they do hug him in their melting bosoms.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O brother, speak with possibilities,</line>
<line>And do not break into these deep extremes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Is not my sorrow deep, having no bottom?</line>
<line>Then be my passions bottomless with them.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>But yet let reason govern thy lament.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>If there were reason for these miseries,</line>
<line>Then into limits could I bind my woes:</line>
<line>When heaven doth weep, doth not the earth o'erflow?</line>
<line>If the winds rage, doth not the sea wax mad,</line>
<line>Threatening the welkin with his big-swoln face?</line>
<line>And wilt thou have a reason for this coil?</line>
<line>I am the sea; hark, how her sighs do blow!</line>
<line>She is the weeping welkin, I the earth:</line>
<line>Then must my sea be moved with her sighs;</line>
<line>Then must my earth with her continual tears</line>
<line>Become a deluge, overflow'd and drown'd;</line>
<line>For why my bowels cannot hide her woes,</line>
<line>But like a drunkard must I vomit them.</line>
<line>Then give me leave, for losers will have leave</line>
<line>To ease their stomachs with their bitter tongues.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Messenger, with two heads and a hand</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Messenger</speaker>
<line>Worthy Andronicus, ill art thou repaid</line>
<line>For that good hand thou sent'st the emperor.</line>
<line>Here are the heads of thy two noble sons;</line>
<line>And here's thy hand, in scorn to thee sent back;</line>
<line>Thy griefs their sports, thy resolution mock'd;</line>
<line>That woe is me to think upon thy woes</line>
<line>More than remembrance of my father's death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Now let hot AEtna cool in Sicily,</line>
<line>And be my heart an ever-burning hell!</line>
<line>These miseries are more than may be borne.</line>
<line>To weep with them that weep doth ease some deal;</line>
<line>But sorrow flouted at is double death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Ah, that this sight should make so deep a wound,</line>
<line>And yet detested life not shrink thereat!</line>
<line>That ever death should let life bear his name,</line>
<line>Where life hath no more interest but to breathe!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">LAVINIA kisses TITUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Alas, poor heart, that kiss is comfortless</line>
<line>As frozen water to a starved snake.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>When will this fearful slumber have an end?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Now, farewell, flattery: die, Andronicus;</line>
<line>Thou dost not slumber: see, thy two sons' heads,</line>
<line>Thy warlike hand, thy mangled daughter here:</line>
<line>Thy other banish'd son, with this dear sight</line>
<line>Struck pale and bloodless; and thy brother, I,</line>
<line>Even like a stony image, cold and numb.</line>
<line>Ah, now no more will I control thy griefs:</line>
<line>Rend off thy silver hair, thy other hand</line>
<line>Gnawing with thy teeth; and be this dismal sight</line>
<line>The closing up of our most wretched eyes;</line>
<line>Now is a time to storm; why art thou still?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Ha, ha, ha!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why dost thou laugh? it fits not with this hour.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, I have not another tear to shed:</line>
<line>Besides, this sorrow is an enemy,</line>
<line>And would usurp upon my watery eyes</line>
<line>And make them blind with tributary tears:</line>
<line>Then which way shall I find Revenge's cave?</line>
<line>For these two heads do seem to speak to me,</line>
<line>And threat me I shall never come to bliss</line>
<line>Till all these mischiefs be return'd again</line>
<line>Even in their throats that have committed them.</line>
<line>Come, let me see what task I have to do.</line>
<line>You heavy people, circle me about,</line>
<line>That I may turn me to each one of you,</line>
<line>And swear unto my soul to right your wrongs.</line>
<line>The vow is made. Come, brother, take a head;</line>
<line>And in this hand the other I will bear.</line>
<line>Lavinia, thou shalt be employ'd: these arms!</line>
<line>Bear thou my hand, sweet wench, between thy teeth.</line>
<line>As for thee, boy, go get thee from my sight;</line>
<line>Thou art an exile, and thou must not stay:</line>
<line>Hie to the Goths, and raise an army there:</line>
<line>And, if you love me, as I think you do,</line>
<line>Let's kiss and part, for we have much to do.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt TITUS, MARCUS, and LAVINIA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Farewell Andronicus, my noble father,</line>
<line>The wofull'st man that ever lived in Rome:</line>
<line>Farewell, proud Rome; till Lucius come again,</line>
<line>He leaves his pledges dearer than his life:</line>
<line>Farewell, Lavinia, my noble sister;</line>
<line>O, would thou wert as thou tofore hast been!</line>
<line>But now nor Lucius nor Lavinia lives</line>
<line>But in oblivion and hateful griefs.</line>
<line>If Lucius live, he will requite your wrongs;</line>
<line>And make proud Saturnine and his empress</line>
<line>Beg at the gates, like Tarquin and his queen.</line>
<line>Now will I to the Goths, and raise a power,</line>
<line>To be revenged on Rome and Saturnine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  A room in Titus's house. A banquet set out.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TITUS, MARCUS, LAVINIA and Young LUCIUS, a boy</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>So, so; now sit: and look you eat no more</line>
<line>Than will preserve just so much strength in us</line>
<line>As will revenge these bitter woes of ours.</line>
<line>Marcus, unknit that sorrow-wreathen knot:</line>
<line>Thy niece and I, poor creatures, want our hands,</line>
<line>And cannot passionate our tenfold grief</line>
<line>With folded arms. This poor right hand of mine</line>
<line>Is left to tyrannize upon my breast;</line>
<line>Who, when my heart, all mad with misery,</line>
<line>Beats in this hollow prison of my flesh,</line>
<line>Then thus I thump it down.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To LAVINIA</para>
<line>Thou map of woe, that thus dost talk in signs!</line>
<line>When thy poor heart beats with outrageous beating,</line>
<line>Thou canst not strike it thus to make it still.</line>
<line>Wound it with sighing, girl, kill it with groans;</line>
<line>Or get some little knife between thy teeth,</line>
<line>And just against thy heart make thou a hole;</line>
<line>That all the tears that thy poor eyes let fall</line>
<line>May run into that sink, and soaking in</line>
<line>Drown the lamenting fool in sea-salt tears.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Fie, brother, fie! teach her not thus to lay</line>
<line>Such violent hands upon her tender life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>How now! has sorrow made thee dote already?</line>
<line>Why, Marcus, no man should be mad but I.</line>
<line>What violent hands can she lay on her life?</line>
<line>Ah, wherefore dost thou urge the name of hands;</line>
<line>To bid AEneas tell the tale twice o'er,</line>
<line>How Troy was burnt and he made miserable?</line>
<line>O, handle not the theme, to talk of hands,</line>
<line>Lest we remember still that we have none.</line>
<line>Fie, fie, how franticly I square my talk,</line>
<line>As if we should forget we had no hands,</line>
<line>If Marcus did not name the word of hands!</line>
<line>Come, let's fall to; and, gentle girl, eat this:</line>
<line>Here is no drink! Hark, Marcus, what she says;</line>
<line>I can interpret all her martyr'd signs;</line>
<line>She says she drinks no other drink but tears,</line>
<line>Brew'd with her sorrow, mesh'd upon her cheeks:</line>
<line>Speechless complainer, I will learn thy thought;</line>
<line>In thy dumb action will I be as perfect</line>
<line>As begging hermits in their holy prayers:</line>
<line>Thou shalt not sigh, nor hold thy stumps to heaven,</line>
<line>Nor wink, nor nod, nor kneel, nor make a sign,</line>
<line>But I of these will wrest an alphabet</line>
<line>And by still practise learn to know thy meaning.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Good grandsire, leave these bitter deep laments:</line>
<line>Make my aunt merry with some pleasing tale.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Alas, the tender boy, in passion moved,</line>
<line>Doth weep to see his grandsire's heaviness.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Peace, tender sapling; thou art made of tears,</line>
<line>And tears will quickly melt thy life away.</line>
<para role="stagedir">MARCUS strikes the dish with a knife</para>
<line>What dost thou strike at, Marcus, with thy knife?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>At that that I have kill'd, my lord; a fly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Out on thee, murderer! thou kill'st my heart;</line>
<line>Mine eyes are cloy'd with view of tyranny:</line>
<line>A deed of death done on the innocent</line>
<line>Becomes not Titus' brother: get thee gone:</line>
<line>I see thou art not for my company.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Alas, my lord, I have but kill'd a fly.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>But how, if that fly had a father and mother?</line>
<line>How would he hang his slender gilded wings,</line>
<line>And buzz lamenting doings in the air!</line>
<line>Poor harmless fly,</line>
<line>That, with his pretty buzzing melody,</line>
<line>Came here to make us merry! and thou hast</line>
<line>kill'd him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Pardon me, sir; it was a black ill-favor'd fly,</line>
<line>Like to the empress' Moor; therefore I kill'd him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, O, O,</line>
<line>Then pardon me for reprehending thee,</line>
<line>For thou hast done a charitable deed.</line>
<line>Give me thy knife, I will insult on him;</line>
<line>Flattering myself, as if it were the Moor</line>
<line>Come hither purposely to poison me.--</line>
<line>There's for thyself, and that's for Tamora.</line>
<line>Ah, sirrah!</line>
<line>Yet, I think, we are not brought so low,</line>
<line>But that between us we can kill a fly</line>
<line>That comes in likeness of a coal-black Moor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Alas, poor man! grief has so wrought on him,</line>
<line>He takes false shadows for true substances.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come, take away. Lavinia, go with me:</line>
<line>I'll to thy closet; and go read with thee</line>
<line>Sad stories chanced in the times of old.</line>
<line>Come, boy, and go with me: thy sight is young,</line>
<line>And thou shalt read when mine begin to dazzle.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT IV</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Rome. Titus's garden.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter young LUCIUS, and LAVINIA running after him,
and the boy flies from her, with books under his
arm. Then enter TITUS and MARCUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Help, grandsire, help! my aunt Lavinia</line>
<line>Follows me every where, I know not why:</line>
<line>Good uncle Marcus, see how swift she comes.</line>
<line>Alas, sweet aunt, I know not what you mean.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Stand by me, Lucius; do not fear thine aunt.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>She loves thee, boy, too well to do thee harm.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Ay, when my father was in Rome she did.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>What means my niece Lavinia by these signs?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Fear her not, Lucius: somewhat doth she mean:</line>
<line>See, Lucius, see how much she makes of thee:</line>
<line>Somewhither would she have thee go with her.</line>
<line>Ah, boy, Cornelia never with more care</line>
<line>Read to her sons than she hath read to thee</line>
<line>Sweet poetry and Tully's Orator.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Canst thou not guess wherefore she plies thee thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, I know not, I, nor can I guess,</line>
<line>Unless some fit or frenzy do possess her:</line>
<line>For I have heard my grandsire say full oft,</line>
<line>Extremity of griefs would make men mad;</line>
<line>And I have read that Hecuba of Troy</line>
<line>Ran mad through sorrow: that made me to fear;</line>
<line>Although, my lord, I know my noble aunt</line>
<line>Loves me as dear as e'er my mother did,</line>
<line>And would not, but in fury, fright my youth:</line>
<line>Which made me down to throw my books, and fly--</line>
<line>Causeless, perhaps. But pardon me, sweet aunt:</line>
<line>And, madam, if my uncle Marcus go,</line>
<line>I will most willingly attend your ladyship.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Lucius, I will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">LAVINIA turns over with her stumps the books which
LUCIUS has let fall</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>How now, Lavinia! Marcus, what means this?</line>
<line>Some book there is that she desires to see.</line>
<line>Which is it, girl, of these? Open them, boy.</line>
<line>But thou art deeper read, and better skill'd</line>
<line>Come, and take choice of all my library,</line>
<line>And so beguile thy sorrow, till the heavens</line>
<line>Reveal the damn'd contriver of this deed.</line>
<line>Why lifts she up her arms in sequence thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I think she means that there was more than one</line>
<line>Confederate in the fact: ay, more there was;</line>
<line>Or else to heaven she heaves them for revenge.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Lucius, what book is that she tosseth so?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Grandsire, 'tis Ovid's Metamorphoses;</line>
<line>My mother gave it me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>For love of her that's gone,</line>
<line>Perhaps she cull'd it from among the rest.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Soft! see how busily she turns the leaves!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Helping her</para>
<line>What would she find? Lavinia, shall I read?</line>
<line>This is the tragic tale of Philomel,</line>
<line>And treats of Tereus' treason and his rape:</line>
<line>And rape, I fear, was root of thine annoy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>See, brother, see; note how she quotes the leaves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Lavinia, wert thou thus surprised, sweet girl,</line>
<line>Ravish'd and wrong'd, as Philomela was,</line>
<line>Forced in the ruthless, vast, and gloomy woods? See, see!</line>
<line>Ay, such a place there is, where we did hunt--</line>
<line>O, had we never, never hunted there!--</line>
<line>Pattern'd by that the poet here describes,</line>
<line>By nature made for murders and for rapes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, why should nature build so foul a den,</line>
<line>Unless the gods delight in tragedies?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Give signs, sweet girl, for here are none</line>
<line>but friends,</line>
<line>What Roman lord it was durst do the deed:</line>
<line>Or slunk not Saturnine, as Tarquin erst,</line>
<line>That left the camp to sin in Lucrece' bed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Sit down, sweet niece: brother, sit down by me.</line>
<line>Apollo, Pallas, Jove, or Mercury,</line>
<line>Inspire me, that I may this treason find!</line>
<line>My lord, look here: look here, Lavinia:</line>
<line>This sandy plot is plain; guide, if thou canst</line>
<line>This after me, when I have writ my name</line>
<line>Without the help of any hand at all.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He writes his name with his staff, and guides it
with feet and mouth</para>
<line>Cursed be that heart that forced us to this shift!</line>
<line>Write thou good niece; and here display, at last,</line>
<line>What God will have discover'd for revenge;</line>
<line>Heaven guide thy pen to print thy sorrows plain,</line>
<line>That we may know the traitors and the truth!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">She takes the staff in her mouth, and guides it
with her stumps, and writes</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, do ye read, my lord, what she hath writ?</line>
<line>'Stuprum. Chiron. Demetrius.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>What, what! the lustful sons of Tamora</line>
<line>Performers of this heinous, bloody deed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Magni Dominator poli,</line>
<line>Tam lentus audis scelera? tam lentus vides?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O, calm thee, gentle lord; although I know</line>
<line>There is enough written upon this earth</line>
<line>To stir a mutiny in the mildest thoughts</line>
<line>And arm the minds of infants to exclaims.</line>
<line>My lord, kneel down with me; Lavinia, kneel;</line>
<line>And kneel, sweet boy, the Roman Hector's hope;</line>
<line>And swear with me, as, with the woful fere</line>
<line>And father of that chaste dishonour'd dame,</line>
<line>Lord Junius Brutus sware for Lucrece' rape,</line>
<line>That we will prosecute by good advice</line>
<line>Mortal revenge upon these traitorous Goths,</line>
<line>And see their blood, or die with this reproach.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>'Tis sure enough, an you knew how.</line>
<line>But if you hunt these bear-whelps, then beware:</line>
<line>The dam will wake; and, if she wind you once,</line>
<line>She's with the lion deeply still in league,</line>
<line>And lulls him whilst she playeth on her back,</line>
<line>And when he sleeps will she do what she list.</line>
<line>You are a young huntsman, Marcus; let it alone;</line>
<line>And, come, I will go get a leaf of brass,</line>
<line>And with a gad of steel will write these words,</line>
<line>And lay it by: the angry northern wind</line>
<line>Will blow these sands, like Sibyl's leaves, abroad,</line>
<line>And where's your lesson, then? Boy, what say you?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>I say, my lord, that if I were a man,</line>
<line>Their mother's bed-chamber should not be safe</line>
<line>For these bad bondmen to the yoke of Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Ay, that's my boy! thy father hath full oft</line>
<line>For his ungrateful country done the like.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>And, uncle, so will I, an if I live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come, go with me into mine armoury;</line>
<line>Lucius, I'll fit thee; and withal, my boy,</line>
<line>Shalt carry from me to the empress' sons</line>
<line>Presents that I intend to send them both:</line>
<line>Come, come; thou'lt do thy message, wilt thou not?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Ay, with my dagger in their bosoms, grandsire.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>No, boy, not so; I'll teach thee another course.</line>
<line>Lavinia, come. Marcus, look to my house:</line>
<line>Lucius and I'll go brave it at the court:</line>
<line>Ay, marry, will we, sir; and we'll be waited on.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt TITUS, LAVINIA, and Young LUCIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O heavens, can you hear a good man groan,</line>
<line>And not relent, or not compassion him?</line>
<line>Marcus, attend him in his ecstasy,</line>
<line>That hath more scars of sorrow in his heart</line>
<line>Than foemen's marks upon his batter'd shield;</line>
<line>But yet so just that he will not revenge.</line>
<line>Revenge, ye heavens, for old Andronicus!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  The same. A room in the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter, from one side, AARON, DEMETRIUS, and
CHIRON; from the other side, Young LUCIUS, and an
Attendant, with a bundle of weapons, and verses
writ upon them</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Demetrius, here's the son of Lucius;</line>
<line>He hath some message to deliver us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Ay, some mad message from his mad grandfather.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>My lords, with all the humbleness I may,</line>
<line>I greet your honours from Andronicus.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>And pray the Roman gods confound you both!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Gramercy, lovely Lucius: what's the news?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  That you are both decipher'd, that's the news,</line>
<line>For villains mark'd with rape.--May it please you,</line>
<line>My grandsire, well advised, hath sent by me</line>
<line>The goodliest weapons of his armoury</line>
<line>To gratify your honourable youth,</line>
<line>The hope of Rome; for so he bade me say;</line>
<line>And so I do, and with his gifts present</line>
<line>Your lordships, that, whenever you have need,</line>
<line>You may be armed and appointed well:</line>
<line>And so I leave you both:</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>like bloody villains.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Young LUCIUS, and Attendant</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>What's here? A scroll; and written round about?</line>
<line>Let's see;</line>
<para role="stagedir">Reads</para>
<line>'Integer vitae, scelerisque purus,</line>
<line>Non eget Mauri jaculis, nec arcu.'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>O, 'tis a verse in Horace; I know it well:</line>
<line>I read it in the grammar long ago.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Ay, just; a verse in Horace; right, you have it.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>Now, what a thing it is to be an ass!</line>
<line>Here's no sound jest! the old man hath found their guilt;</line>
<line>And sends them weapons wrapped about with lines,</line>
<line>That wound, beyond their feeling, to the quick.</line>
<line>But were our witty empress well afoot,</line>
<line>She would applaud Andronicus' conceit:</line>
<line>But let her rest in her unrest awhile.</line>
<line>And now, young lords, was't not a happy star</line>
<line>Led us to Rome, strangers, and more than so,</line>
<line>Captives, to be advanced to this height?</line>
<line>It did me good, before the palace gate</line>
<line>To brave the tribune in his brother's hearing.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>But me more good, to see so great a lord</line>
<line>Basely insinuate and send us gifts.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Had he not reason, Lord Demetrius?</line>
<line>Did you not use his daughter very friendly?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>I would we had a thousand Roman dames</line>
<line>At such a bay, by turn to serve our lust.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>A charitable wish and full of love.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Here lacks but your mother for to say amen.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>And that would she for twenty thousand more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Come, let us go; and pray to all the gods</line>
<line>For our beloved mother in her pains.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  Pray to the devils; the gods have given us over.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Trumpets sound within</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Why do the emperor's trumpets flourish thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Belike, for joy the emperor hath a son.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Soft! who comes here?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Nurse, with a blackamoor Child in her arms</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>Good morrow, lords:</line>
<line>O, tell me, did you see Aaron the Moor?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Well, more or less, or ne'er a whit at all,</line>
<line>Here Aaron is; and what with Aaron now?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>O gentle Aaron, we are all undone!</line>
<line>Now help, or woe betide thee evermore!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, what a caterwauling dost thou keep!</line>
<line>What dost thou wrap and fumble in thine arms?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>O, that which I would hide from heaven's eye,</line>
<line>Our empress' shame, and stately Rome's disgrace!</line>
<line>She is deliver'd, lords; she is deliver'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>To whom?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>I mean, she is brought a-bed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Well, God give her good rest! What hath he sent her?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>A devil.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, then she is the devil's dam; a joyful issue.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>A joyless, dismal, black, and sorrowful issue:</line>
<line>Here is the babe, as loathsome as a toad</line>
<line>Amongst the fairest breeders of our clime:</line>
<line>The empress sends it thee, thy stamp, thy seal,</line>
<line>And bids thee christen it with thy dagger's point.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>'Zounds, ye whore! is black so base a hue?</line>
<line>Sweet blowse, you are a beauteous blossom, sure.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Villain, what hast thou done?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>That which thou canst not undo.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Thou hast undone our mother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Villain, I have done thy mother.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>And therein, hellish dog, thou hast undone.</line>
<line>Woe to her chance, and damn'd her loathed choice!</line>
<line>Accursed the offspring of so foul a fiend!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>It shall not live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>It shall not die.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>Aaron, it must; the mother wills it so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>What, must it, nurse? then let no man but I</line>
<line>Do execution on my flesh and blood.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>I'll broach the tadpole on my rapier's point:</line>
<line>Nurse, give it me; my sword shall soon dispatch it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Sooner this sword shall plough thy bowels up.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Takes the Child from the Nurse, and draws</para>
<line>Stay, murderous villains! will you kill your brother?</line>
<line>Now, by the burning tapers of the sky,</line>
<line>That shone so brightly when this boy was got,</line>
<line>He dies upon my scimitar's sharp point</line>
<line>That touches this my first-born son and heir!</line>
<line>I tell you, younglings, not Enceladus,</line>
<line>With all his threatening band of Typhon's brood,</line>
<line>Nor great Alcides, nor the god of war,</line>
<line>Shall seize this prey out of his father's hands.</line>
<line>What, what, ye sanguine, shallow-hearted boys!</line>
<line>Ye white-limed walls! ye alehouse painted signs!</line>
<line>Coal-black is better than another hue,</line>
<line>In that it scorns to bear another hue;</line>
<line>For all the water in the ocean</line>
<line>Can never turn the swan's black legs to white,</line>
<line>Although she lave them hourly in the flood.</line>
<line>Tell the empress from me, I am of age</line>
<line>To keep mine own, excuse it how she can.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou betray thy noble mistress thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>My mistress is my mistress; this myself,</line>
<line>The vigour and the picture of my youth:</line>
<line>This before all the world do I prefer;</line>
<line>This maugre all the world will I keep safe,</line>
<line>Or some of you shall smoke for it in Rome.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>By this our mother is forever shamed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Rome will despise her for this foul escape.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>The emperor, in his rage, will doom her death.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>I blush to think upon this ignomy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, there's the privilege your beauty bears:</line>
<line>Fie, treacherous hue, that will betray with blushing</line>
<line>The close enacts and counsels of the heart!</line>
<line>Here's a young lad framed of another leer:</line>
<line>Look, how the black slave smiles upon the father,</line>
<line>As who should say 'Old lad, I am thine own.'</line>
<line>He is your brother, lords, sensibly fed</line>
<line>Of that self-blood that first gave life to you,</line>
<line>And from that womb where you imprison'd were</line>
<line>He is enfranchised and come to light:</line>
<line>Nay, he is your brother by the surer side,</line>
<line>Although my seal be stamped in his face.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>Aaron, what shall I say unto the empress?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Advise thee, Aaron, what is to be done,</line>
<line>And we will all subscribe to thy advice:</line>
<line>Save thou the child, so we may all be safe.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Then sit we down, and let us all consult.</line>
<line>My son and I will have the wind of you:</line>
<line>Keep there: now talk at pleasure of your safety.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They sit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>How many women saw this child of his?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, so, brave lords! when we join in league,</line>
<line>I am a lamb: but if you brave the Moor,</line>
<line>The chafed boar, the mountain lioness,</line>
<line>The ocean swells not so as Aaron storms.</line>
<line>But say, again; how many saw the child?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Nurse</speaker>
<line>Cornelia the midwife and myself;</line>
<line>And no one else but the deliver'd empress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>The empress, the midwife, and yourself:</line>
<line>Two may keep counsel when the third's away:</line>
<line>Go to the empress, tell her this I said.</line>
<para role="stagedir">He kills the nurse</para>
<line>Weke, weke! so cries a pig prepared to the spit.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>What mean'st thou, Aaron? wherefore didst thou this?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>O Lord, sir, 'tis a deed of policy:</line>
<line>Shall she live to betray this guilt of ours,</line>
<line>A long-tongued babbling gossip? no, lords, no:</line>
<line>And now be it known to you my full intent.</line>
<line>Not far, one Muli lives, my countryman;</line>
<line>His wife but yesternight was brought to bed;</line>
<line>His child is like to her, fair as you are:</line>
<line>Go pack with him, and give the mother gold,</line>
<line>And tell them both the circumstance of all;</line>
<line>And how by this their child shall be advanced,</line>
<line>And be received for the emperor's heir,</line>
<line>And substituted in the place of mine,</line>
<line>To calm this tempest whirling in the court;</line>
<line>And let the emperor dandle him for his own.</line>
<line>Hark ye, lords; ye see I have given her physic,</line>
<para role="stagedir">Pointing to the nurse</para>
<line>And you must needs bestow her funeral;</line>
<line>The fields are near, and you are gallant grooms:</line>
<line>This done, see that you take no longer days,</line>
<line>But send the midwife presently to me.</line>
<line>The midwife and the nurse well made away,</line>
<line>Then let the ladies tattle what they please.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Aaron, I see thou wilt not trust the air</line>
<line>With secrets.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>For this care of Tamora,</line>
<line>Herself and hers are highly bound to thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt DEMETRIUS and CHIRON bearing off the
Nurse's body</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Now to the Goths, as swift as swallow flies;</line>
<line>There to dispose this treasure in mine arms,</line>
<line>And secretly to greet the empress' friends.</line>
<line>Come on, you thick lipp'd slave, I'll bear you hence;</line>
<line>For it is you that puts us to our shifts:</line>
<line>I'll make you feed on berries and on roots,</line>
<line>And feed on curds and whey, and suck the goat,</line>
<line>And cabin in a cave, and bring you up</line>
<line>To be a warrior, and command a camp.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  The same. A public place.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TITUS, bearing arrows with letters at the
ends of them; with him, MARCUS, Young LUCIUS,
PUBLIUS, SEMPRONIUS, CAIUS, and other Gentlemen,
with bows</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come, Marcus; come, kinsmen; this is the way.</line>
<line>Sir boy, now let me see your archery;</line>
<line>Look ye draw home enough, and 'tis there straight.</line>
<line>Terras Astraea reliquit:</line>
<line>Be you remember'd, Marcus, she's gone, she's fled.</line>
<line>Sirs, take you to your tools. You, cousins, shall</line>
<line>Go sound the ocean, and cast your nets;</line>
<line>Happily you may catch her in the sea;</line>
<line>Yet there's as little justice as at land:</line>
<line>No; Publius and Sempronius, you must do it;</line>
<line>'Tis you must dig with mattock and with spade,</line>
<line>And pierce the inmost centre of the earth:</line>
<line>Then, when you come to Pluto's region,</line>
<line>I pray you, deliver him this petition;</line>
<line>Tell him, it is for justice and for aid,</line>
<line>And that it comes from old Andronicus,</line>
<line>Shaken with sorrows in ungrateful Rome.</line>
<line>Ah, Rome! Well, well; I made thee miserable</line>
<line>What time I threw the people's suffrages</line>
<line>On him that thus doth tyrannize o'er me.</line>
<line>Go, get you gone; and pray be careful all,</line>
<line>And leave you not a man-of-war unsearch'd:</line>
<line>This wicked emperor may have shipp'd her hence;</line>
<line>And, kinsmen, then we may go pipe for justice.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>O Publius, is not this a heavy case,</line>
<line>To see thy noble uncle thus distract?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PUBLIUS</speaker>
<line>Therefore, my lord, it highly us concerns</line>
<line>By day and night to attend him carefully,</line>
<line>And feed his humour kindly as we may,</line>
<line>Till time beget some careful remedy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Kinsmen, his sorrows are past remedy.</line>
<line>Join with the Goths; and with revengeful war</line>
<line>Take wreak on Rome for this ingratitude,</line>
<line>And vengeance on the traitor Saturnine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Publius, how now! how now, my masters!</line>
<line>What, have you met with her?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PUBLIUS</speaker>
<line>No, my good lord; but Pluto sends you word,</line>
<line>If you will have Revenge from hell, you shall:</line>
<line>Marry, for Justice, she is so employ'd,</line>
<line>He thinks, with Jove in heaven, or somewhere else,</line>
<line>So that perforce you must needs stay a time.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>He doth me wrong to feed me with delays.</line>
<line>I'll dive into the burning lake below,</line>
<line>And pull her out of Acheron by the heels.</line>
<line>Marcus, we are but shrubs, no cedars we</line>
<line>No big-boned men framed of the Cyclops' size;</line>
<line>But metal, Marcus, steel to the very back,</line>
<line>Yet wrung with wrongs more than our backs can bear:</line>
<line>And, sith there's no justice in earth nor hell,</line>
<line>We will solicit heaven and move the gods</line>
<line>To send down Justice for to wreak our wrongs.</line>
<line>Come, to this gear. You are a good archer, Marcus;</line>
<para role="stagedir">He gives them the arrows</para>
<line>'Ad Jovem,' that's for you: here, 'Ad Apollinem:'</line>
<line>'Ad Martem,' that's for myself:</line>
<line>Here, boy, to Pallas: here, to Mercury:</line>
<line>To Saturn, Caius, not to Saturnine;</line>
<line>You were as good to shoot against the wind.</line>
<line>To it, boy! Marcus, loose when I bid.</line>
<line>Of my word, I have written to effect;</line>
<line>There's not a god left unsolicited.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Kinsmen, shoot all your shafts into the court:</line>
<line>We will afflict the emperor in his pride.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Now, masters, draw.</line>
<para role="stagedir">They shoot</para>
<line>O, well said, Lucius!</line>
<line>Good boy, in Virgo's lap; give it Pallas.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>My lord, I aim a mile beyond the moon;</line>
<line>Your letter is with Jupiter by this.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Ha, ha!</line>
<line>Publius, Publius, what hast thou done?</line>
<line>See, see, thou hast shot off one of Taurus' horns.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>This was the sport, my lord: when Publius shot,</line>
<line>The Bull, being gall'd, gave Aries such a knock</line>
<line>That down fell both the Ram's horns in the court;</line>
<line>And who should find them but the empress' villain?</line>
<line>She laugh'd, and told the Moor he should not choose</line>
<line>But give them to his master for a present.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, there it goes: God give his lordship joy!</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter a Clown, with a basket, and two pigeons in
it</para>
<line>News, news from heaven! Marcus, the post is come.</line>
<line>Sirrah, what tidings? have you any letters?</line>
<line>Shall I have justice? what says Jupiter?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>O, the gibbet-maker! he says that he hath taken</line>
<line>them down again, for the man must not be hanged till</line>
<line>the next week.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>But what says Jupiter, I ask thee?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>Alas, sir, I know not Jupiter; I never drank with him</line>
<line>in all my life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, villain, art not thou the carrier?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>Ay, of my pigeons, sir; nothing else.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, didst thou not come from heaven?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>From heaven! alas, sir, I never came there     God</line>
<line>forbid I should be so bold to press to heaven in my</line>
<line>young days. Why, I am going with my pigeons to the</line>
<line>tribunal plebs, to take up a matter of brawl</line>
<line>betwixt my uncle and one of the emperial's men.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, sir, that is as fit as can be to serve for</line>
<line>your oration; and let him deliver the pigeons to</line>
<line>the emperor from you.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Tell me, can you deliver an oration to the emperor</line>
<line>with a grace?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>Nay, truly, sir, I could never say grace in all my life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Sirrah, come hither: make no more ado,</line>
<line>But give your pigeons to the emperor:</line>
<line>By me thou shalt have justice at his hands.</line>
<line>Hold, hold; meanwhile here's money for thy charges.</line>
<line>Give me pen and ink. Sirrah, can you with a grace</line>
<line>deliver a supplication?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>Ay, sir.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Then here is a supplication for you. And when you</line>
<line>come to him, at the first approach you must kneel,</line>
<line>then kiss his foot, then deliver up your pigeons, and</line>
<line>then look for your reward. I'll be at hand, sir; see</line>
<line>you do it bravely.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>I warrant you, sir, let me alone.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Sirrah, hast thou a knife? come, let me see it.</line>
<line>Here, Marcus, fold it in the oration;</line>
<line>For thou hast made it like an humble suppliant.</line>
<line>And when thou hast given it the emperor,</line>
<line>Knock at my door, and tell me what he says.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>God be with you, sir; I will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come, Marcus, let us go. Publius, follow me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE IV.  The same. Before the palace.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter SATURNINUS, TAMORA, DEMETRIUS, CHIRON,
Lords, and others; SATURNINUS with the arrows in
his hand that TITUS shot</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Why, lords, what wrongs are these! was ever seen</line>
<line>An emperor in Rome thus overborne,</line>
<line>Troubled, confronted thus; and, for the extent</line>
<line>Of egal justice, used in such contempt?</line>
<line>My lords, you know, as know the mightful gods,</line>
<line>However these disturbers of our peace</line>
<line>Buz in the people's ears, there nought hath pass'd,</line>
<line>But even with law, against the willful sons</line>
<line>Of old Andronicus. And what an if</line>
<line>His sorrows have so overwhelm'd his wits,</line>
<line>Shall we be thus afflicted in his wreaks,</line>
<line>His fits, his frenzy, and his bitterness?</line>
<line>And now he writes to heaven for his redress:</line>
<line>See, here's to Jove, and this to Mercury;</line>
<line>This to Apollo; this to the god of war;</line>
<line>Sweet scrolls to fly about the streets of Rome!</line>
<line>What's this but libelling against the senate,</line>
<line>And blazoning our injustice every where?</line>
<line>A goodly humour, is it not, my lords?</line>
<line>As who would say, in Rome no justice were.</line>
<line>But if I live, his feigned ecstasies</line>
<line>Shall be no shelter to these outrages:</line>
<line>But he and his shall know that justice lives</line>
<line>In Saturninus' health, whom, if she sleep,</line>
<line>He'll so awake as she in fury shall</line>
<line>Cut off the proud'st conspirator that lives.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>My gracious lord, my lovely Saturnine,</line>
<line>Lord of my life, commander of my thoughts,</line>
<line>Calm thee, and bear the faults of Titus' age,</line>
<line>The effects of sorrow for his valiant sons,</line>
<line>Whose loss hath pierced him deep and scarr'd his heart;</line>
<line>And rather comfort his distressed plight</line>
<line>Than prosecute the meanest or the best</line>
<line>For these contempts.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Aside</para>
<line>Why, thus it shall become</line>
<line>High-witted Tamora to gloze with all:</line>
<line>But, Titus, I have touched thee to the quick,</line>
<line>Thy life-blood out: if Aaron now be wise,</line>
<line>Then is all safe, the anchor's in the port.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter Clown</para>
<line>How now, good fellow! wouldst thou speak with us?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>Yea, forsooth, an your mistership be emperial.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Empress I am, but yonder sits the emperor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>'Tis he. God and Saint Stephen give you good den:</line>
<line>I have brought you a letter and a couple of pigeons here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">SATURNINUS reads the letter</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Go, take him away, and hang him presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>How much money must I have?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Come, sirrah, you must be hanged.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Clown</speaker>
<line>Hanged! by'r lady, then I have brought up a neck to</line>
<line>a fair end.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit, guarded</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Despiteful and intolerable wrongs!</line>
<line>Shall I endure this monstrous villany?</line>
<line>I know from whence this same device proceeds:</line>
<line>May this be borne?--as if his traitorous sons,</line>
<line>That died by law for murder of our brother,</line>
<line>Have by my means been butcher'd wrongfully!</line>
<line>Go, drag the villain hither by the hair;</line>
<line>Nor age nor honour shall shape privilege:</line>
<line>For this proud mock I'll be thy slaughterman;</line>
<line>Sly frantic wretch, that holp'st to make me great,</line>
<line>In hope thyself should govern Rome and me.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter AEMILIUS</para>
<line>What news with thee, AEmilius?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AEMILIUS</speaker>
<line>Arm, arm, my lord;--Rome never had more cause.</line>
<line>The Goths have gather'd head; and with a power</line>
<line>high-resolved men, bent to the spoil,</line>
<line>They hither march amain, under conduct</line>
<line>Of Lucius, son to old Andronicus;</line>
<line>Who threats, in course of this revenge, to do</line>
<line>As much as ever Coriolanus did.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Is warlike Lucius general of the Goths?</line>
<line>These tidings nip me, and I hang the head</line>
<line>As flowers with frost or grass beat down with storms:</line>
<line>Ay, now begin our sorrows to approach:</line>
<line>'Tis he the common people love so much;</line>
<line>Myself hath often over-heard them say,</line>
<line>When I have walked like a private man,</line>
<line>That Lucius' banishment was wrongfully,</line>
<line>And they have wish'd that Lucius were their emperor.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Why should you fear? is not your city strong?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Ay, but the citizens favor Lucius,</line>
<line>And will revolt from me to succor him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>King, be thy thoughts imperious, like thy name.</line>
<line>Is the sun dimm'd, that gnats do fly in it?</line>
<line>The eagle suffers little birds to sing,</line>
<line>And is not careful what they mean thereby,</line>
<line>Knowing that with the shadow of his wings</line>
<line>He can at pleasure stint their melody:</line>
<line>Even so mayst thou the giddy men of Rome.</line>
<line>Then cheer thy spirit : for know, thou emperor,</line>
<line>I will enchant the old Andronicus</line>
<line>With words more sweet, and yet more dangerous,</line>
<line>Than baits to fish, or honey-stalks to sheep,</line>
<line>When as the one is wounded with the bait,</line>
<line>The other rotted with delicious feed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>But he will not entreat his son for us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>If Tamora entreat him, then he will:</line>
<line>For I can smooth and fill his aged ear</line>
<line>With golden promises; that, were his heart</line>
<line>Almost impregnable, his old ears deaf,</line>
<line>Yet should both ear and heart obey my tongue.</line>
<para role="stagedir">To AEmilius</para>
<line>Go thou before, be our ambassador:</line>
<line>Say that the emperor requests a parley</line>
<line>Of warlike Lucius, and appoint the meeting</line>
<line>Even at his father's house, the old Andronicus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>AEmilius, do this message honourably:</line>
<line>And if he stand on hostage for his safety,</line>
<line>Bid him demand what pledge will please him best.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AEMILIUS</speaker>
<line>Your bidding shall I do effectually.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Now will I to that old Andronicus;</line>
<line>And temper him with all the art I have,</line>
<line>To pluck proud Lucius from the warlike Goths.</line>
<line>And now, sweet emperor, be blithe again,</line>
<line>And bury all thy fear in my devices.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Then go successantly, and plead to him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter role="act"><title>ACT V</title>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE I.  Plains near Rome.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter LUCIUS with an army of Goths, with drum and colours</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Approved warriors, and my faithful friends,</line>
<line>I have received letters from great Rome,</line>
<line>Which signify what hate they bear their emperor</line>
<line>And how desirous of our sight they are.</line>
<line>Therefore, great lords, be, as your titles witness,</line>
<line>Imperious and impatient of your wrongs,</line>
<line>And wherein Rome hath done you any scath,</line>
<line>Let him make treble satisfaction.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Goth</speaker>
<line>Brave slip, sprung from the great Andronicus,</line>
<line>Whose name was once our terror, now our comfort;</line>
<line>Whose high exploits and honourable deeds</line>
<line>Ingrateful Rome requites with foul contempt,</line>
<line>Be bold in us: we'll follow where thou lead'st,</line>
<line>Like stinging bees in hottest summer's day</line>
<line>Led by their master to the flowered fields,</line>
<line>And be avenged on cursed Tamora.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All the Goths</speaker>
<line>And as he saith, so say we all with him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>I humbly thank him, and I thank you all.</line>
<line>But who comes here, led by a lusty Goth?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Goth, leading AARON with his Child in his arms</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Second Goth</speaker>
<line>Renowned Lucius, from our troops I stray'd</line>
<line>To gaze upon a ruinous monastery;</line>
<line>And, as I earnestly did fix mine eye</line>
<line>Upon the wasted building, suddenly</line>
<line>I heard a child cry underneath a wall.</line>
<line>I made unto the noise; when soon I heard</line>
<line>The crying babe controll'd with this discourse:</line>
<line>'Peace, tawny slave, half me and half thy dam!</line>
<line>Did not thy hue bewray whose brat thou art,</line>
<line>Had nature lent thee but thy mother's look,</line>
<line>Villain, thou mightst have been an emperor:</line>
<line>But where the bull and cow are both milk-white,</line>
<line>They never do beget a coal-black calf.</line>
<line>Peace, villain, peace!'--even thus he rates</line>
<line>the babe,--</line>
<line>'For I must bear thee to a trusty Goth;</line>
<line>Who, when he knows thou art the empress' babe,</line>
<line>Will hold thee dearly for thy mother's sake.'</line>
<line>With this, my weapon drawn, I rush'd upon him,</line>
<line>Surprised him suddenly, and brought him hither,</line>
<line>To use as you think needful of the man.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O worthy Goth, this is the incarnate devil</line>
<line>That robb'd Andronicus of his good hand;</line>
<line>This is the pearl that pleased your empress' eye,</line>
<line>And here's the base fruit of his burning lust.</line>
<line>Say, wall-eyed slave, whither wouldst thou convey</line>
<line>This growing image of thy fiend-like face?</line>
<line>Why dost not speak? what, deaf? not a word?</line>
<line>A halter, soldiers! hang him on this tree.</line>
<line>And by his side his fruit of bastardy.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Touch not the boy; he is of royal blood.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Too like the sire for ever being good.</line>
<line>First hang the child, that he may see it sprawl;</line>
<line>A sight to vex the father's soul withal.</line>
<line>Get me a ladder.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">A ladder brought, which AARON is made to ascend</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Lucius, save the child,</line>
<line>And bear it from me to the empress.</line>
<line>If thou do this, I'll show thee wondrous things,</line>
<line>That highly may advantage thee to hear:</line>
<line>If thou wilt not, befall what may befall,</line>
<line>I'll speak no more but 'Vengeance rot you all!'</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Say on: an if it please me which thou speak'st</line>
<line>Thy child shall live, and I will see it nourish'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>An if it please thee! why, assure thee, Lucius,</line>
<line>'Twill vex thy soul to hear what I shall speak;</line>
<line>For I must talk of murders, rapes and massacres,</line>
<line>Acts of black night, abominable deeds,</line>
<line>Complots of mischief, treason, villanies</line>
<line>Ruthful to hear, yet piteously perform'd:</line>
<line>And this shall all be buried by my death,</line>
<line>Unless thou swear to me my child shall live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Tell on thy mind; I say thy child shall live.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Swear that he shall, and then I will begin.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Who should I swear by? thou believest no god:</line>
<line>That granted, how canst thou believe an oath?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>What if I do not? as, indeed, I do not;</line>
<line>Yet, for I know thou art religious</line>
<line>And hast a thing within thee called conscience,</line>
<line>With twenty popish tricks and ceremonies,</line>
<line>Which I have seen thee careful to observe,</line>
<line>Therefore I urge thy oath; for that I know</line>
<line>An idiot holds his bauble for a god</line>
<line>And keeps the oath which by that god he swears,</line>
<line>To that I'll urge him: therefore thou shalt vow</line>
<line>By that same god, what god soe'er it be,</line>
<line>That thou adorest and hast in reverence,</line>
<line>To save my boy, to nourish and bring him up;</line>
<line>Or else I will discover nought to thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Even by my god I swear to thee I will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>First know thou, I begot him on the empress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O most insatiate and luxurious woman!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Tut, Lucius, this was but a deed of charity</line>
<line>To that which thou shalt hear of me anon.</line>
<line>'Twas her two sons that murder'd Bassianus;</line>
<line>They cut thy sister's tongue and ravish'd her</line>
<line>And cut her hands and trimm'd her as thou saw'st.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O detestable villain! call'st thou that trimming?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Why, she was wash'd and cut and trimm'd, and 'twas</line>
<line>Trim sport for them that had the doing of it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O barbarous, beastly villains, like thyself!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Indeed, I was their tutor to instruct them:</line>
<line>That codding spirit had they from their mother,</line>
<line>As sure a card as ever won the set;</line>
<line>That bloody mind, I think, they learn'd of me,</line>
<line>As true a dog as ever fought at head.</line>
<line>Well, let my deeds be witness of my worth.</line>
<line>I train'd thy brethren to that guileful hole</line>
<line>Where the dead corpse of Bassianus lay:</line>
<line>I wrote the letter that thy father found</line>
<line>And hid the gold within the letter mention'd,</line>
<line>Confederate with the queen and her two sons:</line>
<line>And what not done, that thou hast cause to rue,</line>
<line>Wherein I had no stroke of mischief in it?</line>
<line>I play'd the cheater for thy father's hand,</line>
<line>And, when I had it, drew myself apart</line>
<line>And almost broke my heart with extreme laughter:</line>
<line>I pry'd me through the crevice of a wall</line>
<line>When, for his hand, he had his two sons' heads;</line>
<line>Beheld his tears, and laugh'd so heartily,</line>
<line>That both mine eyes were rainy like to his :</line>
<line>And when I told the empress of this sport,</line>
<line>She swooned almost at my pleasing tale,</line>
<line>And for my tidings gave me twenty kisses.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Goth</speaker>
<line>What, canst thou say all this, and never blush?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Ay, like a black dog, as the saying is.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Art thou not sorry for these heinous deeds?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Ay, that I had not done a thousand more.</line>
<line>Even now I curse the day--and yet, I think,</line>
<line>Few come within the compass of my curse,--</line>
<line>Wherein I did not some notorious ill,</line>
<line>As kill a man, or else devise his death,</line>
<line>Ravish a maid, or plot the way to do it,</line>
<line>Accuse some innocent and forswear myself,</line>
<line>Set deadly enmity between two friends,</line>
<line>Make poor men's cattle break their necks;</line>
<line>Set fire on barns and hay-stacks in the night,</line>
<line>And bid the owners quench them with their tears.</line>
<line>Oft have I digg'd up dead men from their graves,</line>
<line>And set them upright at their dear friends' doors,</line>
<line>Even when their sorrows almost were forgot;</line>
<line>And on their skins, as on the bark of trees,</line>
<line>Have with my knife carved in Roman letters,</line>
<line>'Let not your sorrow die, though I am dead.'</line>
<line>Tut, I have done a thousand dreadful things</line>
<line>As willingly as one would kill a fly,</line>
<line>And nothing grieves me heartily indeed</line>
<line>But that I cannot do ten thousand more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Bring down the devil; for he must not die</line>
<line>So sweet a death as hanging presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>If there be devils, would I were a devil,</line>
<line>To live and burn in everlasting fire,</line>
<line>So I might have your company in hell,</line>
<line>But to torment you with my bitter tongue!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Sirs, stop his mouth, and let him speak no more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter a Goth</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Third Goth</speaker>
<line>My lord, there is a messenger from Rome</line>
<line>Desires to be admitted to your presence.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Let him come near.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter AEMILIUS</para>
<line>Welcome, AEmilius what's the news from Rome?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AEMILIUS</speaker>
<line>Lord Lucius, and you princes of the Goths,</line>
<line>The Roman emperor greets you all by me;</line>
<line>And, for he understands you are in arms,</line>
<line>He craves a parley at your father's house,</line>
<line>Willing you to demand your hostages,</line>
<line>And they shall be immediately deliver'd.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Goth</speaker>
<line>What says our general?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>AEmilius, let the emperor give his pledges</line>
<line>Unto my father and my uncle Marcus,</line>
<line>And we will come. March away.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE II.  Rome. Before TITUS's house.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TAMORA, DEMETRIUS, and CHIRON, disguised</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Thus, in this strange and sad habiliment,</line>
<line>I will encounter with Andronicus,</line>
<line>And say I am Revenge, sent from below</line>
<line>To join with him and right his heinous wrongs.</line>
<line>Knock at his study, where, they say, he keeps,</line>
<line>To ruminate strange plots of dire revenge;</line>
<line>Tell him Revenge is come to join with him,</line>
<line>And work confusion on his enemies.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">They knock</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TITUS, above</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Who doth molest my contemplation?</line>
<line>Is it your trick to make me ope the door,</line>
<line>That so my sad decrees may fly away,</line>
<line>And all my study be to no effect?</line>
<line>You are deceived: for what I mean to do</line>
<line>See here in bloody lines I have set down;</line>
<line>And what is written shall be executed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Titus, I am come to talk with thee.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>No, not a word; how can I grace my talk,</line>
<line>Wanting a hand to give it action?</line>
<line>Thou hast the odds of me; therefore no more.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>If thou didst know me, thou wouldest talk with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I am not mad; I know thee well enough:</line>
<line>Witness this wretched stump, witness these crimson lines;</line>
<line>Witness these trenches made by grief and care,</line>
<line>Witness the tiring day and heavy night;</line>
<line>Witness all sorrow, that I know thee well</line>
<line>For our proud empress, mighty Tamora:</line>
<line>Is not thy coming for my other hand?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Know, thou sad man, I am not Tamora;</line>
<line>She is thy enemy, and I thy friend:</line>
<line>I am Revenge: sent from the infernal kingdom,</line>
<line>To ease the gnawing vulture of thy mind,</line>
<line>By working wreakful vengeance on thy foes.</line>
<line>Come down, and welcome me to this world's light;</line>
<line>Confer with me of murder and of death:</line>
<line>There's not a hollow cave or lurking-place,</line>
<line>No vast obscurity or misty vale,</line>
<line>Where bloody murder or detested rape</line>
<line>Can couch for fear, but I will find them out;</line>
<line>And in their ears tell them my dreadful name,</line>
<line>Revenge, which makes the foul offender quake.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Art thou Revenge? and art thou sent to me,</line>
<line>To be a torment to mine enemies?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>I am; therefore come down, and welcome me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Do me some service, ere I come to thee.</line>
<line>Lo, by thy side where Rape and Murder stands;</line>
<line>Now give me some surance that thou art Revenge,</line>
<line>Stab them, or tear them on thy chariot-wheels;</line>
<line>And then I'll come and be thy waggoner,</line>
<line>And whirl along with thee about the globe.</line>
<line>Provide thee two proper palfreys, black as jet,</line>
<line>To hale thy vengeful waggon swift away,</line>
<line>And find out murderers in their guilty caves:</line>
<line>And when thy car is loaden with their heads,</line>
<line>I will dismount, and by the waggon-wheel</line>
<line>Trot, like a servile footman, all day long,</line>
<line>Even from Hyperion's rising in the east</line>
<line>Until his very downfall in the sea:</line>
<line>And day by day I'll do this heavy task,</line>
<line>So thou destroy Rapine and Murder there.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>These are my ministers, and come with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Are these thy ministers? what are they call'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Rapine and Murder; therefore called so,</line>
<line>Cause they take vengeance of such kind of men.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Good Lord, how like the empress' sons they are!</line>
<line>And you, the empress! but we worldly men</line>
<line>Have miserable, mad, mistaking eyes.</line>
<line>O sweet Revenge, now do I come to thee;</line>
<line>And, if one arm's embracement will content thee,</line>
<line>I will embrace thee in it by and by.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit above</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>This closing with him fits his lunacy</line>
<line>Whate'er I forge to feed his brain-sick fits,</line>
<line>Do you uphold and maintain in your speeches,</line>
<line>For now he firmly takes me for Revenge;</line>
<line>And, being credulous in this mad thought,</line>
<line>I'll make him send for Lucius his son;</line>
<line>And, whilst I at a banquet hold him sure,</line>
<line>I'll find some cunning practise out of hand,</line>
<line>To scatter and disperse the giddy Goths,</line>
<line>Or, at the least, make them his enemies.</line>
<line>See, here he comes, and I must ply my theme.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter TITUS below</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Long have I been forlorn, and all for thee:</line>
<line>Welcome, dread Fury, to my woful house:</line>
<line>Rapine and Murder, you are welcome too.</line>
<line>How like the empress and her sons you are!</line>
<line>Well are you fitted, had you but a Moor:</line>
<line>Could not all hell afford you such a devil?</line>
<line>For well I wot the empress never wags</line>
<line>But in her company there is a Moor;</line>
<line>And, would you represent our queen aright,</line>
<line>It were convenient you had such a devil:</line>
<line>But welcome, as you are. What shall we do?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>What wouldst thou have us do, Andronicus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Show me a murderer, I'll deal with him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Show me a villain that hath done a rape,</line>
<line>And I am sent to be revenged on him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Show me a thousand that have done thee wrong,</line>
<line>And I will be revenged on them all.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Look round about the wicked streets of Rome;</line>
<line>And when thou find'st a man that's like thyself.</line>
<line>Good Murder, stab him; he's a murderer.</line>
<line>Go thou with him; and when it is thy hap</line>
<line>To find another that is like to thee,</line>
<line>Good Rapine, stab him; he's a ravisher.</line>
<line>Go thou with them; and in the emperor's court</line>
<line>There is a queen, attended by a Moor;</line>
<line>Well mayst thou know her by thy own proportion,</line>
<line>for up and down she doth resemble thee:</line>
<line>I pray thee, do on them some violent death;</line>
<line>They have been violent to me and mine.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Well hast thou lesson'd us; this shall we do.</line>
<line>But would it please thee, good Andronicus,</line>
<line>To send for Lucius, thy thrice-valiant son,</line>
<line>Who leads towards Rome a band of warlike Goths,</line>
<line>And bid him come and banquet at thy house;</line>
<line>When he is here, even at thy solemn feast,</line>
<line>I will bring in the empress and her sons,</line>
<line>The emperor himself and all thy foes;</line>
<line>And at thy mercy shalt they stoop and kneel,</line>
<line>And on them shalt thou ease thy angry heart.</line>
<line>What says Andronicus to this device?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Marcus, my brother! 'tis sad Titus calls.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Enter MARCUS</para>
<line>Go, gentle Marcus, to thy nephew Lucius;</line>
<line>Thou shalt inquire him out among the Goths:</line>
<line>Bid him repair to me, and bring with him</line>
<line>Some of the chiefest princes of the Goths;</line>
<line>Bid him encamp his soldiers where they are:</line>
<line>Tell him the emperor and the empress too</line>
<line>Feast at my house, and he shall feast with them.</line>
<line>This do thou for my love; and so let him,</line>
<line>As he regards his aged father's life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>This will I do, and soon return again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Now will I hence about thy business,</line>
<line>And take my ministers along with me.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Nay, nay, let Rape and Murder stay with me;</line>
<line>Or else I'll call my brother back again,</line>
<line>And cleave to no revenge but Lucius.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside to her sons</phrase>  What say you, boys? will you</line>
<line>bide with him,</line>
<line>Whiles I go tell my lord the emperor</line>
<line>How I have govern'd our determined jest?</line>
<line>Yield to his humour, smooth and speak him fair,</line>
<line>And tarry with him till I turn again.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line><phrase role="stagedir">Aside</phrase>  I know them all, though they suppose me mad,</line>
<line>And will o'erreach them in their own devices:</line>
<line>A pair of cursed hell-hounds and their dam!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">DEMETRIUS</speaker>
<line>Madam, depart at pleasure; leave us here.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Farewell, Andronicus: Revenge now goes</line>
<line>To lay a complot to betray thy foes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>I know thou dost; and, sweet Revenge, farewell.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit TAMORA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Tell us, old man, how shall we be employ'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Tut, I have work enough for you to do.</line>
<line>Publius, come hither, Caius, and Valentine!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter PUBLIUS and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PUBLIUS</speaker>
<line>What is your will?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Know you these two?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PUBLIUS</speaker>
<line>The empress' sons, I take them, Chiron and Demetrius.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Fie, Publius, fie! thou art too much deceived;</line>
<line>The one is Murder, Rape is the other's name;</line>
<line>And therefore bind them, gentle Publius.</line>
<line>Caius and Valentine, lay hands on them.</line>
<line>Oft have you heard me wish for such an hour,</line>
<line>And now I find it; therefore bind them sure,</line>
<line>And stop their mouths, if they begin to cry.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exit</para>
<para role="stagedir">PUBLIUS, &amp;c. lay hold on CHIRON and DEMETRIUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">CHIRON</speaker>
<line>Villains, forbear! we are the empress' sons.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">PUBLIUS</speaker>
<line>And therefore do we what we are commanded.</line>
<line>Stop close their mouths, let them not speak a word.</line>
<line>Is he sure bound? look that you bind them fast.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter TITUS, with LAVINIA; he bearing a knife,
and she a basin</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Come, come, Lavinia; look, thy foes are bound.</line>
<line>Sirs, stop their mouths, let them not speak to me;</line>
<line>But let them hear what fearful words I utter.</line>
<line>O villains, Chiron and Demetrius!</line>
<line>Here stands the spring whom you have stain'd with mud,</line>
<line>This goodly summer with your winter mix'd.</line>
<line>You kill'd her husband, and for that vile fault</line>
<line>Two of her brothers were condemn'd to death,</line>
<line>My hand cut off and made a merry jest;</line>
<line>Both her sweet hands, her tongue, and that more dear</line>
<line>Than hands or tongue, her spotless chastity,</line>
<line>Inhuman traitors, you constrain'd and forced.</line>
<line>What would you say, if I should let you speak?</line>
<line>Villains, for shame you could not beg for grace.</line>
<line>Hark, wretches! how I mean to martyr you.</line>
<line>This one hand yet is left to cut your throats,</line>
<line>Whilst that Lavinia 'tween her stumps doth hold</line>
<line>The basin that receives your guilty blood.</line>
<line>You know your mother means to feast with me,</line>
<line>And calls herself Revenge, and thinks me mad:</line>
<line>Hark, villains! I will grind your bones to dust</line>
<line>And with your blood and it I'll make a paste,</line>
<line>And of the paste a coffin I will rear</line>
<line>And make two pasties of your shameful heads,</line>
<line>And bid that strumpet, your unhallow'd dam,</line>
<line>Like to the earth swallow her own increase.</line>
<line>This is the feast that I have bid her to,</line>
<line>And this the banquet she shall surfeit on;</line>
<line>For worse than Philomel you used my daughter,</line>
<line>And worse than Progne I will be revenged:</line>
<line>And now prepare your throats. Lavinia, come,</line>
<para role="stagedir">He cuts their throats</para>
<line>Receive the blood: and when that they are dead,</line>
<line>Let me go grind their bones to powder small</line>
<line>And with this hateful liquor temper it;</line>
<line>And in that paste let their vile heads be baked.</line>
<line>Come, come, be every one officious</line>
<line>To make this banquet; which I wish may prove</line>
<line>More stern and bloody than the Centaurs' feast.</line>
<line>So, now bring them in, for I'll play the cook,</line>
<line>And see them ready 'gainst their mother comes.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt, bearing the dead bodies</para>
</section>

<section role="scene"><title>SCENE III.  Court of TITUS's house. A banquet set out.</title>
<para role="stagedir">Enter LUCIUS, MARCUS, and Goths, with AARON prisoner</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Uncle Marcus, since it is my father's mind</line>
<line>That I repair to Rome, I am content.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">First Goth</speaker>
<line>And ours with thine, befall what fortune will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Good uncle, take you in this barbarous Moor,</line>
<line>This ravenous tiger, this accursed devil;</line>
<line>Let him receive no sustenance, fetter him</line>
<line>Till he be brought unto the empress' face,</line>
<line>For testimony of her foul proceedings:</line>
<line>And see the ambush of our friends be strong;</line>
<line>I fear the emperor means no good to us.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>Some devil whisper curses in mine ear,</line>
<line>And prompt me, that my tongue may utter forth</line>
<line>The venomous malice of my swelling heart!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Away, inhuman dog! unhallow'd slave!</line>
<line>Sirs, help our uncle to convey him in.</line>
<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Goths, with AARON. Flourish within</para>
<line>The trumpets show the emperor is at hand.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Enter SATURNINUS and TAMORA, with AEMILIUS,
Tribunes, Senators, and others</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>What, hath the firmament more suns than one?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>What boots it thee to call thyself a sun?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Rome's emperor, and nephew, break the parle;</line>
<line>These quarrels must be quietly debated.</line>
<line>The feast is ready, which the careful Titus</line>
<line>Hath ordain'd to an honourable end,</line>
<line>For peace, for love, for league, and good to Rome:</line>
<line>Please you, therefore, draw nigh, and take your places.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Marcus, we will.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Hautboys sound. The Company sit down at table</para>
<para role="stagedir">Enter TITUS dressed like a Cook, LAVINIA veiled,
Young LUCIUS, and others. TITUS places the dishes
on the table</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Welcome, my gracious lord; welcome, dread queen;</line>
<line>Welcome, ye warlike Goths; welcome, Lucius;</line>
<line>And welcome, all: although the cheer be poor,</line>
<line>'Twill fill your stomachs; please you eat of it.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Why art thou thus attired, Andronicus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Because I would be sure to have all well,</line>
<line>To entertain your highness and your empress.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>We are beholding to you, good Andronicus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>An if your highness knew my heart, you were.</line>
<line>My lord the emperor, resolve me this:</line>
<line>Was it well done of rash Virginius</line>
<line>To slay his daughter with his own right hand,</line>
<line>Because she was enforced, stain'd, and deflower'd?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>It was, Andronicus.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Your reason, mighty lord?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Because the girl should not survive her shame,</line>
<line>And by her presence still renew his sorrows.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>A reason mighty, strong, and effectual;</line>
<line>A pattern, precedent, and lively warrant,</line>
<line>For me, most wretched, to perform the like.</line>
<line>Die, die, Lavinia, and thy shame with thee;</line>
<para role="stagedir">Kills LAVINIA</para>
<line>And, with thy shame, thy father's sorrow die!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>What hast thou done, unnatural and unkind?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Kill'd her, for whom my tears have made me blind.</line>
<line>I am as woful as Virginius was,</line>
<line>And have a thousand times more cause than he</line>
<line>To do this outrage: and it now is done.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>What, was she ravish'd? tell who did the deed.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Will't please you eat? will't please your</line>
<line>highness feed?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TAMORA</speaker>
<line>Why hast thou slain thine only daughter thus?</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Not I; 'twas Chiron and Demetrius:</line>
<line>They ravish'd her, and cut away her tongue;</line>
<line>And they, 'twas they, that did her all this wrong.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Go fetch them hither to us presently.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Why, there they are both, baked in that pie;</line>
<line>Whereof their mother daintily hath fed,</line>
<line>Eating the flesh that she herself hath bred.</line>
<line>'Tis true, 'tis true; witness my knife's sharp point.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Kills TAMORA</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">SATURNINUS</speaker>
<line>Die, frantic wretch, for this accursed deed!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Kills TITUS</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Can the son's eye behold his father bleed?</line>
<line>There's meed for meed, death for a deadly deed!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Kills SATURNINUS. A great tumult. LUCIUS, MARCUS,
and others go up into the balcony</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>You sad-faced men, people and sons of Rome,</line>
<line>By uproar sever'd, like a flight of fowl</line>
<line>Scatter'd by winds and high tempestuous gusts,</line>
<line>O, let me teach you how to knit again</line>
<line>This scatter'd corn into one mutual sheaf,</line>
<line>These broken limbs again into one body;</line>
<line>Lest Rome herself be bane unto herself,</line>
<line>And she whom mighty kingdoms court'sy to,</line>
<line>Like a forlorn and desperate castaway,</line>
<line>Do shameful execution on herself.</line>
<line>But if my frosty signs and chaps of age,</line>
<line>Grave witnesses of true experience,</line>
<line>Cannot induce you to attend my words,</line>
<para role="stagedir">To LUCIUS</para>
<line>Speak, Rome's dear friend, as erst our ancestor,</line>
<line>When with his solemn tongue he did discourse</line>
<line>To love-sick Dido's sad attending ear</line>
<line>The story of that baleful burning night</line>
<line>When subtle Greeks surprised King Priam's Troy,</line>
<line>Tell us what Sinon hath bewitch'd our ears,</line>
<line>Or who hath brought the fatal engine in</line>
<line>That gives our Troy, our Rome, the civil wound.</line>
<line>My heart is not compact of flint nor steel;</line>
<line>Nor can I utter all our bitter grief,</line>
<line>But floods of tears will drown my oratory,</line>
<line>And break my utterance, even in the time</line>
<line>When it should move you to attend me most,</line>
<line>Lending your kind commiseration.</line>
<line>Here is a captain, let him tell the tale;</line>
<line>Your hearts will throb and weep to hear him speak.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Then, noble auditory, be it known to you,</line>
<line>That cursed Chiron and Demetrius</line>
<line>Were they that murdered our emperor's brother;</line>
<line>And they it were that ravished our sister:</line>
<line>For their fell faults our brothers were beheaded;</line>
<line>Our father's tears despised, and basely cozen'd</line>
<line>Of that true hand that fought Rome's quarrel out,</line>
<line>And sent her enemies unto the grave.</line>
<line>Lastly, myself unkindly banished,</line>
<line>The gates shut on me, and turn'd weeping out,</line>
<line>To beg relief among Rome's enemies:</line>
<line>Who drown'd their enmity in my true tears.</line>
<line>And oped their arms to embrace me as a friend.</line>
<line>I am the turned forth, be it known to you,</line>
<line>That have preserved her welfare in my blood;</line>
<line>And from her bosom took the enemy's point,</line>
<line>Sheathing the steel in my adventurous body.</line>
<line>Alas, you know I am no vaunter, I;</line>
<line>My scars can witness, dumb although they are,</line>
<line>That my report is just and full of truth.</line>
<line>But, soft! methinks I do digress too much,</line>
<line>Citing my worthless praise: O, pardon me;</line>
<line>For when no friends are by, men praise themselves.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Now is my turn to speak. Behold this child:</line>
<para role="stagedir">Pointing to the Child in the arms of an Attendant</para>
<line>Of this was Tamora delivered;</line>
<line>The issue of an irreligious Moor,</line>
<line>Chief architect and plotter of these woes:</line>
<line>The villain is alive in Titus' house,</line>
<line>And as he is, to witness this is true.</line>
<line>Now judge what cause had Titus to revenge</line>
<line>These wrongs, unspeakable, past patience,</line>
<line>Or more than any living man could bear.</line>
<line>Now you have heard the truth, what say you, Romans?</line>
<line>Have we done aught amiss,--show us wherein,</line>
<line>And, from the place where you behold us now,</line>
<line>The poor remainder of Andronici</line>
<line>Will, hand in hand, all headlong cast us down.</line>
<line>And on the ragged stones beat forth our brains,</line>
<line>And make a mutual closure of our house.</line>
<line>Speak, Romans, speak; and if you say we shall,</line>
<line>Lo, hand in hand, Lucius and I will fall.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AEMILIUS</speaker>
<line>Come, come, thou reverend man of Rome,</line>
<line>And bring our emperor gently in thy hand,</line>
<line>Lucius our emperor; for well I know</line>
<line>The common voice do cry it shall be so.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All</speaker>
<line>Lucius, all hail, Rome's royal emperor!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Go, go into old Titus' sorrowful house,</line>
<para role="stagedir">To Attendants</para>
<line>And hither hale that misbelieving Moor,</line>
<line>To be adjudged some direful slaughtering death,</line>
<line>As punishment for his most wicked life.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt Attendants</para>
<para role="stagedir">LUCIUS, MARCUS, and the others descend</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">All</speaker>
<line>Lucius, all hail, Rome's gracious governor!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Thanks, gentle Romans: may I govern so,</line>
<line>To heal Rome's harms, and wipe away her woe!</line>
<line>But, gentle people, give me aim awhile,</line>
<line>For nature puts me to a heavy task:</line>
<line>Stand all aloof: but, uncle, draw you near,</line>
<line>To shed obsequious tears upon this trunk.</line>
<line>O, take this warm kiss on thy pale cold lips,</line>
<para role="stagedir">Kissing TITUS</para>
<line>These sorrowful drops upon thy blood-stain'd face,</line>
<line>The last true duties of thy noble son!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
<line>Tear for tear, and loving kiss for kiss,</line>
<line>Thy brother Marcus tenders on thy lips:</line>
<line>O were the sum of these that I should pay</line>
<line>Countless and infinite, yet would I pay them!</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Come hither, boy; come, come, and learn of us</line>
<line>To melt in showers: thy grandsire loved thee well:</line>
<line>Many a time he danced thee on his knee,</line>
<line>Sung thee asleep, his loving breast thy pillow:</line>
<line>Many a matter hath he told to thee,</line>
<line>Meet and agreeing with thine infancy;</line>
<line>In that respect, then, like a loving child,</line>
<line>Shed yet some small drops from thy tender spring,</line>
<line>Because kind nature doth require it so:</line>
<line>Friends should associate friends in grief and woe:</line>
<line>Bid him farewell; commit him to the grave;</line>
<line>Do him that kindness, and take leave of him.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">Young LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>O grandsire, grandsire! even with all my heart</line>
<line>Would I were dead, so you did live again!</line>
<line>O Lord, I cannot speak to him for weeping;</line>
<line>My tears will choke me, if I ope my mouth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Re-enter Attendants with AARON</para>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AEMILIUS</speaker>
<line>You sad Andronici, have done with woes:</line>
<line>Give sentence on this execrable wretch,</line>
<line>That hath been breeder of these dire events.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Set him breast-deep in earth, and famish him;</line>
<line>There let him stand, and rave, and cry for food;</line>
<line>If any one relieves or pities him,</line>
<line>For the offence he dies. This is our doom:</line>
<line>Some stay to see him fasten'd in the earth.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">AARON</speaker>
<line>O, why should wrath be mute, and fury dumb?</line>
<line>I am no baby, I, that with base prayers</line>
<line>I should repent the evils I have done:</line>
<line>Ten thousand worse than ever yet I did</line>
<line>Would I perform, if I might have my will;</line>
<line>If one good deed in all my life I did,</line>
<line>I do repent it from my very soul.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<dialogue role="speech"><linegroup>
<speaker role="speaker">LUCIUS</speaker>
<line>Some loving friends convey the emperor hence,</line>
<line>And give him burial in his father's grave:</line>
<line>My father and Lavinia shall forthwith</line>
<line>Be closed in our household's monument.</line>
<line>As for that heinous tiger, Tamora,</line>
<line>No funeral rite, nor man m mourning weeds,</line>
<line>No mournful bell shall ring her burial;</line>
<line>But throw her forth to beasts and birds of prey:</line>
<line>Her life was beast-like, and devoid of pity;</line>
<line>And, being so, shall have like want of pity.</line>
<line>See justice done on Aaron, that damn'd Moor,</line>
<line>By whom our heavy haps had their beginning:</line>
<line>Then, afterwards, to order well the state,</line>
<line>That like events may ne'er it ruinate.</line>
</linegroup></dialogue>

<para role="stagedir">Exeunt</para>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>