<?xml version="1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="user.guide"><title>DocBook XSL: The Incomplete Sample</title><info><title>DocBook XSL: The Incomplete Sample</title><author><personname>
                <firstname>Bob</firstname>
                <surname>Stayton</surname>
            </personname></author><publishername>Sagehill Enterprises</publishername><copyright><year>2002</year><year>2003</year><year>2004</year><year>2005</year><year>2006</year><year>2007</year><holder>Sagehill
Enterprises</holder></copyright><biblioid class="isbn">ISBN: 978-0-9741521-3-4</biblioid><edition>Fourth</edition><pubdate>September, 2007</pubdate><releaseinfo>A PDF version of this document is available for purchase
from <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sagehill.net">Sagehill Enterprises</link>.
</releaseinfo><legalnotice><para>All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic or mechanical, including photocopying, recording, or by any information storage and retrieval system, without written permission from the publisher, except for the inclusion of brief quotations in a review.</para></legalnotice><legalnotice><title>Warning and Disclaimer</title><para>Every effort has been made to make this book as complete and accurate as possible, but Sagehill Enterprises makes no warranties, either express or implied, regarding the content or its fitness for any particular purpose.  The information is provided on an as-is basis. The author and Sagehill Enterprises shall have neither liability nor responsibility to any person or entity with respect to any loss or damages arising from the information contained in this book.</para><para>This guide contains links to third-party Web sites that are not under the control of Sagehill Enterprises, and Sagehill Enterprises and the author are not responsible for the content of any linked site. If you access a third-party website mentioned in this guide, then you do so at your own risk. Sagehill Enterprises provides these links only as a convenience, and the inclusion of the link does not imply that Sagehill Enterprises or the author endorses or accepts any responsibility for the content of those third-party sites.</para></legalnotice><legalnotice><title>Trademarks</title><para>All terms mentioned in this book that are known to be trademarks or service marks have been appropriately capitalized. Use of a term in this book should not be regarded as affecting the validity of any trademark or service mark.</para></legalnotice><publisher><publishername>Sagehill
Enterprises</publishername><address><street>PO Box 2911</street>
<city>Santa Cruz</city> <state>CA</state>
<postcode>95063-2911</postcode>
<otheraddr>Website: 
<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.sagehill.net"/></otheraddr>
<email>info@sagehill.net</email></address></publisher></info><preface xml:id="preface"><info><title>Preface</title></info><para>The nature of publishing has changed so much over the last twenty years that anybody
    can be a publisher these days. Now you can reach a world-wide audience by putting a few
    HTML pages up on your website. Or you can use desktop publishing software to produce
    beautifully typeset material that can be printed on demand or downloaded to a printer
    anywhere in the world. With DocBook, you can publish both ways from the same source
    material.</para><section xml:id="WhatIsDocbook"><info><title>What is DocBook?</title></info><para>DocBook is a collection of standards and tools for technical publishing. DocBook
        was originally created by a consortium of software companies as a standard for
        computer documentation. But the basic <quote>book</quote> features of DocBook can be
        used for other kinds of content, so it has been adapted to many purposes.</para><para>The core DocBook standard is the <glossterm>DocBook Document Type Definition
            (DTD)</glossterm> maintained by the DocBook Technical Committee in <indexterm><primary>OASIS</primary></indexterm><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook">OASIS</link>. The DTD
        defines the vocabulary of content elements that an author can use and how they
        relate to each other. For example, a <literal>book</literal> element can contain a
            <literal>title</literal> element, any number of <literal>para</literal> elements
        for paragraphs, and any number of <literal>chapter</literal> elements. Using the DTD
        and XML syntax, authors mark up their text content with tag names enclosed in angle
        brackets like <literal>&lt;chapter&gt;</literal>. The markup is similar to
        HTML, but with more tags and tighter rules.</para><para>Text that is marked up in this standard way can be processed by any number of
        software tools. A major advantage of DocBook is the availability of DocBook tools
        from many sources, not just from a single vendor of a proprietary file format. You
        can mix and match components for editing, typesetting, version control, and HTML
        conversion. You can assemble a custom system that is well suited to your needs, and
        many of the components are available for free.</para><para>The other major advantage of DocBook is the set of free stylesheets that are
        available for it. Written by Norman Walsh in the Extensible Stylesheet Language
        (XSL), these stylesheets enable anyone to publish their DocBook content in print and
        HTML. The stylesheets are now developed and maintained as an open-source project on
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook">SourceForge</link><indexterm><primary>SourceForge</primary></indexterm>. An active community of users and contributors keeps up the development
        of the stylesheets and answers questions.</para><para>As a publishing system, DocBook is best suited for any of these situations:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Large quantities of content.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Highly structured content.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Content that needs to be interchanged among otherwise incompatible
                systems.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Content that needs automated batch processing.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Content to be rendered in multiple output forms and versions.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>DocBook is not a WYSIWYG word processor (although graphical editors are available
        for DocBook). DocBook is hardly worth the trouble for short or one-off documents.
        And since the formatting is strictly by batch process with stylesheets, DocBook is
        not well matched to highly designed layout-driven content like magazines.</para><para>DocBook is well suited to any collection of technical documentation that is
        regularly maintained and published. Because you are not locked into a single vendor,
        you have flexibility in your choice of processes and tools, both now and in the
        future. Multiple authors can contribute, and their content can easily be merged
        because all the authors are using a standard markup language. The files are plain
        text, not binary, so they also work well with most version control systems.</para><para>Setting up a DocBook system will take some time and effort. But the payoff will be
        an efficient, flexible, and inexpensive publishing system that can grow with your
        needs.</para></section><section xml:id="Audience"><info><title>Audience</title></info><para>This book is for people who want to publish DocBook XML files using the DocBook
        XSL stylesheets. It is a "how to" guide that gets you up and running quickly, and
        then provides the details you need to gain access to the full power of DocBook. The
        book covers:</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Obtaining and setting up XSL tools and the DocBook XSL stylesheets.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Using the built-in options to control the XSL stylesheets.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Customizing the XSL stylesheets to match your design needs.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>(This book does not cover the SGML version of DocBook, nor the DocBook DSSSL
        stylesheets.) </para><para>You do not need to be an XML expert to use DocBook XSL. You will need to know
        about XML elements and attributes, since you will be working with DocBook XML files.
        And you will need to know how to execute commands by typing them on a command line
        rather than through a point-and-click interface. If you know nothing about XSL, you
        can still use the stylesheets to generate high-quality output. You can also
        customize to a degree using the built-in stylesheet parameters. Learning some XSL
        will enable you to more fully customize the output. This book can teach you basic
        XSL, and provides dozens of examples that you can use and learn from.</para><para>This book will not show you how to write DocBook documents. The best reference for
        writing in DocBook is <citetitle>DocBook: The Definitive Guide</citetitle> by Norman
        Walsh. That book has been made available by O'Reilly Books for reading from the web
        at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://docbook.org/tdg/en/html/docbook.html"/>. Keep that link
        bookmarked for future reference. A printed and bound version of the book is also
        available from O'Reilly Books, but it is a bit out of date now. The online book
        documents the most recent version of the DTD.</para></section></preface><part xml:id="ToolsPart"><info><title>Setting up the tools</title></info><chapter xml:id="introchapter"><info><title>Introduction</title></info><para>The <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/">
                <citetitle>Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL)</citetitle>
                </link> is a formal Recommendation put forward by the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org">World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</link> as a language
        for expressing stylesheets. It complements the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/XML/">
                <citetitle>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</citetitle>
                </link> by providing the methods for formatting content written in XML. One of the
        major goals of XML was keeping content and its semantic markup separate from its
        formatting, so that formatting could be applied independently. An XSL stylesheet
        describes the formatting that can be applied to XML files using an XSL processor.
        The XSL standard and XSL processors are described more fully in <xref linkend="XSLprocessors"/>.</para><para>The DocBook XSL stylesheets were written by Norman Walsh to help people publish
        their DocBook content with XSL. The stylesheets are now an open-source project
        maintained on <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook/">SourceForge</link>. The stylesheet distribution consists of a collection of
        modular XSL files that are assembled into several complete XSL stylesheets. There is
        a stylesheet for generating a single HTML file, and one for generating multiple
        smaller HTML files from a single DocBook document. There are stylesheets for print
        output, XHTML output, HTML Help output, and JavaHelp output. The stylesheet
        collection is freely available for download. Since there are XSL processors for all
        major computer types, you can use DocBook on Unix, Linux, Windows, and Macintosh
        computers.</para><para>This book shows you how to use and customize the DocBook XSL stylesheets. It
        unlocks the power of these stylesheets by documenting all of their features and
        making them easy to use.</para><section xml:id="HowOrganized"><info><title>How this book is organized</title></info><para>Applying an XSL stylesheet to an XML file is a very straightforward process,
        once you get the tools working. <emphasis role="bold">Part I</emphasis> of this
        book tells you how to obtain and set up the XSL tools. It covers several XSL
        processors, and provides essential details for each one. It also covers XML
        Catalogs, which are used to map file references to actual directory locations on
        your system. XML Catalogs make the tools more versatile and portable.</para><para> Once you have the tools working, you can generate formatted print and HTML
        output from your DocBook XML documents. As you use the stylesheets, you will
        probably want to change certain aspects about the format or processing. The
        DocBook stylesheets provide a large number of options. The options are in the
        form of stylesheet parameters, which let you assign a value to a named variable
        that is used in the stylesheet. You can do quite a bit of customization of your
        output using just the parameters. <emphasis role="bold">Part II</emphasis> of
        this book describes the various stylesheet parameters and how to use them. </para><para>You will turn to <emphasis role="bold">Part III</emphasis> when you want to
        change something but you cannot find a parameter to do it. At that point you
        will need to do some stylesheet customization, which is done using the XSL
        language. You'll need to learn the syntax and methods of XSL, so that you can
        write a customization file with it. The chapters in Part III describe the
        methods of customization, as well as many applications for HTML and print
        output. You can use the appendix introducing XSL  to get started with XSL, but it
        is beyond the scope of this book to teach you all about XSL. You will need a
        good XSL reference book to create extensive customization. You can also use
            the appendix on debugging XSL  for help with debugging your
        customizations.</para><para><emphasis role="bold">Part IV</emphasis> of this book covers all of the
        special features of DocBook that require extra attention. That part is an
        encyclopedia of special topics, from bibliographies to websites. Use it as a
        reference when you need to process a certain feature, or browse it for new
        possibilities that you did not know DocBook could do.</para><note><title>Note on examples</title><para><indexterm><primary>backslash</primary><secondary>in examples</secondary></indexterm>Some examples of commands and code in this book are too long to
            fit on one line. Where a long line is broken to fit, the line will end with
            a backslash character "\". If you are using Microsoft Windows, you should
            omit the backslash character and join such a line to the following line. If
            you are using a Unix shell, you can use the example "as is".</para></note></section><section xml:id="OnlineResources"><info><title>Online resources for finding solutions to problems</title></info><para><indexterm><primary>online resources</primary></indexterm>If you run into problems with the DocBook XSL stylesheets that are
            not addressed anywhere in this guide, you can use a number of online resources
            to find solutions. <itemizedlist><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>mailing lists</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>docbook-apps mailing list</primary></indexterm>First try searching the archives of the <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem> mailing list for
                        keywords related to the problem. There is a good chance that someone
                        else has run into something similar. Archives of the list are
                        available at two different sites: an <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://lists.oasis-open.org/archives/docbook-apps/">archive
                            at OASIS</link> (which also hosts the actual mailing list) and
                        an <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sources.redhat.com/ml/docbook-apps/">archive
                            at Red Hat</link>.</para><para>If, for example, you are seeing a specific error message, trying
                        cutting and pasting the error message (or some part of it) into the
                        search form for the mailing list archives.</para></listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>chat channel</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>IRC channel</primary></indexterm>You can get help in real time on the <systemitem role="channel">#docbook</systemitem> channel on <systemitem class="fqdomainname">irc.openprojects.net</systemitem>. If your
                        browser supports IRC URLs (or, like Mozilla, has a built-in IRC
                        client), you can access the channel by entering the following URL in
                        your browser: <blockquote><simpara> <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="irc://irc.openprojects.net#docbook"/> </simpara></blockquote>
                    </para></listitem><listitem><para>If you cannot find a solution in the <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem> or on the
                            <systemitem role="channel">#docbook</systemitem>, you should try
                        posting a question to <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem>. To subscribe to the list, send a
                        message from your email account to: <blockquote><simpara> <email>docbook-apps-subscribe@lists.oasis-open.org</email> </simpara></blockquote> To post a message to the list, send it to: <blockquote><simpara>
                    <email>docbook-apps@lists.oasis-open.org</email> </simpara></blockquote>
                    </para><para>Please read the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/mailinglist/guidelines.html">list guidelines</link> first, and to include examples of your
                        DocBook source document and your output (for example, HTML or FO
                        output) along with details about the tools you're using (including
                        version numbers of the tools). <note><simpara>Do not include attachments when you post to <systemitem role="mailinglist">docbook-apps</systemitem>—the mailing
                                list management software automatically strips out
                                attachments. If you have a long example or an output format
                                that you cannot paste into your message, post it to a Web
                                site, and then include the URL in your message to the
                                list.</simpara></note> </para></listitem><listitem><para>The <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://wiki.docbook.org">DocBook Wiki</link>
                        website collects contributions from DocBook users and makes them
                        available to the world.</para></listitem><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>SourceForge</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>DocBook</primary><secondary>SourceForge</secondary></indexterm>If you find something that seems to be a legitimate bug
                        in the DocBook XSL stylesheets, you can file a bug report from the
                            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=21935">Tracker page</link> at the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/docbook/">DocBook Open
                            Repository</link> site at SourceForge. If instead you want to
                        request an enhancement to the stylesheets, file a <emphasis>feature
                            request</emphasis> from the same Tracker page at the SourceForge
                        site. <note><simpara>You will need to have a SourceForge user account to
                                file a bug report or feature request. This requirement makes
                                it easier follow up on bug reports. If the DocBook XSL
                                stylesheet developers need to get more details about a
                                specific bug report, it's difficult to follow up on it if it
                                was submitted anonymously.</simpara><simpara>You can <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/account/registration">register for an account</link> at the SourceForge
                                site.</simpara></note> </para></listitem></itemizedlist> </para></section></chapter><chapter xml:id="XSLprocessors"><info><title>XSL processors</title></info><para><indexterm><primary>XSL</primary><secondary>processors</secondary></indexterm>An <emphasis>XSL processor</emphasis> is the software that transforms an
        XML file into formatted output. There is a growing list of XSL processors to choose
        from. Each tool implements parts or all of the XSL standard, which actually has
        several components: <variablelist><title>The XSL Standards</title><varlistentry><term>Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL)</term><listitem><para>A language for expressing stylesheets written in XML. It includes
                        the XSL formatting objects (XSL-FO) language, but refers to separate
                        documents for the transformation language and the path
                        language.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XSL Transformation (XSLT)</term><listitem><para>The part of XSL for transforming XML documents into other XML
                        documents, HTML, or text. It can be used to rearrange the content
                        and generate new content.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XML Path Language (XPath)</term><listitem><para>A language for addressing parts of an XML document. It is used to
                        find the parts of your document to apply different styles to. All
                        XSL processors use this component.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist></para><para>To publish HTML from your XML documents, you just need an XSLT processor. It will include the XPath
        language since that is used extensively in XSLT. To get to print, you need an XSLT
        processor to produce an intermediate formatting objects (FO) file, and then you need
        an XSL-FO processor to produce
        PostScript or PDF output from the FO file. A diagram of the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://nwalsh.com/docbook/procdiagram/index.html">DocBook Publishing
            Model</link> <indexterm><primary>publishing model</primary></indexterm>is available if you want to see how all the components flow
        together.</para><section xml:id="XSLTprocessors"><info><title>XSLT processors</title></info><para><indexterm><primary>XSLT processor</primary></indexterm>Currently there are three processors that are widely used for XSLT
        processing because they most closely conform to the XSLT specification: <variablelist><varlistentry><term>Saxon</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Saxon</primary></indexterm>Saxon (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://saxon.sourceforge.net/"/>)
                        was written by Michael Kay, the author of <citetitle>XSLT
                            Reference</citetitle>, one of the best books on XSLT. Saxon
                        is a free processor written in Java, so it can be run on any
                        operating system with a modern Java interpreter. Saxon now comes
                        in two flavors: Saxon 6 which handles the XSLT 1.0 standard, and
                        Saxon 8 which handles the newly emerging XSLT 2.0 and other new
                        XML standards.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Xalan</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Xalan</primary></indexterm>Xalan (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/index.html"/>) is part of
                        the Apache XML Project. It has versions written in both Java and
                        C++, both of them free. The Java version is described in this
                        book because it is highly portable and easier to set up.
                        Generally Xalan is used with the Xerces XML parser, also
                        available from the Apache XML Project.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>xsltproc</term><listitem><indexterm><primary>xsltproc</primary></indexterm><para>The xsltproc (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xmlsoft.org/XSLT/"/>)
                        processor is written in C by Daniel Veillard. It is free, as
                        part of the open source libxml2 library from the Gnome
                        development project. It is considered the fastest of the
                        processors, and is highly conformant to the specification. It is
                        much faster than either of the Java processors. It also
                        processes XIncludes.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist></para><para>There are a few other XSLT processors that should also be mentioned: <variablelist><varlistentry><term>XT</term><listitem><para>James Clark's XT (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.blnz.com/xt/index.html"/>) was the first
                        useful XSLT engine, and it is still in use. It is written in
                        Java, so it runs on many platforms, and it is free. XT comes
                        with James Clark's nonvalidating parser XP, but you can
                        substitute a different Java parser.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>MSXML</term><listitem><para>Microsoft's MSXML (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/xml/"/>) engine includes an XSLT processor. It is reported to be
                        fast, but only runs on Windows.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Sablotron</term><listitem><para>Sablotron (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.gingerall.com/charlie/ga/xml/p_sab.xml"/>),
                        written in C++, from Ginger Alliance.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>4XSLT</term><listitem><para>4XSLT (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/foursuite/"/>), written in Python, now an open project on
                        SourceForge.</para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist></para></section><section xml:id="FOprocessors"><info><title>XSL-FO processors</title></info><para><indexterm><primary>XSL-FO processor</primary></indexterm>XSL-FO processors are really typesetting engines. An XSL-FO file is
        a mixture of text from your XML source document and XSL-FO tags that suggest how
        the text should be formatted. It is the XSL-FO processor that actually creates
        the typeset lines of text and lays them out on pages. An XSL-FO processor
        typically generates a PDF or PostScript file which can be fed to a printer to
        produce hardcopy output.</para><para>Currently there are many XSL-FO processors, but few of them have completely
        implemented the standard. There are at least three reasons for this: <itemizedlist><listitem><para>The XSL-FO standard was finalized almost two years after the XSLT
                    standard.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The XSL-FO standard is big and complicated.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Typesetting is hard.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para><para>The authors of the XSL-FO standard recognized how difficult it would be to
        implement, and so divided it into three levels of conformance: basic, extended,
        and complete. That way a processor can claim conformance to the lower
        conformance levels and produce useful output, while still be under development
        for the higher conformance levels.</para><para>Here are some of the currently available XSL-FO processors, listed in
        alphabetical order. FOP, PassiveTeX, and xmlroff are the free processors, but
        the commercial products implement more of the XSL-FO standard.</para><variablelist><varlistentry><term>E3</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>E3 FO processor</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Arbortext</primary></indexterm>High end publishing server from Arbortext, Inc. (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.arbortext.com"/>). It runs on Windows and
                    Unix.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>FOP</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>FOP</primary></indexterm>FOP is a Java-based processor available free from the
                    Apache XML Project (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xml.apache.org/fop/"/>). FOP
                    can produce usable output, but it is still under development and has
                    some limitations. </para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>PassiveTeX</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>PassiveTeX</primary></indexterm>PassiveTeX from Sebastian Rahtz (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Software/passivetex/"/>) is a free
                    XSL-FO processor based on TeX. It has fallen behind in its
                    implementation of the XSL-FO specification, and many features of
                    DocBook XSL do not work in PassiveTeX. Not recommended.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Unicorn Formatting Objects</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Unicorn Formatting Objects</primary></indexterm>A commercial product from Unicorn Enterprises SA (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.unicorn-enterprises.com"/>). Implements only a
                    subset of the XSL-FO standard. For Windows only.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XEP</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>XEP</primary></indexterm>A commercial product from RenderX <indexterm><primary>RenderX</primary></indexterm>(<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.renderx.com"/>). It is a
                    Java-based product that runs on most platforms.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>Xinc</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>Xinc FO processor</primary></indexterm>A commercial product from Lunasil LTD (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.lunasil.com/"/>). It is a Java-based product
                    that runs on Linux and Windows. </para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XML2PDF</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>XML2PDF</primary></indexterm>A commercial product from Altsoft (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.alt-soft.com/"/>). For Windows only.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term> XML Professional Publisher (XPP)</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>XPP FO processor</primary></indexterm>A high-end XML publishing environment from XyEnterprise
                        (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.xyenterprise.com/"/>). It runs on
                    Windows and Unix.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>xmlroff</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>xmlroff</primary></indexterm>xmlroff (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xmlroff.sourceforge.net/"/>)
                    is a free open source project based on libxml2 and other GNOME
                    libraries. It is written in C.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>XSL Formatter</term><listitem><para><indexterm><primary>XSL Formatter</primary><see>Antenna House</see></indexterm><indexterm><primary>Antenna House</primary></indexterm>A commercial product from Antenna House (<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.antennahouse.com"/>). It runs on Windows, Unix,
                    and Linux.</para></listitem></varlistentry><varlistentry><term>other</term><listitem><para>Other XSL-FO processors are listed on the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/">W3C's XSL information
                        page</link>. </para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist><para>A useful method for evaluating an XSL-FO processor is to review its compliance
        to the XSL-FO standard. Most processor vendors can provide a summary of which
        XSL-FO elements and properties their processor supports. Scan the list for
        features you need to see if they are supported. Such summaries are also useful
        in comparing different processors.</para></section><section xml:id="Portability"><info><title>Portability considerations</title></info><para><indexterm><primary>portability</primary></indexterm>If you need to be able to process XML files on more than one
            operating system, you need to consider how portable the XSL processors
            are.</para><itemizedlist><listitem><para>Java-based processors are highly portable, as long as each platform
                    has a modern Java interpreter. (How modern depends on the individual
                    processor and version. Check the processor's requirements list.) With
                    Saxon, Xalan-Java, FOP, and other Java-based processors, you can install
                    a few Java archives without any compiling and produce identical results
                    on Linux, Unix, Windows, and Macintosh.</para></listitem><listitem><para>Processors written in C such as xsltproc and Sablotron are less
                    portable. You need a version compiled for each platform you want to run
                    it on. Many are available in precompiled packages, such as RPMs for
                    Linux or Zip files for Windows. But the packaged versions can lag behind
                    the latest version, so you may need to compile it yourself for a given
                    platform. The C code is written to be portable, but there are always
                    issues that come up when you have to compile.</para></listitem><listitem><para>The PassiveTeX FO processor is unique in that it is written in TeX, a
                    typesetting language. TeX is also very portable, but it is currently
                    difficult to get PassiveTeX to work properly with the DocBook XSL
                    stylesheets</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Another portability consideration is file permissions. Some packages may try
            to install files into areas of a filesystem controlled by a system
            administrator. If you do not have the necessary permissions, you may not be able
            to install a given package. All of the processors can be installed elsewhere,
            but you may need to spend time figuring out how to do so.</para></section></chapter></part></book>
