<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY standard "Standard">
<!ENTITY tracker "http://sourceforge.net/tracker/">
<!ENTITY RFE "&tracker;/index.php?func=detail&amp;group_id=21935&amp;atid=384107&amp;">
]>
<article status="Working Draft">
<?dbhtml filename="docbook-svg-1.0b2.html"?>
<articleinfo>
<title>The DocBook SVG Module</title>
<productnumber>Version 1.0 Beta 2</productnumber>
<subtitle>OASIS DocBook Technical Committee</subtitle>
<authorgroup>
<editor>
  <firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname>
  <affiliation>
    <shortaffil>Sun</shortaffil>
    <orgname>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</orgname>
    <address><email>Norman.Walsh@Sun.COM</email></address>
  </affiliation>
</editor>
</authorgroup>
<pubdate>21 May 2002</pubdate>
<releaseinfo role="cvs">
$Id$
</releaseinfo>
<copyright><year>2001</year><year>2002</year>
<holder>
The Organization for the Advancement of Structured Information
Standards [OASIS]. All Rights Reserved.
</holder></copyright>
<legalnotice>
<para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to
others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published and
distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any kind,
provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are
included on all such copies and derivative works. However, this
document itself may not be modified in any way, such as by removing
the copyright notice or references to OASIS, except as needed for the
purpose of developing OASIS specifications, in which case the
procedures for copyrights defined in the OASIS Intellectual Property
Rights document must be followed, or as required to translate it into
languages other than English.</para>

<para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be
revoked by OASIS or its successors or assigns.</para>

<para>This document and the information contained herein is provided
on an <quote>AS IS</quote> basis and OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE
INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED
WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</para>
</legalnotice>

<legalnotice role="status"><title>Status of this Document</title>

<para>This is a working draft constructed by the editor. It is not
an official committee work product and may not reflect the consensus
opinion of the committee.</para>

<!--
<para>This Committee Specification was approved for publication by the
OASIS DocBook Technical Committee. It represents the
consensus of the committee. Comments on this document may be
sent to
<ulink url="mailto:docbook@lists.oasis-open.org">docbook@lists.oasis-open.org</ulink>.
</para>
-->

</legalnotice>

<abstract><title>Abstract</title>

<para>DocBook is a general purpose XML and SGML document type
particularly well suited to books and papers about computer hardware
and software. SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics) is an XML document type
designed for describing two-dimensional graphics (vector graphic
shapes, images, and text).</para>

<para>This module integrates SVG into DocBook, allowing elements from the
SVG namespace to be used in DocBook documents.</para>
</abstract>

<revhistory>
<revision role="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/svg/docbook-svg-1.0-b2.html">
  <revnumber>Beta Release 2</revnumber>
  <date>21 May 2002</date>
</revision>
</revhistory>
</articleinfo>

<section id="s.intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para><xref linkend="bib.docbook42"/>
is a general purpose XML and SGML document type particularly well
suited to books and papers about computer hardware and software
(though it is by no means limited to these applications).
</para>

<para><xref linkend="bib.svg11"/>
(Scalable Vector Graphics) is an XML document type designed for describing
two-dimensional graphics (vector graphic shapes, images, and text).</para>

<para>This module integrates SVG into DocBook, allowing elements from the
SVG namespace to be used in <sgmltag>imageobject</sgmltag>s.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="mailto:docbook-tc@oasis-open.org">DocBook
Technical Committee</ulink> maintains the DocBook schema.</para>

<para>The <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/">W3C</ulink> maintains SVG.</para>

<para>The 1.0 Beta 2 release of this module is based on the
<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/">SVG 1.1 Candidate Release</ulink>
DTD.</para>

<para>The DocBook Technical Committee welcomes bug reports and
requests for enhancement (RFEs) from the user community. The current list
of outstanding requests is available through the
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</ulink>
<ulink url="&tracker;/?atid=384107&amp;group_id=21935&amp;func=browse">tracker</ulink>
interface. This is also the preferred mechanism for submitting new requests.
Old RFEs, from a previous legacy tracking system, are
<ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/old-rfes.html">archived</ulink>
for reference.</para>

</section>

<section id="s.terminology"><title>Terminology</title>

<para>The key words <glossterm>must</glossterm>, <glossterm>must
not</glossterm>, <glossterm>required</glossterm>,
<glossterm>shall</glossterm>, <glossterm>shall not</glossterm>,
<glossterm>should</glossterm>, <glossterm>should not</glossterm>,
<glossterm>recommended</glossterm>, <glossterm>may</glossterm>, and
<glossterm>optional</glossterm> in this &standard; are to be
interpreted as described in <xref linkend="rfc2119"/>. Note that for
reasons of style, these words are not capitalized in this
document.</para>

</section>

<section id="svg-module">
<title>The DocBook SVG Module V1.0b2</title>

<para>This module integrates SVG into DocBook by incorporating the SVG
V1.1 DTD using a namespace prefix and extending the content model of
DocBook's <sgmltag>imageobject</sgmltag> element to allow those
elements to occur.</para>

<section id="usage">
<title>Usage</title>

<para>To use this module, specify the public and system identifiers of this
module in your document type declaration. For example, to use this module
to write a book, use the following document type declaration:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook SVG Module V1.0beta2//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/svg/1.0beta2/dbsvg.dtd">]]></screen>

<para>Naturally, you can include an internal subset if you wish.</para>

<para>This module declares <literal>svg:</literal> as the namespace
prefix for SVG. If you wish to change that prefix, you may declare an alternative
by changing the declaration of the parameter entity <literal>SVG.prefix</literal>.
</para>

<para>For example, to write an article using this module and to specify that
the namespace prefix for SVG elements should be <literal>s:</literal>, you could
use the following document type declaration:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook SVG Module V1.0beta2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/svg/1.0beta2/dbsvg.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % SVG.prefix "s">
]>]]></screen>

<para>To incorporate this module into a higher-level customization layer, use the
public and system identifiers of this module in your customization layer. For
example:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[<!ENTITY %docbooksvg PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook SVG Module V1.0beta2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/svg/1.0beta2/dbsvg.dtd">
%docbooksvg;]]></screen>

</section>

<section id="limitations">
<title>Limitations</title>

<para>This module is DTD-based. DTDs and <xref linkend="xml-names"/>
do not work together with perfect harmony. In particular, although you
can change the namespace prefix used for SVG diagrams on a
per-document basis, you cannot change it on a per-diagram basis. You
simply cannot use <literal>svg:</literal> as the prefix on one diagram
and <literal>s:</literal> as the prefix in another diagram within the
same document. Such a document may be well-formed, and many XML tools
may process it correctly, but it cannot be validated against this
module's DTD.</para>

<para>The SVG module overrides the declaration of the <sgmltag>imageobject</sgmltag>
element. In order to write a customization layer that also changes the declaration
of <sgmltag>imageobject</sgmltag>, that customization layer must
disable <sgmltag class="paramentity">docbook.svg.imageobject.element</sgmltag>
before including the SVG module.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="relnotes"><title>Release Notes</title>

<para>This module is a customization layer on top of DocBook XML V4.2
Candidate Release 2. The DocBook Candidate Release specification may
change without warning. This module will not (can not) be published in
final form until DocBook V4.2 is officially published.</para>

<para>This module is currently based on the
<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/">SVG 1.1 Candidate Release</ulink>
specification. The Candidate Release specification may change without
warning. This module will not (can not) be published in final form until
the SVG 1.1 Recommendation is released.</para>
</section>

<appendix id="a.committee" role="non-normative">
<title>OASIS DocBook Technical Committee</title>

<para>The following individuals were members of the committee during
the formulation of this &standard;:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Dennis Evans</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Paul Grosso (prospective)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Dick Hamilton</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Nancy (Paisner) Harrison</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sabine Ocker</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Michael Sabrio</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Michael Smith</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tim Teebken (prospective)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Norman Walsh (Chair, Editor)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</appendix>

<bibliography id="bibl"><title>References</title>

<bibliodiv><title>Normative</title>

<bibliomixed id="bib.docbook42"/>
<bibliomixed id="bib.svg11"/>
<bibliomixed id="xml-names"/>
<bibliomixed id="rfc2119"/>

</bibliodiv>

</bibliography>

</article>
